<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEC2747A623A54B2CAAE6A2D9EA1DFDDD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 10263 IH: Responsible AI Disclosure Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-11-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 10263</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20241126">November 26, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Federal financial agencies to carry out a study and report on standardized descriptions for vendor-provided artificial intelligence systems, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9507EC38F7E64F68A3BEE8987EAA0164" style="OLC"><section id="H9B52D84E71194B10ACE456FC7E0B7970" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Responsible AI Disclosure Act of 2024</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HBCA62DFF7E9443BE9F019079214A16F3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study and report on standardized description for vendor-provided artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="HE611E16C419D475A94C1CAF6B96B6166"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The heads of each covered agency may coordinate with other covered agencies and consult with other relevant Government agencies to carry out a study that—</text><paragraph id="H1D528B64BC654342A9D5967F62D43F7D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes current and recommended definitions and standards for categorizing artificial intelligence data and methodologies used to train artificial intelligence models that are commonly utilized by regulated entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52310F72A69B406090EFF0947667F697"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assesses current and recommended practices for regulated entities and vendors to identify data used to train artificial intelligence models that are utilized by regulated entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE26DE59D47BF4C94B5B4EEE02CB0620C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assesses current and recommended standards for the delineation and ratios of synthetic versus genuine data in the training of artificial intelligence models;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC014FBC2426C4E18B9E207F72D729A26"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identifies the sources of such data;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H169C13CE5BF94CE098D3D87787C7132F" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assesses how such models are designed and function, including how the data submitted to such models are incorporated and other ways in which the data is typically used; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DCCA068B3E542C3AD2B4E1C038F3960"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">examines best practices for complying with applicable Federal laws and regulations, including anti-discrimination, consumer protection, and investor protection requirements with respect to internal or vendor-provided artificial intelligence systems utilized by regulated entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3F6939517FB448E9C20478C06B71447"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of the 6-month period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the heads of each covered agency shall issue a report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate that contains—</text><paragraph id="HDC6E9077EF4B44B8B24D6177195EC060"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all findings and determinations made in carrying out the study required under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC921E62C2E5423283C743DAB25502A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations on whether Federal statutes, regulations, guidance, orders, supervisory practices, or any other administrative actions should be revised with regard to the disclosures and standardized descriptions of vendor-provided artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD54CE0685F3341939BBBB2CC1C501BD1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Existing authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the issuance of the report required under subsection (b), each covered agency shall, if the agency determines it appropriate and determines the agency has the authority to act under another provision of law, require—</text><paragraph id="H44CC942CB3B849ECA4033EF12A376F30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>regulated entities and vendors providing artificial intelligence systems to regulated entities to—</text><subparagraph id="H7B6E7EBD34E043E8B990F278DA7BFCC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>report to the covered agency—</text><clause id="H6EB49185EF184BBFA5E73CE19CF9F191"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how the entity or vendor identifies data used to train artificial intelligence models;</text></clause><clause id="H401365C58B9443B982B1DA24DC2DF7C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the delineation and ratios of synthetic versus genuine data in the training of artificial intelligence models;</text></clause><clause id="HAE8915072B2649D5BA3C34CAF8AD9559"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the sources of such data; or</text></clause><clause id="HB099FFE4506D4680BDA76F7F208B77B9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how such models are designed and function, including how the data submitted to such models are incorporated and other ways in which the data is typically used; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81E2059A3D59431B924E7D45ED53E144"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disclose all or part of the information described under subparagraph (A) to the public in such form as the covered agency determines appropriate; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB852FA39949F4BDA947CDAF926AA7E4B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">vendors seeking to provide artificial intelligence systems to regulated entities to provide the regulated entities with a standardized disclosure, as determined by the covered agency, with information described in paragraph (1)(A) for each artificial intelligence model the regulated entity seeks to utilize.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD82D42477F14FC8A91909F1E2EAE3EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that a covered agency that determines the requirements described under subsection (c) are needed should not wait to implement such requirements until after the issuance of the report under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB9CCAB8B07BA44788C5D48D0EA2F5378"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8501A3D2E37440C8983232D4CD8E4AD6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered agency</quote> means the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the National Credit Union Administration, and the Securities and Exchange Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCA5B01666E644AB8EE6CA102B520A26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulated entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a covered agency, the term <quote>regulated entity</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H7A4F18AE9C734D359A5CE4361B4BF38F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity with respect to which the covered agency is the primary financial regulatory agency (as defined under section 2 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30C29C8A93AF413CABC3C6AC6E719E1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a State credit union or a Federal credit union (as such terms are defined, respectively, under section 101 of the Federal Credit Union Act), with respect to the National Credit Union Administration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B7A124367254A33BFE4627053D649F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a covered person (as defined under section 1002 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010), with respect to the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

