<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD4A874726F2542BD866FC5ADCD5EC2AD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 8756 IH: AI Leadership To Enable Accountable Deployment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 8756</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240614">June 14, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers Council, Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers, and Artificial Intelligence Coordination Boards, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEF7A12C31111468B8664969EFBF19ED7" style="OLC"><section id="H50F9AF6AB7E5472181C96C46553743FA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>AI Leadership To Enable Accountable Deployment Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AI LEAD Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0A601A484124227B41EE4F5F5A8C7D5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HADB194755BAB4C53B94EBA458093D89F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3502 of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2431AF9BF08644DC8459C0CC1D0A84EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given the term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3BDEBBCC7E8A4BAF979593CEB747EF12"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer</header><text>The term <term>Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer</term> means an official designated by the head of an agency pursuant to section 4(b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB84F8B02A7F4458A0442613611B640D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Council</header><text>The term <term>Council</term> means the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers Council established under section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C01DE1ECB774F089D8F6E2BD44368DA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H073F39F3406B42B69F5C02B083A4DF41"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>relevant congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19C57B0BD06044D1B3592957697D5D80"><enum>3.</enum><header>Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers Council</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2BCC46C182B4E00872F9AD0DB9550B6"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director shall establish a Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers Council.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H62D814E7A9794713B30DFBD38EA16BCF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Council shall—</text><paragraph id="H024997B49B824AB1BB93E86D6ADCED12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote artificial intelligence innovation and responsible design, development, and application;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5235C752F1454FE59859698819263EFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>oversee compliance with Governmentwide requirements, including existing requirements for agencies to inventory and publish use cases of artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H774B3CEE21C545CBBC89F8A9836B6648"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop recommendations for, and advise agencies on, best practices for the design, acquisition, development, modernization, use, operation, sharing, risk management, auditing, and performance of artificial intelligence technologies while ensuring privacy, security, and the protection of civil rights and civil liberties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H333FB79027D04915A58AE95767A8B8B4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>share experiences, ideas, and promising practices, including work process redesign and the development of performance measures to optimize Federal Government use of and investments in artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3409504E76B420395B53D97DC6E61A9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in coordination with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, assess and monitor the hiring, training, classification, and professional development needs of the Federal workforce relating to artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD659262904654C2DBB6157E5D685F89A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>examine and track the costs and benefits of artificial intelligence use in the Federal Government, and make recommendations for any limits that should be placed on the acquisition, development, and use of artificial intelligence and the capabilities of artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9924799589614ADE94480FF94D4B5810"><enum>(7)</enum><text>help improve the abilities of agencies to understand artificial intelligence and intervene in crisis;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B226DB6507241D99336087A9A1C573B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>review and analyze already deployed artificial intelligence systems within the Federal Government for potential harm; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H793793F3645C4CAD928882F41B8589D0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>assist the Director, as necessary, in—</text><subparagraph id="H8D18241BA024478185D882975264A1A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying, developing, coordinating, and overseeing multi-agency projects and other initiatives to improve Government performance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D2D30F892DF492ABCB7A77909B0D577"><enum>(B)</enum><text>monitoring and managing risks relating to developing, obtaining, or using artificial intelligence, including by—</text><clause id="HAFABE8DFFDB44B84A89D3FC2F348DD1F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>promoting the development and use of efficient, common, and shared approaches to key processes that improve the delivery of services for the public;</text></clause><clause id="H2897F50BAEDC4DF78A24ABF62D667CE1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>soliciting and providing perspectives on matters of concern to the Council, as appropriate, from and to—</text><subclause id="H9526E74FF831429C95BBE7644BDADE2E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Chief Financial Officers Council;</text></subclause><subclause id="H581B77E6BF60457FB6614303EFB24D57"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Chief Human Capital Officers Council;</text></subclause><subclause id="H78FAF47D0E34489D9F6A5A769D8C7230"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the Chief Acquisition Officers Council;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5905A3FDBF7D4E2C9124681E8AAE9A83"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the Chief Information Officers Council;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA9F5D636F72F4D3495218738B622847F"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the Chief Data Officers Council;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3D0E28A63AE145AC89F39017EBA17D4B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>other interagency councils;</text></subclause><subclause id="HEA38B66EDC014EC5A1DE74902B57989D"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>other key groups of the Federal Government;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF36BB11541964DA49E2A99A673B2BD98"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>industry;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE980E60B505F49C5B905CF4A2C1761DB"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>academia;</text></subclause><subclause id="HDD271969B4AB43CB939EB3524BE3492D"><enum>(X)</enum><text>State, local, Tribal, territorial, and international governments; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H29AFACA9D02843A2BE39AD1A9CAE84CD"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>other individuals and entities, as determined necessary by the Director;</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B5945DB5E9841DC8E3BC242CC2855E6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>creating a framework for how agencies can reduce risk in the design, development, and use of artificial intelligence systems; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBEAFE14DDFFA4F25968DAD3DB8FA0A69"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">implementing measurements and producing specific guidance on use cases for which the Federal Government should not be developing, procuring, or using artificial intelligence systems;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB37EB84E96D64982A249CE4F87620F78"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensuring artificial intelligence systems used and procured by agencies are and have been responsibly developed and evaluated such that the artificial intelligence systems are transparent and secure, do not infringe on privacy, and promote civil interests;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6995342621A0431BAEC08991AEE891B2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>continually monitoring the capabilities of artificial intelligence systems used and procured by the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H168DB7E9718F46A795E8CEA91B1652C3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>ensuring accountability for the use and procurement of artificial intelligence systems that result in flawed, inaccurate, or biased decisions that would impact individuals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFB86D45B381427196133DEC54DD099B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership of CAIOC</header><paragraph id="H039206F6509C4E4394836A8D2D0831E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Director shall serve as the chair of the Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H495B0981EF3F4EE4BB6A9F56913152A4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cochair</header><text>The cochair of the Council shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H79BD564A0927469A8503DB0E418AFDAE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>nominated by a majority of the members of the Council; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C17224344B24103AE339ADD84FB152E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>designated as the cochair of the Council by the Director.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50B205EC5A4B478BB5A8074DCD6AE42C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Members</header><text>Members of the Council shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HD2D2E4F887904AB0B216AF996E061BA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer of each agency described in section 901(b) of title 31, United States Code; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED16D387BDF648359B846625DC9C61A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a representative from an agency with—</text><clause id="HBC804B95CCE949669F260F9DA8F50C3C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advisory experience in scientific and technological issues that require attention at the highest level of Government; and</text></clause><clause id="H0E89DF52397E4AFD87AB3E8397DC3528"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a role working with agencies to create strategies, plans, policies and programs for science and technology, including artificial intelligence; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3DE4ACE16F44ECCB2F84974CB534B68"><enum>(C)</enum><text>other members, as determined necessary by the Director.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD53D414B1364487D8F0A371A58C5901E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Standing committees; working groups</header><text>The Council shall have the authority to establish standing committees and working groups as necessary to consider items of concern to the Council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96EA47ACA59D459F85A7C19F3937A7E5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administrative support</header><text>The Administrator of General Services shall provide administrative support for the Council. </text></subsection></section><section id="H305C1F2B4B634D2283912F900AC4ECF7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Agency artificial intelligence officers</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE5C2EBE516764AA9AC7A9841B5BFB17E"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Duties of agencies</header><text>The head of each agency shall ensure the responsible research, development, acquisition, application, governance, and use of artificial intelligence by the agency that is consistent with democratic values, including—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4ABB6839CB5424D8867D4406CC392DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">privacy;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC798172D3C2D40FB9740A5DFB3F337C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>civil rights and civil liberties;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF38CFD0F97C044A5A3F7BD72EA1B48DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>information security;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DF5FAE6420844F2A69F6587685CDBA4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>nondiscrimination;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD98EF303CF6140F3B5A38BC6D2A3BE11"><enum>(5)</enum><text>transparency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA54BB19EDB3D43A886100E69D71F1300"><enum>(6)</enum><text>trustworthiness.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBBF052FA199E4D6F9D657B1F210648B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chief artificial intelligence officer</header><paragraph id="H23720422B8E34EBE81F9B4DED5285196"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall designate a Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer with responsibility for— </text><subparagraph id="H073B3AD5D5A649EC8ED600075B6E8A2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promoting artificial intelligence innovation and use within the agency to further the agency’s effectiveness and efficiency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EADC4C4EBF4469C9FD39B7D79360831"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing input on the decision processes for annual and multi-year planning, programming, budgeting, and execution decisions, related reporting requirements, and reports relating to artificial intelligence of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87EF133FA7CA436C8BD5C965AF7213B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>participating in internal control processes or entities convened for the purpose of reviewing artificial intelligence acquisitions throughout the acquisition life cycle;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9042EC5791CB4DC892B583DECFBBD7C7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>producing a risk management plan for agency-specific use cases of artificial intelligence, including—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFC28E6570B5431A92030A439ECAEBD7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a procedure for classifying risk levels in agency use of artificial intelligence; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BBF1F98270E45D4826DDEFD61C16225"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specific guidance on use cases for which the agency should not developing, procuring, or using artificial intelligence systems;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21A7CD2773C5489AAE6D1C84241D93FF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in coordination with other responsible officials of the agency—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H761251E14D3846519D97D0372F54CD07"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assessing and addressing agency personnel requirements and professional development requirements relating to artificial intelligence; and</text></clause><clause id="HE78C9D848D324931A28287E7EAA14A73"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing and overseeing agency processes regarding the design, acquisition, development, modernization, use, data management, operation, sharing, and auditing of artificial intelligence systems by the agency, including existing requirements to inventory and publish agency use cases; </text></clause><clause id="H43B55C23635247DE9EBCFFCB06E42702"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensuring artificial intelligence policies of the agency comply with the Constitution of the United States and Governmentwide requirements;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC495B484AE9E44FE93A1B9118457E17E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring all artificial intelligence systems used and procured by the agency are and have been responsibly developed and evaluated such that the systems are transparent and secure, do not infringe on privacy, and promote civil interests;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6165AE514316406E8AF2B72BED639C45"><enum>(v)</enum><text>continually monitoring the capabilities and impacts of artificial intelligence systems used and procured by the agency; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47D5274416864D0A914DF974BF82BF13"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>ensuring accountability for the use and procurement of artificial intelligence systems that result in flawed, inaccurate, or biased decisions that would impact individuals;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD3A1CF260B048ECB4148A0C927D7B06"><enum>(F)</enum><text>helping to improve the ability of the agency to understand artificial intelligence and to intervene in crisis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2A607CF6DEB412F93EAB5E6A88C6962"><enum>(G)</enum><text>reviewing and analyzing already deployed artificial intelligence systems of the agency for potential harm; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H127F1CCE83AF494D84EE4CDA5C96757D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>performing other functions relating to artificial intelligence, as determined by the Director or the head of the agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H89AA599D79EC44C2A6D01BEE847577D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Structure</header><text>The Director shall issue guidance on the appropriate reporting structure, qualifications, and seniority level for the role of a Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3261221B6AB2419F84ABD330FBEB9DCB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Seniority</header><text>With respect to the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer of any agency described in section 901(b) of title 31, United States Code, the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer shall be an executive with a position classified above GS–15 of the General Schedule or the equivalent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D1708B37F744C0CBC695F51E38E0791"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Roles</header><text>The head of each agency shall ensure that the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer of the agency has a significant role in—</text><subparagraph id="H67449D62EBD9462C87760A9D5BCC7237"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the decision processes for all annual and multi-year planning, programming, budgeting, and execution decisions, related reporting requirements, and reports relating to artificial intelligence of the agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CF2F7A137CA495F93E9E8383DDC4D9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the management, governance, acquisition, and oversight processes of the agency relating to artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB66FE20A454436081E96FC077600ACB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Full-time employee</header><subparagraph id="H749933E3E9D34C82A884F87380BC8C61"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To the extent practicable, each Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer designated under paragraph (1) shall be a full-time employee of the agency on the date of the designation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBB3F9CE7BC74969A0705B02E19D0AC8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Justification</header><text>If the head of an agency designates a Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer of the agency who is not a full-time employee on the date of the designation, the head of the agency shall provide the Comptroller General of the United States a justification for the designation of an individual who is not a full-time employee, such as a lack of qualified personnel. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFBBE98A424884DB0A7C988A0C1ED7151"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inclusion in report</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall include each justification provided by the head of agency under subparagraph (B) in the report required under section 6(a). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6DB109D0B6B941A0A715BC05632099F5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Informing Congress</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C2299140DBC41E6A10F54BC49624F08"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">inform the relevant congressional committees of the appointment of a Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer pursuant to subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H972C1E8403FA42A1815A35DC9D95CCAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if relevant, provide to the relevant congressional committees a full description of any authorities and responsibilities of the individual serving as the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer that are performed in addition to the authorities and responsibilities of the individual in the role of the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB3EB2FC28ABA4835AD10836F6E966CBC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Agency coordination on artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="H0460865226E84357B9B3AB3FBFA49453"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director shall issue guidance directing the head of each agency described in section 901(b) of title 31, United States Code, to establish within the agency an Artificial Intelligence Coordination Board to—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60FBA6C85AA34B42B99150BD4D8594BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate artificial intelligence issues of the agency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB97F373A565B424FBE75CA9741FFF514"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent applicable to the agency, publish a statement of principles and goals relating to artificial intelligence. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H58482200A4444DF4A8DCE0314B3609D6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The guidance issued under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="HE0367DADF77244B392F87CA5CADD63FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>define the structure and activities of Artificial Intelligence Coordination Boards of agencies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE33F87B8BB524A319A597D752B0538B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that the membership of the Artificial Intelligence Coordination Board of an agency may include, to the extent applicable to the agency—</text><subparagraph id="HECFEC4C11E6048489DE5B5D866C52BB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the deputy head of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD529ACE7F0BD4249BE2F0E5AA5B208DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Chief Artificial Intelligence Officer of the agency, who shall serve as the chair of the Artificial Intelligence Coordination Board of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H814996082A4C48099354621E135FDAAF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the chief information officer of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F6DF8A217C643148E21CEBDE676188E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the chief acquisition officer of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FAED11DAB5A467499A18816E80CED16"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the senior procurement executive of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6DBA8A1D57F45689C9ADCD4C4AE41C0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the chief data officer of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBC313EEE65A452AAA43B54CD1E31274"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the chief human capital officer of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE6F1D03A9354B68A0C97EAF65087271"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the chief financial officer of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD47194204CB47729BB051F0F9FA1DA9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the senior agency official for privacy of the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06F4A1F5CA9C413690376BED17777F7C"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the senior agency official for civil rights and civil liberties of the agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB43B8A4A8F64700973222FB22500BC2"><enum>(K)</enum><text>other individuals, as determined by the Director.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8D4E831D93C43068DD5B787AB4D8D5E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Strategy</header><paragraph id="H97FF39D49809471D867C72138CB820A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The head of each agency shall establish an artificial intelligence strategy for the responsible and trustworthy adoption of artificial intelligence by the agency to better achieve the mission of the agency to serve the people of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8221F946D83D48EB8F1B2F8312F86D74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The strategy required under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H4341C2E1867F46D1B115F543FB21C6B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Defined roles and responsibilities for the use and oversight of artificial intelligence by the agency, including oversight of compliance with relevant laws, regulations, standards, and guidance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA495160E7B84467AE46D69395CA600E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Defined values, ethics, and principles to foster public trust and responsible use of artificial intelligence by the agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B1F1E2F48BC4340AFE07D4429501D75"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The standards, regulations, investments, practices, and other items the agency will use to improve trust and safety and ensure that artificial intelligence systems are designed, developed, and deployed in a manner that protects the rights and safety of individuals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2352B5CFFD94A598532BA1C93AF08CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>How the agency will oversee artificial intelligence systems and applications to identify and mitigate risk and prevent harm, including with respect to privacy, civil rights, civil liberties, and information security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7604066DD5944A938D28410EC7513DC4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The considerations and safeguards the agency will use to protect the rights and safety of the public with respect to artificial intelligence, including mitigation of algorithmic discrimination.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H455C4BC8932547AEBF411D16D03E5A5E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The domains or areas in which the agency uses or anticipates using artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4933BD9CF8A434D823890CC0B63C5B7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The steps the agency will take to strengthen workforce knowledge to maximize the value artificial intelligence can bring to mission outcomes while mitigating any associated risks.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23D9D8A2217246489C1CE619565C18E8"><enum>(H)</enum><text>How and under what conditions the agency can use artificial intelligence to improve the interactions of the agency with the public and the fulfillment of the mission of the agency, while protecting against harmful impacts on agency employees or the public.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF1ED07156D1498EB3AFC872D2F0D0FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>How the agency will coordinate and work across components, offices, and programs of the agency on artificial intelligence-related matters.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5F4406FBB7B4481A7FC31DE75C2F649"><enum>(J)</enum><text>How the agency will engage in interagency governance and coordination with respect to artificial intelligence, including to leverage shared resources, expertise, and lessons learned to better leverage artificial intelligence to improve Federal Government operations and mitigate the risks of artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0087522A6A246ABBD5F57A788C32B8D"><enum>(K)</enum><text>How the agency will promote the use and availability of data to support the artificial intelligence efforts of the agency in accordance with statutory, regulatory, and policy requirements.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13936E7558714C8F8C821756DC620BEB"><enum>(L)</enum><text>How the agency will work with the private sector to ensure that procured artificial intelligence systems or capabilities include protections to safeguard the rights and safety of individuals and to secure Federal Government data and other information.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD473F17A1A574F22A87C8A0E5F68BC89" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(M)</enum><text>An outline of specific actions to implement the strategy of the agency and desired outcomes. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H92AD3EF68CED486B8AD1B5A056CAF778"><enum>6.</enum><header>GAO reports</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B32EF24D24444FDB373EE648CD89D61"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a report on—</text><paragraph id="HD776F407A3EE497AA974EC74AC44327D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the implementation and effectiveness of Artificial Intelligence Coordination Boards established pursuant to guidance issued under section 5(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD96B79CEE01C44648AB1F8E87306FE17"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assessment of agency implementation and the effectiveness of Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B82DF5B4CA941F0BDA1CE46035626F4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations for improving the implementation and effectiveness of Artificial Intelligence Coordination Boards established pursuant to guidance issued under section 5(a) and Chief Artificial Intelligence Officers; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4669E2ABC5AF4BE7935ACD62AA90F965"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis by the Comptroller General of the United States with respect to the costs and benefits of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8061CC8FC973462DBA2702C7EA0C4E25"><enum>(A) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal implementation of artificial intelligence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H30149AA1F4894B6FA3BCCAC6B2A36E2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the activities of the Artificial Intelligence Coordination Boards established pursuant to guidance issued under section 5(a);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3012FDDBD9DC4F7DB896A877B1B1B405"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment of the extent to which select agencies appropriately consider the costs and benefits of the design, development, deployment, and continuous monitoring of artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4139B05A7454EC1BF7AC1F71C2C2032"><enum>(6)</enum><text>an assessment of jobs that could be at risk of dislocation and opportunities of other jobs with the Federal Government and the economy of the United States as a result of technological developments with respect to artificial intelligence, including potential effects on blue collar and white collar occupational categories;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10375EF48B6B49F78861BC177D4D108E"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an inventory of artificial intelligence use cases of each agency, including an assessment of how each agency protects privacy and mitigates bias in the use by the agency of artificial intelligence; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB956456AB3304C01A69F60677B85FBCB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>other relevant matters, as determined by the Comptroller General of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF9340C7C50443519A79A01B2029577C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a report on the impact of biased datasets on Federal use and implementation of artificial intelligence systems. </text></subsection></section><section id="H00E2A038DB8D4457B1E496012D41B9D8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Post-enactment guidance from the Director</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H01C84400D593491785DC4DF91735BF77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider technological and other developments, current and future requirements, and options for artificial intelligence governance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H719B6E71DA7F4931A5955506DFE38FE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">issue a directive to agencies—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48BDBA618FDE4FDD8A577745CAF40BD3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">updating leadership roles, organizational structures, and other matters relating to artificial intelligence, as determined relevant by the Director; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4FEEC5C8D2C42358BBBBB47DA02F864"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that includes an action plan and timeline for implementation. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HF31C4B35B52946A4A4632D227BFAA02F"><enum>8.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective on the date that is 90 days after the date of issuance of the directive under section 7, this Act shall have no force or effect.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

