<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BAG24E96-NLV-LN-38V" star-print="no-star-print" key="H"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S3162 RS: Testing and Evaluation Systems for Trusted Artificial Intelligence Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-12-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 722</calendar><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 3162</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20231030">October 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S409">Mr. Luján</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S253">Mr. Durbin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S303">Mr. Thune</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S396">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S323">Mr. Risch</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S422">Mr. Welch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00" added-display-style="italic" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation</committee-name></action-desc></action><action stage="Reported-in-Senate"><action-date date="20241217" legis-day="20241216">December 17 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported by <sponsor name-id="S275">Ms. Cantwell</sponsor>, with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To improve the requirement for the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology to establish testbeds to support the development and testing of trustworthy artificial intelligence systems and to improve interagency coordination in development of such testbeds, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Testing and Evaluation Systems for Trusted Artificial Intelligence Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TEST AI Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="idd939eb0df277401c8af31c89e2cb492c" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interagency coordination to facilitate testbeds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (g) of section 22A of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id12252cd091e84107ab63468d90306ab8" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><subsection id="id288c055b53004ae1b641dcaa8938a2f4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Testbeds</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id20c86ddc555c4d3b8e88aa6a7b23a1b4"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definition of artificial intelligence</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddbeacba429094331a85ad20e959074e8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In general</header><text> The Director shall, in coordination with the Secretary of Energy, the head of the interagency committee established under section 5103(a) of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413(a)</external-xref>), and such heads of such Federal agencies, private sector entities, and institutions of higher education as the head of such interagency committee considers appropriate, establish testbeds, including virtual and experimental environments, to support the development and testing of trustworthy artificial intelligence systems, including testbeds that support development of artificial intelligence guardrails, examine risks of misuse of such systems, and evaluate the vulnerabilities and conditions that may lead to failure in, malfunction of, or attacks on such systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddb7ce0d4d4ea4e6690806b8d6d1f559b"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><subparagraph id="id7de83e36d5194860aa0c0255409c5c58"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall enter into a memorandum of understanding to implement the coordination between the Secretary of Energy and the Director required by paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf8238a4cf7b046a9aac02ab5744d27f4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The memorandum shall be sufficient to ensure the Institute and other Federal agencies have access as may be necessary to the resources, personnel, and facilities at the Department of Energy, including the cross-cutting research and development programs—</text><clause id="iddc340f2df8ab4ae59c13580cc01869cc"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to advance artificial intelligence tools, systems, facilities, capabilities, and workforce needs;</text></clause><clause id="idb16433009de74ff0acb1bc40fc59cf02"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to improve the reliability and trustworthiness of artificial intelligence methods and solutions relevant to the mission of the Federal agencies conducting development or testing of artificial intelligence systems for use by the agency, or in conducting Federal oversight of commercial uses of artificial intelligence systems; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id37fb9f60ef964e9e9f4c04d5ef3d48a8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to establish testbeds, including a classified testbed as necessary, to support safeguards and systems to prevent the misuse of artificial intelligence systems, particularly in but not limited to weapons of mass destruction proliferation, undertake annual risk assessments of artificial intelligence misuse, formulate evaluation strategies, and employ testing and evaluation resources to support Federal oversight of artificial intelligence systems.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body><legis-body display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause"><section id="idade439cceb234afd817d7341179f8af7" section-type="section-one" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Testing and Evaluation Systems for Trusted Artificial Intelligence Act of 2024</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TEST AI Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id6373db707f2b4e5ab0c3ea97c2c6961f" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on establishing testbeds to support development, red-teaming, and blue-teaming of artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="idf3f5de18c95a4d8487a54693c5f4d895" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id9b6890f98186413f86f09e4140e167ec"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence blue-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence blue-teaming</term> means an effort to conduct operational vulnerability evaluations and provide mitigation techniques to entities who have a need for an independent technical review of the security posture of an artificial intelligence system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1a3318c6137e4411b2f89a604fef3b9b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence system</header><text>The term <term><added-phrase>artificial intelligence system</added-phrase></term> has the meaning given the term <quote>artificial intelligence</quote> in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id538ba5b0b12245ba88e24d4ce6eaf088"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence red-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence red-teaming</term> means structured adversarial testing efforts of an artificial intelligence system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4ee9204570684c848399c69dba6e6a55"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given such term in subsection (e) of the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8e02978ec4c34673b2e189432f4c6152"><enum>(5)</enum><header>National security</header><text>The term <term>national security</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7b96c86ea6ac4918b34f51544ebcbc49"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the protection of the United States from foreign aggression; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida32c3ca4201c40f3afa3becb15ca1eab"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not otherwise include the protection of the general welfare of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd9ef4b1ae95547cbb1d868852476c608"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means a facility or mechanism equipped for conducting rigorous and replicable testing of tools and technologies to help evaluate the functionality, performance, and security of those tools or technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idc97e552f078d449093671c08afa971b1" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot program required</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Secretary of Energy shall, in coordination with the head of the interagency committee established under section 5103(a) of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413(a)</external-xref>), private sector entities, and institutions of higher education as the Director and Secretary of Energy consider appropriate, jointly carry out a pilot program to assess the feasibility and advisability of establishing testbeds, including virtual and experimental environments, to support the development, red-teaming and blue-teaming of artificial intelligence systems.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id10145bad134d437f8ad6416357b6b6bd" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Testbeds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the pilot program required by subsection (b), the Director and the Secretary shall jointly establish one or more testbeds for the purposes described in subsection (b), including testbeds that support development of artificial intelligence standards for identifying, evaluating, and mitigating cyber, data, and network vulnerabilities that if exploited would create substantial risks to critical infrastructure or national security.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc445a84a37454d2c805320ddf8434f60" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Primary focus</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The primary focus of the pilot program required by subsection (b) shall be artificial intelligence systems used by Federal agencies or that are under evaluation for future use by Federal agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc9922e281cf9453785622bb1ae37301f" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><paragraph id="ide1ed843d0ccd48a69d9339e46c6507c1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall enter into a memorandum of understanding to implement the coordination between the Secretary of Energy and the Director required by subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8ecaa73046a3436b8764aae7cf579aa8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The memorandum of understanding entered into under paragraph (1) shall be sufficient to ensure the National Institute of Standards and Technology has such access as may be necessary to the resources, personnel, and facilities at the Department of Energy, including the cross-cutting research and development programs—</text><subparagraph id="id7fe7c1a2e386406e8a4dd6d3db069851"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to employ testing and evaluation resources to support Federal agency adoption and use of artificial intelligence systems by improving the reliability, functionality, performance, and security of artificial intelligence systems used by the Federal agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide62f775c18194a7eb5a6735519497784"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to establish testbeds, including a classified testbed as necessary, to support the testing, evaluation and development of artificial intelligence systems to identify, evaluate, and mitigate cybersecurity, data, and network vulnerabilities that if exploited would create substantial risks to critical infrastructure or national security, such as weapons of mass destruction proliferation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9b020f2e96cd4e21bf388047345fe3bb"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to support the development of testing and evaluation standards, tools, and technologies inclusive of standards, tools, and technologies for artificial intelligence red-teaming and artificial intelligence blue-teaming, for such purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9e45707f2fc6491181f9ca1bc65baf99" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the commencement of the pilot program required by subsection (b), the Director and the Secretary of Energy shall jointly develop metrics to assess the effectiveness of the pilot program in achieving the requirements set forth under subsection (e)(2).</text></subsection><subsection id="idac724ea8717a47debb03598a08dfa431" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the commencement of the pilot program required by subsection (b) and not less frequently than once each year thereafter for the duration of the pilot program, the Director and the Secretary shall jointly—</text><paragraph id="id414328104d1d4265b21b089b8fea6b55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the success of the pilot program, using the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (f); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2b39fa97b4a44f4599332c04a06340e4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress the findings of the Director and the Secretary with respect to the evaluation carried out pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6f1c06c7282442bebde6bf1d5946fc9d" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The pilot program required by subsection (b) and the memorandum of understanding entered into under subsection (e) shall both terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="id6723d1f5a2b74d3ebd4def4c477bc7b0" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Research security</header><paragraph id="id724af6cbec54427e89c8cec407b986f4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="id2550138c983e461eba59f094d331613e"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><clause id="id548e3e6312d14d888182f74b09ca0e3d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the congressional intelligence committees (as defined in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>));</text></clause><clause id="id43e11adcafc5410593c9ca5d2599d696"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></clause><clause id="id73f1b15436004b73b42c5534aec637f8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security, the Committee on Space, Science, and Technology, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc8818ec6431c4b759a546cb0fe1c00c1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Country of risk</header><text>The term <term>country of risk</term> means a country identified in the report submitted to Congress by the Director of National Intelligence in 2024 pursuant to section 108B of the National Security Act of 1947 ( <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3043b">50 U.S.C. 3043b</external-xref>) (commonly referred to as the <quote>Annual Threat Assessment</quote>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id23ed7c8297524d21bfa2645c831e3f0e"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Covered assignee; covered visitor</header><text>The terms <term>covered assignee</term> and <term>covered visitor</term> mean a foreign national from a country of risk that is <quote>engaging in competitive behavior that directly threatens U.S. national security</quote>, who is not an employee of either the Department of Energy or the management and operations contractor operating a National Laboratory on behalf of the Department of Energy, and has requested access to the premises, information, or technology of a National Laboratory.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id62a214ed0c664ea4882d7db7ceabd06f"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office of Intelligence and Counterintelligence of the Department of Energy (or their designee).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc9b380f9b18a4646a6462cca7b18dbff"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Foreign national</header><text>The term <term>foreign national</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>alien</quote> in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act ( <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbb626826d832434dbadb16cf19e44485"><enum>(F)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 ( <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id937f78b2e4d445668c14b70abc33f362"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Nontraditional collection threat</header><text>The term <term>nontraditional collection threat</term> means a threat posed by an individual not employed by a foreign intelligence service, who is seeking access to information about a capability, research, or organizational dynamics of the United States to inform a foreign adversary or non-state actor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idac363be328034ced937301cd0ce89377"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of the Senate</header><text>It is the sense of the Senate that—</text><subparagraph id="id134baf8e59774dffb5db81548a6536cd"><enum>(A)</enum><text>before being granted access to the premises, information, or technology of a National Laboratory, citizens of foreign countries identified in the 2024 Annual Threat Assessment of the intelligence community as <quote>engaging in competitive behavior that directly threatens U.S. national security</quote> should be appropriately screened by the National Laboratory to which they seek access, and by the Office of intelligence and Counterintelligence of the Department, to identify risks associated with granting the requested access to sensitive military, or dual-use technologies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide73f2eecea8e4a299f687014470ac4b5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identified risks should be mitigated.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id5afbf904eacb4fe8b4b5054942705262"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Review of country of risk covered visitor and covered assignee access requests</header><text>The Director shall, in consultation with the applicable Under Secretary of the Department of Energy that oversees the National Laboratory, or their designee, promulgate a policy to assess the counterintelligence risk that covered visitors or covered assignees pose to the research or activities undertaken at a National Laboratory.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4fb5a8763e83481e9dd7c8eb541733a6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Advice with respect to covered visitors or covered assignees</header><subparagraph id="id8fafffc4afd74ae48061655911516099"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall provide advice to a National Laboratory on covered visitors and covered assignees when 1 or more of the following conditions are present:</text><clause id="id6b3f49d0f58445dcb56ec6b67dcf9b7f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Director has reason to believe that a covered visitor or covered assignee is a nontraditional intelligence collection threat.</text></clause><clause id="id962f26a904ed41dab4f6e13f91b684eb"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Director is in receipt of information indicating that a covered visitor or covered assignee constitutes a counterintelligence risk to a National Laboratory.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4389548f08aa4bd0a06cffca46b96a45"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Advice described</header><text>Advice provided to a National Laboratory in accordance with paragraph (1) shall include a description of the assessed risk.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id68fd58ed01cb4305bd0b5c624479f427"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Risk mitigation</header><text>When appropriate, the Director shall, in consultation with the applicable Under Secretary of the Department of Energy that oversees the National Laboratory, or their designee, provide recommendations to mitigate the risk as part of the advice provided in accordance with paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id997acfc6e001456083a6a2c1e3ffe7b2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and quarterly thereafter, the Secretary of Energy shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="id4ef8cc4a0ce1435ebd973c1b00010a72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of covered visitors or covered assignees permitted to access the premises, information, or technology of each National Laboratory;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1751bd1889a24357b49c55d9e61b11ab"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of instances in which the Director provided advice to a National Laboratory in accordance with subsection (e); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1cc74a70f18b4d6896eb48179f27033d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of instances in which a National Laboratory took action inconsistent with advice provided by the Director in accordance with subsection (e). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9708f41c25f241c59c2e2f8c27d42fad" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Conforming repeal</header><text>Section 22A of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2387d8e3b8724d14978c7ec097fce638"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking subsection (g); and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6cf81b72ce9f4c3191bd97ef706925c5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (h) as subsection (g).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20241217" legis-day="20241216">December 17 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

