<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-ALL24730-X87-J4-3GL"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S4596 RS: Artificial Intelligence Public Awareness and Education Campaign Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-12-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 726</calendar><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 4596</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20240620">June 20, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S391">Mr. Young</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S353">Mr. Schatz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation</committee-name></action-desc></action><action stage="Reported-in-Senate"><action-date date="20241218" legis-day="20241216">December 18 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported by <sponsor name-id="S275">Ms. Cantwell</sponsor>, with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Commerce to conduct a public awareness and education campaign to provide information regarding the benefits of, risks relating to, and the prevalence of artificial intelligence in the daily lives of individuals in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence Public Awareness and Education Campaign Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2ce7d17a512f4512bb514bdd7ab6d89e"><enum>2.</enum><header>Artificial intelligence public awareness and education campaign</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1ca43a87cc3844a6902c25a95a045b87"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id5dc6ee607b1a4f6293faa9a1dcfb1ff7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI Campaign</header><text>The term <term>AI Campaign</term> means the public awareness and education campaign conducted under this section. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3c14422849ee4e2e90fc8290d9683040"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given the term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id423ab6a9c49047a7a9734b4b0e448a64"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>agency</term> in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id05ce60c31aed41b9afaf399109faa990"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Key performance indicator</header><text>The term <quote>key performance indicator</quote> means a quantifiable metric that demonstrates how effectively an initiative is at achieving its objectives. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcfc4f54c77194dec8af666287f3ff1b7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>relevant congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id14fe092c0299434a9771890ef6fb9b0e"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id58c9f0eb2b244236878bf2777087be7e"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id12067569b02440348546354a2d1e0550" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9eb0ef4d8a594d86b38b2c576d9fdd0b"><enum>(b)</enum><header>AI Campaign</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in coordination with the heads of relevant Federal agencies, including the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, shall conduct a public awareness and education campaign to provide information regarding the benefits of, risks relating to, and the prevalence of artificial intelligence in the daily lives of individuals in the United States.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id41af2bad2feb41b1b315228c86ed80a9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>In carrying out the AI Campaign, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5ba6845bb3f84ed3b443524119e79dde"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine the key performance indicators to evaluate the effectiveness of the AI Campaign and obtain any baseline data necessary for a comparative measurement of success; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4f4f6dc925c744808920f01cab0a6229"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate access to, and the exchange of, information regarding artificial intelligence in order to promote up-to-date knowledge regarding artificial intelligence and the rights of an individual under law with respect to artificial intelligence; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idadefe2987fe0403f9158c2172a0876f6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify, promote, and encourage the use of best practices for the detection of provenance information with respect to digital media by—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbaa015d6e56e438faa940a99a935e94e"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">including such media that is generated by human beings and such media that is generated or significantly modified by algorithms, including artificial intelligence, including media commonly referred to as <quote>deepfakes</quote> and content created by the programs commonly referred to as <quote>chatbots</quote>; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idca5bf42ec8344931aadee840155f77dc"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing resources and guidance on available tools and methods for detecting or differentiating such media; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida4dffdb4a7134a74af8d79b1d36a1c99"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identifying populations particularly susceptible to artificial intelligence-enabled fraudulent activitiy, including senior citizens, and conducting target outreach to inform such populations of, and inoculate such populations against, artificial intelligence-enabled scams and fraud; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7451307cebec4e53adb19c84df708b41"><enum>(4)</enum><text>conduct outreach to the general public relating to the prevalence of artificial intelligence in the daily lives of individuals in the United States, including—</text><subparagraph id="idbe92707fc6a5492caf28b1d90494d3f3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>applications that enable increase the productivity of individuals, such as text-to-speech functionality, real-time route planning, and predictive text suggestions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab390d1618524e06ad2b03ce26363b0a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>applications in use commercially, such as automated decision-making, fraud detection, and financial trading; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2b78639a39ba4882a474fcca0e892e62"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conduct outreach about workforce opportunities, including opportunities to work in the Federal Government, for technologists and others with experience in the development, deployment, and use of artificial intelligence, including to institutions of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)<added-phrase reported-display-style="italic">)</added-phrase>. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id350d342fec3d4380be56a655dc37438a"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expert consultation</header><text>In conducting the AI Campaign, the Secretary shall consult with a variety of stakeholders from academic or research communities, public-private partnerships, and private industry, including companies with different roles in the use of artificial intelligence, developers, deployers, users, and community development organizations with expertise working with artificial intelligence. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3a71844c674141e695aeb40a17016a0d"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id14ef6dc113b443c6ae25d44e617135e9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Secretary initiates the AI Campaign, the Secretary shall submit to the relevant congressional committees a report on the activities conducted under the AI Campaign.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide074a12b10b24bd8abb6873eba3e95c4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddb466e0c18164856a5ba2e62da80004e"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the key performance indicators determined for the purpose of evaluating the overall effectiveness of the AI Campaign; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id091e4dc942e543cabf4527bffa9dd67c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations for subsequent actions, including in any key areas in which the outcomes of the AI Campaign were identified as insufficient. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd645207c642c478db4cf5e2ff88ee6fe"><enum>(f)</enum><header>No additional funds</header><text>No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated for the purpose of carrying out this Act. </text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20241218" legis-day="20241216">December 18 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

