<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BAG23D60-NFK-F7-VGM"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 S3004 IS: To specify control and management of Department of Defense data and to establish the Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 3004</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S338">Mr. Manchin</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S381">Mr. Rounds</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To specify control and management of Department of Defense data and to establish the Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="id7e5e8caf13b34843bc5401d200e9632a" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Control and management of Department of Defense data and establishment of Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council</header><subsection id="idcbb0c72e6c8143bc922f3623b57224f4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Control and management of Department of Defense data</header><text>The Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer of the Department of Defense shall maintain the authority, but not the requirement, to access and control, on behalf of the Secretary of Defense, of all data collected, acquired, accessed, or utilized by Department of Defense components consistent with section 1513 of the James M. Inhofe National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/4001">10 U.S.C. 4001</external-xref> note).</text></subsection><subsection id="id06fac75678454f17a409b6df1db7aa75"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council</header><text>Section 238(d) of the John S. McCain National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/232">Public Law 115–232</external-xref>; 10 U.S.C. note prec. 4061) is amended by striking paragraph (3) and inserting the following new paragraph (3):</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idE733983D5716458C8C71F2746A12A263"><paragraph id="id2e1c85c57e6341b28e426a533007d7b5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0116beb115d84d089a4ed5c8be57927d"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="id9c06793e614746f8b3d3b3443ef365ab"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish a council to provide policy oversight to ensure the responsible, coordinated, and ethical employment of data and artificial intelligence capabilities across Department of Defense missions and operations.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd2141b5e585d40f78c4d3192088aec7f" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The council established pursuant to clause (i) shall be known as the <quote>Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer Governing Council</quote> (in this paragraph the <quote>Council</quote>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6adc359376cd4c7bb45723a400efac8c"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Council shall be composed of the following:</text><clause id="id756b6807349b46849bbd266f6aabafd3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Joint Staff J–6.</text></clause><clause id="idec59d215179942f8b25958b34b66eaaa" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment.</text></clause><clause id="id62287a250061465c8eb096b8aea44650" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering.</text></clause><clause id="id904b28aa4a0d4761826c179fdcdbd479" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of Defense for Intelligence and Security.</text></clause><clause id="id815814ec34d34df0b9acbfac4e3911de" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Under Secretary of Defense for Policy.</text></clause><clause id="id0875b986468348fa84c62eeb4b841159" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The Director of Cost Analysis and Program Evaluation.</text></clause><clause id="idae67016164ea42418907c664ce8514c2" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>The Chief Information Officer of the Department.</text></clause><clause id="id2eb945b90cee4e2db0a9b19f01997697" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>The Director of Administration and Management.</text></clause><clause id="idc0e2ed3fbe38407eb4ff65ef49e053cd" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>The service acquisition executives of each of the military departments.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7049b10ffbbf4b45a0fb7722c17f3e10"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Head of Council</header><text>The Council shall be headed by the Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer of the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfceea4c8bda4424ca987689f3576ae81"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Council shall meet not less frequently than twice each fiscal year. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfddddde50f6e45eda258ceae4e2cc57c"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Duties of Council</header><text>The duties of the Council are as follows:</text><clause id="iddb2cfb04942d47ffbc6e355b890ccd12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>To streamline the organizational structure of the Department as it relates to artificial intelligence development, implementation, and oversight.</text></clause><clause id="id4af0556b153b4961aba00801cddcdbf2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>To improve coordination on artificial intelligence governance with the defense industry sector.</text></clause><clause id="id82ea71b088054aa8a91ffa3d32f06bf3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>To establish and oversee artificial intelligence guidance on ethical requirements and protections for usage of artificial intelligence supported by Department funding and reduces or mitigates instances of unintended bias in artificial intelligence algorithms.</text></clause><clause id="idb9178e5feeb74c65a96089d7359061df"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>To identify, monitor, and periodically update appropriate recommendations for operational usage of artificial intelligence.</text></clause><clause id="id81bf24f4ed534c34a9f013c27ff23985"><enum>(v)</enum><text>To review, as the head of the Council considers necessary, artificial intelligence program funding to ensure that any Department investment in an artificial intelligence tool, system, or algorithm adheres to all Department established policy related to artificial intelligence.</text></clause><clause id="idbe3a4a6064924aa28f5c93dce79002d1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>To provide periodic status updates on the efforts of the Department to develop and implement artificial intelligence into existing Department programs and processes.</text></clause><clause id="id1ce07c67fcd34bf49b1bd024ae501a65"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>To provide guidance on access and distribution restrictions relating to data, models, tool sets, or testing or validation infrastructure.</text></clause><clause id="id8ac6385f6703492cb5169e2423640423"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>to implement and oversee a data and artificial intelligence educational program for the purpose of familiarizing the Department at all levels on the applications of artificial intelligence in their operations.</text></clause><clause id="ida2d04fb986d44b3ba2a1356e4781c92d"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>To implement and oversee a data decree scorecard.</text></clause><clause id="idf07a9e6498cf4b1484100c190b4e540f"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Such other duties as the Council determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida3b750ff2d6a4399a7cfda4c922d665e"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Periodic reports</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this paragraph and not less frequently than once every 18 months thereafter, the Council shall submit to the Secretary and the congressional defense committees a report on the activities of the Council during the period covered by the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

