<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFA04E243438F455B8A832E50260895AF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 8700 IH: International Artificial Intelligence Research Partnership Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-06-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 8700</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240611">June 11, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish international artificial intelligence research partnerships, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB593728C002F4C62B9943F94D52D4BA6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H001E54B65F0441C58DA6D8571949F833" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>International Artificial Intelligence Research Partnership Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7FC4A5E9B2E948BEB555ED90C5779CE6"><enum>2.</enum><header>International artificial intelligence research partnership</header> <subsection id="H2003511C429D4D7BB69B17C2A09B122F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H2489C27FA6414E2DB5256ACA32262FE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>For over six decades, international city-to-city partnerships have played a crucial role in promoting United States priorities, fostering mutual understanding, and strengthening diplomatic ties between the United States and countries around the world.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D668E3264D044AD8F64F9FD20B7E7D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>These partnerships have received strong bipartisan support over the past 40 years, as demonstrated by the participation of every United States President since Dwight D. Eisenhower and the passage of numerous congressional resolutions recognizing the contributions of these partnerships to international cooperation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD780863F75B493B9C02CFF561E12EEF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaboration between United States cities and their international counterparts on artificial intelligence research can further strengthen these partnerships while promoting United States leadership in this critical field.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04273E0B0F4C464F8762EF1262EFBF76" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Coordination with the National Science Foundation and leveraging the National AI Research Resource can ensure that partnership activities align with United States research priorities and benefit from existing resources and expertise.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBE0FBBB0101B43A68E7F74D4B6B74BD3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research partnerships</header> 
<paragraph id="HAA0A8107492343F58785563FE0252920"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State should, either directly or through public-private partnerships, including nonprofits and academic institutions, carry out the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H8AFEC332585A43DBBE59C400AC05C3D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Encourage and support the establishment of artificial intelligence research partnerships between United States cities and their international counterparts.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7078307EA2E24B239980C8DB2458A660"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Provide guidance and assistance to United States cities seeking to establish such partnerships.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H02F10010EF1B44ACA10569B8061C5D6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Coordinate with the Director of the National Science Foundation to align partnership activities with United States artificial intelligence research priorities and leverage the National AI Research Resource.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD689702CA8F425BBD66CC4BC9779E54"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Ensure that such partnerships and related activities are consistent with United States foreign policy and national security interests.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84EF90D314AF4C9F911DA6C2524DD9F9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> A foreign city shall not be eligible to participate in a partnership or related activities under this section if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H76BFCE86A3094CD2A8023DF26DF7E007" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such city is located in a foreign country of concern; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D3D15780F044B6C8D3851E210A9160F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Director of National Intelligence, has determined such city is engaged in conduct that is detrimental to the national security or foreign policy of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA469AFDF632C41EF809D374EE6FCA909"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Partnerships and related activities under this section shall be subject to the following limitations:</text> <subparagraph id="H645DB88A94EE47DD87365D9035C9F9B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Research conducted pursuant to such partnerships shall be limited to non-national security areas of artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAE7D2BDDE3F84117AC307103C7793F10"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Such partnerships shall focus on economic cooperation and workforce development.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23C5642BDD1A43D2A452F67A50989135"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such activities conducted shall adhere to all applicable export control regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H090DB9BF1AF74F19ADFB25238D82DFC3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contracting authority</header> 
<paragraph id="H2CCA3A9619454302B1C062E971333817"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State is authorized to enter into contracts with appropriate entities to facilitate the establishment and implementation of artificial intelligence research partnerships under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD036AA47A60F4E46B25C27D02D9DF3E0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of State $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2028 to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBB3597FE11704462ADCA63D35B6646B9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter for the following two years, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report on activities carried out under this section, including information relating to the following:</text> <paragraph id="H5EAE37DCF0B44A8E975486197643091C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number and nature of artificial intelligence research partnerships established.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1A198D28D26548D994AE290C0D99345E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The scope of research areas covered by such partnerships.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2FFE23A1B3324C8FBAB8435AA63935DC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The level of participation from domestic and foreign cities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H699FD47769F04BF2969646FEDDB35BC0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Coordination efforts with the National Science Foundation and utilization of the National AI Research Resource.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4E10A7E628DB4470B0A1F36D9B390363"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any challenges or barriers to implementation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA48545BA90C84C19A4F742B9BCD08602"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H9635C7A3A6D94E3BA406ABF1A4ED4C77"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>artificial intelligence</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (enacted as division E of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD18B6C5A498D411AA7D19AB51943B0D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research partnership</header><text>The term <quote>artificial intelligence research partnership</quote> means translational artificial intelligence research that bridges foundational and use-inspired research with the delivery and deployment of its outcomes to the target community, and that supports essential bidirectional interplays with respect to which the delivery and deployment process informs such research.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9292FBE2C746413F9C8D29AB6C27C291"><enum>(3)</enum><header>External partner</header><text>The term <quote>external partner</quote> means a nonprofit organization that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3F17B6C5793F4CB49BFBCEC282907802"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a proven track record of facilitating international city-to-city partnerships;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1464696059224ADBBAAF816E8DD26C84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>maintains a network of United States cities with established international partnerships; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2154E99E1FF14CD68CA9057B7E335A63"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has experience managing Federal grants and contracts related to international cooperation and exchange programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C1D27B7D4844BADA2E4AB11E71F239F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign country of concern</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 10638 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/19237">19 U.S.C. 19237</external-xref>; enacted as division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


