<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAE98C78B2DDF49C8A9FC0E2400C2EE66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 9044 IH: To provide for citizen engagement on the development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-07-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 9044</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240715">July 15, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for citizen engagement on the development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAE115998AAB74DABBD1EF3D241A53268" style="OLC"><section id="H49CD1804A62B46278B6726870D60778A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Citizen engagement on development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="H40A4905DCCFE465DA1886E5963D967C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall conduct virtual and in-person listening sessions in various locations in the United States to provide a forum for discussion and consultation with appropriate representatives of States, territories, Tribal authorities, civil rights organizations, human rights organizations, women’s rights organizations, immigrant communities, faith communities, environmental protection organizations, agricultural businesses (including family and specialty farming and ranching entities), labor organizations, and academia regarding the development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0B8F11C5CDDF41FD982FA9C4D7950A8B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Further engagement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall encourage entities described in subsection (a) to conduct listening sessions similar to those described in such subsection, and report back to the Secretary regarding development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCED900B9F4BB44CE830DA0C928168CC5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 240 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to Congress a report on the attitudes, opinions, and beliefs of the American public regarding development and adoption of Federal civilian agency use of artificial intelligence.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

