<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H40115727DE194DBD995D6CACAC196587" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 9671 IH: Department of Energy Artificial Intelligence Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 9671</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240918">September 18, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide guidance for and investment in the research and development activities of artificial intelligence at the Department of Energy, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5D3E291A7064495F9E836B815AF6B535" style="OLC"><section id="HA7B2D4B0B6B148F49A4448D2817D6EEB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Energy Artificial Intelligence Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HEF689A7F1FC64D938BC7B882F8EEDBF7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Energy artificial intelligence research program</header><subsection id="H21FB28686FA24EFAAAB46F388CC75397"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title LV of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC0622E4E23FA426E80EDB420DA743554" display-inline="no-display-inline"><title id="HAC7D612370DB42BCA8784233F8F6D8BF"><enum>LV</enum><header>Department of Energy artificial intelligence research program</header><toc container-level="title-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="HAC7D612370DB42BCA8784233F8F6D8BF" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H046F97ABDE244F87867BA604C79EC298" level="section">Sec. 5501. Department of Energy artificial intelligence research program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6E63036C195C4A3B8F2199E857EAE2C9" level="section">Sec. 5502. Ensuring energy security for data centers and computing resources.</toc-entry></toc><section id="H046F97ABDE244F87867BA604C79EC298"><enum>5501.</enum><header>Department of Energy artificial intelligence research program</header><subsection id="H514EB116AB7447DD99A5CF86B9CBDB47" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a cross-cutting research and development program to advance artificial intelligence tools, systems, capabilities, and workforce needs and develop artificial intelligence capabilities for the purposes of advancing the missions of the Department (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>). In carrying out such program, the Secretary shall coordinate across all relevant offices and programs of the Department, including the Office of Science, the Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, the Office of Nuclear Energy, the Office of Fossil Energy, the Office of Electricity, the Office of Cybersecurity, Energy Security, Emergency Response, and the Advanced Research Projects Agency-Energy.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0A5A839CA04E40C3A26F0F352F0EC423"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Research areas</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall award financial assistance to eligible entities to carry out research projects on topics including the following:</text><paragraph id="H469DF8F902AE4699BB01B177C5182324"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The application of artificial intelligence systems to improve large-scale simulations of natural and other phenomena.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FA3270BA122496A85871DC421DF3457"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The study of applied mathematics, computer science, and statistics, including foundations of methods and systems of artificial intelligence, causal and statistical inference, and the development of algorithms for artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B77E469C0C24A03AE8F54A6CA6A1977" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The analysis of existing and new large-scale datasets from science and engineering experiments and simulations, including energy simulations and sponsored research activities, and, as determined by the Secretary, other priorities of the Department that utilize artificial intelligence tools and techniques.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EEA239170D14DF1A4DD84895793C7C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The development of operation and control systems that enhance automated, intelligent decision-making capabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD21FEE90BBCF47FCBACE1ABC4F2AD560"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The development of advanced computing hardware and computer architecture tailored to artificial intelligence systems, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H164EAD39CAD344E4A17495A92727BBEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The codesign of software and computational hardware.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H127F2623529344ED96FBB8E4D170327A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Energy-efficient computing hardware and algorithms for artificial intelligence training and inference.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3E32CCBB923409FACDD7AF107B18F9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Mechanisms to improve the energy efficiency of data centers, including relevant energy efficiency benchmarks for such centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C931E0AB0A64661BB1CFE5D36AE5A9B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The aggregation, curation, and distribution of standardized datasets for emerging artificial intelligence research fields and applications, including methods for addressing data scarcity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H212F479A8C774B2090E2116D0E059EE0" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The development of advanced artificial intelligence systems for pressing scientific, energy, and national security applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H243AB4208AFD4D61AC3D4029634516F4"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The development of trustworthy artificial intelligence systems, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H0D62F6586D034BCAA03A1B11AB811D51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Algorithmic explainability.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE47FEDA90ED94BC69F14EB2B2261CA1E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Analytical methods for identifying and mitigating bias in artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H060785B36DE140558AE76FD51B2AC0BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Safety and robustness, including assurance, verification, validation, security, and control.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC603D1D4C1D4590AB207F9D509BE775"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technology transfer</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall support technology transfer of artificial intelligence systems for the benefit of society and United States economic competitiveness.</text></subsection><subsection id="H09D8DBBF82C643179193E1363CC16BD4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Facility use and upgrades</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="H71BEF07931BB45168C40CFA7A237C16B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Make available high-performance computing infrastructure at National Laboratories for the development and use of advanced artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E32AE137D444C9FB7EE478426BBD197" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Make any upgrades necessary to enhance the use of existing computing facilities for artificial intelligence systems, including upgrades to hardware and other resources necessary for developing, training, and evaluating advanced artificial intelligence technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FB24DD9CAE047A3B51DE0DD8E124E69" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Establish new computing capabilities necessary to manage data and conduct high performance computing that enables the development and use of advanced artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BE903865BD643729DFF625FB0628FF1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Maintain and improve, as needed, networking infrastructure, data input and output mechanisms, and data analysis, storage, and service capabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC347E1287C4042C6B0B9C82D1F879A5A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Facilitate the development of unclassified and classified high-performance computing systems and artificial intelligence platforms through Department-owned infrastructure data and computing facilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC321AFA65D594CF190D6B74551F5E4DB"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide other resources necessary for the Department to develop, train, and evaluate advanced artificial intelligence systems and related technologies;</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B15956DA1BE45C3B895B2A69C509733"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Testbeds for next-Generation computing platforms and infrastructure</header><paragraph id="H5E856A47E18E430C8E3E73C7D9233D13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall establish at least one data center testbed for the development and assessment of hardware and algorithms for energy-efficient and energy-flexible artificial intelligence training and inference.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C0EF28AF1A542C29D0A8240FA42370D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out the testbed established under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall carry out the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF6CCFEE6621C433781D9A272C355585C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Test and evaluate new software, hardware, codesign of hardware and software, algorithms, networking, and other artificial intelligence-based technologies and applications to improve energy efficiency across the artificial intelligence ecosystem.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0FB595F550E4B30AD04D1206C63B6F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Carry out cooperative research projects with industry, including end user companies, hardware systems vendors, artificial intelligence developers, data center developers and operators, energy utilities, and other appropriate stakeholders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96959C9D1A3C4A64A850C5455D890317"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Aggregation, curation, and distribution of artificial intelligence training datasets</header><text>In carrying out activities described in subsection (b)(6), the Secretary shall develop methods, platforms, protocols, and other tools required for efficient, responsible, and effective aggregation, generation, curation, and distribution of artificial intelligence training and inference datasets, including the following:</text><paragraph id="HA14F3EC68CB14118B59498ABCE0A4AD6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Assembling, aggregating, and curating large-scale training data for advanced artificial intelligence systems, including outputs from research programs of the Department and other open science data, with the goal of developing comprehensive scientific artificial intelligence training databases and testing and validation data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5310AF563A48F59A590DD518C6C515" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Developing dataset documentation and metadata protocols and visualization tools, taking into account appropriate standards and guidelines to promote interoperability and consistency in documentation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D939F97BC304A3199102555F3D89FF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Developing and implementing appropriate data management plans for the ethical, responsible, and secure use of classified and unclassified scientific data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF40C10F5CB94BACADADACAB0D5D5BCC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Identifying, curating, and safely distributing, as appropriate based on the application, the following:</text><subparagraph id="H460926A419FE4E40B6CC7E183097D3C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Scientific and experimental departmental datasets.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70181737905744B9A1D5EE38DE1A468E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Sponsored research activities that are needed for the training of foundational and adapted downstream artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA147722E2384B5888148EA333717090" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Partnering with stakeholders to curate critical datasets that reside outside the Department but are determined by the Secretary to be critical to optimizing the capabilities of advanced artificial intelligence systems relevant to the missions of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEE74224796B44CCBBD508D477162EFF9" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Development of advanced artificial intelligence systems for pressing scientific, energy, and national security applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subsection (b)(7), the Secretary shall carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="H8250744692E14C4D9457228119FA0CA9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Develop innovative concepts in applied mathematics, computer science, engineering, and other science disciplines needed for advanced artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3C76968A7394D6D88225286734975E4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Develop best-in-class advanced artificial intelligence systems, model derivatives that support downstream use cases, and other technologies to solve pressing scientific, energy, and national security challenges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4551EB9CA2A441390766FE64769BA60" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Carry out cooperative research projects with industry, including end user companies, hardware systems vendors, and artificial intelligence software companies, to advance artificial intelligence technologies relevant to the missions of the Department and mitigate risks associated with such technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H751081344974488CA7920F223B3D2464" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In coordination with the Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Homeland Security, research counter-adversarial artificial intelligence solutions to predict, prevent, mitigate, and respond to threats to critical infrastructure, energy security, and nuclear nonproliferation, and biological and chemical threats.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7E8FBC6883246F7906F40757A754778" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In coordination with energy utilities, State energy offices, data center developers and operators, and other key stakeholders the Secretary determines appropriate, carry out research to examine how artificial intelligence technologies may be impacted by or applied to energy supply bottlenecks, energy demand projections, site reliability challenges, and data center operational flexibilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2E4313B2BCD4EBC80E01830C7CC876E" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Establish crosscutting research efforts to understand and mitigate artificial intelligence-related risks, including the establishment of unclassified and classified data platforms across the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA5430D606254E80A5EA111AA59B5EFB"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Shared resources for artificial intelligence</header><paragraph id="H0E39DCF98A054A60899C7968AADF5BF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the program, the Secretary shall identify, support, and sustain shared resources and enabling tools that have the potential to accelerate the pace of scientific discovery and technological innovation with respect to the missions of the Department relating to science, energy, and national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3C4812834BB4F6AB578AFFFEE58D18C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with relevant experts in the Federal Government, industry, energy utilities, academia, State energy offices, and the National Laboratories.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DAE4C136DA8414AAC8DD92EFBF08775"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Focus</header><text>Shared resources and enabling tools referred to in paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HABB93173FA574DAA830ECA2AA3986777"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Scientific data and knowledge bases for training artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2ED083A1BB6C43D58628414D5D838BCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Benchmarks and competitions for evaluating advances in artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H452FD8177EED4AB692B5A3DF263C558F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Platform technologies that lower the cost of generating training data or enable the generation of training data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58AA69D951F046C887240C5824351F57"><enum>(D)</enum><text>High-performance computing, including hybrid computing systems that integrate artificial intelligence and high-performance computing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2979E1C6A359493B92F959B930239793"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The combination of artificial intelligence and scientific automation, such as cloud labs and self-driving labs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1797745CFB38460893C053B2B924FA65"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Tools that enable artificial intelligence to solve inverse design problems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CB956CBC35F46EEAFF665076925E355" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Testbeds for accelerating progress at the intersection of artificial intelligence and cyberphysical systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8DC08C9D93448D78B243FEA6AD794DA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Testbeds for testing and evaluating artificial intelligence-based technologies and applications to improve energy efficiency across artificial intelligence systems, in accordance with subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFDBAF07891C405EBBE62F75FA72E02C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure coordination with, and avoid unnecessary duplication of, activities to provide shared resources with the National Science Foundation, the agencies participating in the Interagency Committee established under section 5103 of this Act, and the Networking and Information Technology Research and Development Program authorized under section 101 of the High Performance Computing Act of 1991 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/5511">15 U.S.C. 5511</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCBFD277E9F9744BAAE79BF2360837A43" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research institutes</header><text>The Secretary shall support on a competitive, merit-reviewed basis not fewer than two multidisciplinary artificial intelligence research institutes pursuant to section 5201 of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C225C0E1B0C4F18A2B022A7145BC658" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Research To improve energy permitting processes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In consultation with the Federal Permitting Improvement Steering Council established under section 41002(a) of the FAST Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4370m-1">42 U.S.C. 4370m–1(a)</external-xref>), the Secretary shall carry out research and development activities to evaluate the potential for utilizing artificial intelligence to improve Federal permitting processes for energy-related projects, including critical materials (as such term is defined in section 7002 of title VII of division Z of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/30/1606">30 U.S.C. 1606</external-xref>)) projects, by building tools to improve future reviews and analyzing data from past environmental and other permitting reviews to inform more flexible and effective categorical exclusions.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E847D6764B34F5CB8EAD5C574F84F27"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Risk management</header><paragraph id="H1E34A508986148EC8859C7130AD5CE2A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall review agency policies for risk management in artificial intelligence related projects and issue, as necessary, policies and principles that are consistent with the framework developed under section 22A of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A1A8D1B564A44098DB3BCF6A19CF958"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Taxonomy</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall develop a taxonomy of safety and security risks associated with artificial intelligence systems relevant to the missions of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA3CE723DBE9749D38EF6DB4562EAA95F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Stem education and workforce development</header><text>As part of the program, the Secretary, in coordination with the Director of the National Science Foundation, may develop the required workforce, and hire and train researchers to meet the rising demand for artificial intelligence talent, including by carrying out the following:</text><paragraph id="HBB4C27E06A36419DB605B1F084FB516A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Providing training, grants, and research opportunities, including experiential learning experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in advanced artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3970800848954EC6AE04F308943E2E6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Carrying out public awareness campaigns regarding artificial intelligence related career paths.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07318D7940A34CEAA4D691D7D6D7C2B9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Assisting institutions of higher education to establish new degree and certificate programs in artificial intelligence-related disciplines.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2680562885784EB08A70EF1DED09376F"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="H2188CDFA0EBF49FDB13034DE24589CF9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research security</header><text>The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9DCEDFA1C18466590A05E0AE128278A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cybersecurity</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure the integration of robust cybersecurity measures into all artificial intelligence research-to-deployment efforts authorized under this section to protect the integrity and confidentiality of collected and analyzed data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5C1149FDADE4F37A2A00884003643E8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ethical considerations</header><text>Taking into account the guidance issued pursuant to section 10343(c) of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19052">42 U.S.C. 19052(c)</external-xref>), the Secretary shall issue guidance governing the ethical, safe, and responsible conduct of research activities funded by the Department and performed at National Laboratories and user facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F376A034D584767BABE2778AD4EC27F"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Data privacy and sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall review agency policies for data sharing with other public and private sector organizations and issue, as necessary, policies and principles that are consistent with the standards and guidelines submitted under section 22A of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1(e)</external-xref>). In addition, the Secretary shall establish a streamlined mechanism for approving research projects or partnerships that require sharing sensitive public or private data with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9BCE947E28F14D1CAFEF7996D58BA029"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><paragraph id="HA853C20182A647928BAA06E0646345F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal partnerships</header><text>The Secretary may request, accept, and provide funds from other Federal departments and agencies, State, United States territory, local, or Tribal government agencies, private sector for-profit entities, and nonprofit entities, to be available to the extent provided by appropriations Acts, to support a research project or partnership carried out under this section. The Secretary may not give any special consideration to any agency or entity in return for a donation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB1AF1EDF13B42F8973CCECB242765B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partnerships with private entities</header><subparagraph id="H9F4A28364C91482D80C5DB936D71C924"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to establish partnerships with private companies and nonprofit organizations in carrying out this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H909ABC2E23854511AFC63256885DE276"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall protect any information submitted to or shared by the Department consistent with applicable laws and regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5BA3F19BB2CF428DB1F35635D5014484"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Stakeholder engagement</header><text>In carrying out the activities authorized in this section, the Secretary shall carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="H2C75545C058E4AECB5163FD0459C95FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Collaborate with a range of stakeholders, including small businesses, institutes of higher education, industry, and the National Laboratories.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DBE3F00118A4D6D9A3A2885A35FAC3C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Leverage the collective body of knowledge from existing artificial intelligence and machine learning research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H878B76BCA3FB465B983A31967598D8CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Engage with other Federal departments and agencies, research communities, and potential users of information produced under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9DB9C67CBBCC4DDB89B27E2C011EB0C3"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><paragraph id="H54384B991EB84AADA80316C77C6545E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall develop a strategic plan with specific short-term and long-term goals and resource needs to advance applications in artificial intelligence for science, energy, and national security to support the missions of the Department. The strategic plan shall be consistent with the following:</text><subparagraph id="H089BB121CAAB4B3296CDF970410E07A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The 2023 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>Advanced Research Directions on AI for Science, Energy, and Security</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D180084E2AB4250BD96A518BF6E736B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The 2024 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>AI for Energy</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F1BCCB376BE4786817B049645FC843C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The strategic plan required under section 5103 of division E of this Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B089216E04A43489591055D8FB25E9F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee of Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate the strategic plan required under paragraph (1), and shall notify such committees of any substantial updates to such plan in subsequent years.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C86D10ED52F4395822BAC1D8FEBDBC5"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H14FD935F62084C548CB6216811DBF5C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence system</header><text>The term <quote>artificial intelligence system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 7223 of the Advancing American AI Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/40/11301">40 U.S.C. 11301</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CD105F24F39431290FC62A8A45C6EAA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA981B1B40D1E4545AC6EA18F79CF2B65"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entities</quote> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HD304E64EA06548EAAEB52E02A4FD7766"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H663E04568E2A43C89D6B4588A105EB72"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A National Laboratory.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE00A555B1F9A45C6B897443868046FB4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A Federal research agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H489E2DE1F5424A6EB051B74457F20E4F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A State research agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCFCE56DE6BB46A29FB01BCFDC68797A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A nonprofit research organization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE13EA3A364A44BD0BE97C13850048B2A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A private sector entity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13BB3532ACBA453E98BA520F15E1E603"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A consortium of two or more entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (F).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H58F78A9C3DB8404991C51CF13F282345" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <quote>National Laboratory</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD6B67A4D6014CC28AABADE91AB0428F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD4EB196503347CB8F3A1E25B084B1A4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <quote>testbed</quote> means any platform, facility, or environment that enables the testing and evaluation of scientific theories and new technologies, including hardware, software, or field environments in which structured frameworks can be implemented to conduct tests to assess the performance, reliability, safety, and security of a wide range of items, including prototypes, systems, applications, artificial intelligence systems, instruments, computational tools, devices, and other technological innovations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFC5E4A1D7AC84C57A4ABEF98CC348729"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $300,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2030.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6E63036C195C4A3B8F2199E857EAE2C9"><enum>5502.</enum><header>Ensuring energy security for data centers and computing resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HC71F0524504B4087BF289AF20DCE5BB3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H611D0F00571042C6A7BFBF33089D699D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The growth of computing data centers and advanced computing electrical power load in the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24EDA87AAAFE47ADA416F6CC796596AD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Potential risks of growth in computing centers or growth in the required electrical power to United States energy security and national security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A43DF54E2CE4CE0AEBF5675D4A0755E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The extent to which emerging technologies, such as artificial intelligence and advanced computing, may impact hardware and software systems used at data and computing centers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H527B625A5F7B4583B6207AD455D2EF02" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Cost, performance, reliability, availability, space requirements, emissions, and supply chain issues for current technologies, including renewable diesel, natural gas, renewable natural gas, fuel cells, nuclear energy, battery storage, enhanced geothermal, long-duration energy storage, and other potentially viable technologies available to support regional data center expansion and for backup power.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2186DA348F7B48E28282F97AC6AE80B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recommendations for the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBCFEA07486F54DD1976BEF9188B02781" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Resources and capabilities that the Department may provide to promote access to energy resources by data centers, advanced computing hardware and algorithms, and artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94D1DD0E88C1436ABC996D12D760D355" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Policy changes to ensure domestic deployment of data center and advanced computing resources to prevent offshoring of United States data and resources.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94D160B726C14D49B16BB2B43A1F4F3B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Improving the energy efficiency of data centers, advanced computing hardware and algorithms, and artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA7E8973D489A4E9BA37B5C6D76382A4E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents in section 2(b) of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 5501 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1AAB62E3DD00401CAB677F798960834C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 5502. Ensuring energy security for data centers and computing resources.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

