<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H705C82C3139949239792C62FB1A2EE24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 7603 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to ensure that the audit of the financial statements of the Department of Defense for fiscal year 2024 is conducted using technology that uses artificial intelligence, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 7603</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240308">March 8, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to ensure that the audit of the financial statements of the Department of Defense for fiscal year 2024 is conducted using technology that uses artificial intelligence, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B841BFFF8DF4F6288A896127ABC6EBA" style="OLC"><section id="H50A09D95D7FA4F8AAE53EFED523100B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Use of technology using artificial intelligence to facilitate audit of the financial statements of the Department of Defense for fiscal year 2024</header><subsection id="H3D8802CB62AC470699323C8A816003A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development of AI technology for audits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary of Defense (Comptroller) and the Inspector General of the Department of Defense shall jointly develop technology that uses artificial intelligence for the purpose of facilitating audits of the financial statements of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H354CD80EC8E3447881CBFBCFD2BFCEA7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of Technology</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that—</text><paragraph id="HEBA8E72079554D8D8529EC944922EC96"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the audit of the financial statements of the Department of Defense for fiscal year 2024, as required under section 240a of title 10, United States Code, is performed using the technology developed under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB33A57D68B6448F696371999EED1F841"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the technology developed under subsection (a) is used to accelerate the retirement of older financial management systems used by the Department without compromising essential controls or generally accepted Government auditing standards.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F18D64930344E76A6AC2758019B41FD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of surplus funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amounts identified in such audit as being surplus to the needs of the Department of Defense by reason of future valuation and accounting errors shall be rescinded and deposited in the General Fund of the Treasury to be used for deficit reduction.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB54C37AFADA344EE9B2C28CBE3C1A62B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall provide to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a briefing on—</text><paragraph id="H5400B68D7996420BA0E43F3BF42C56E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the progress of the audit of the financial statements of the Department of Defense for fiscal year 2024; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04864015B20348CCB2AD11208B6BE511"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the technology developed pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

