<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-ELT24350-FSF-72-SFJ"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>95 S4664 RS: Department of Energy AI Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-11-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 631</calendar><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 4664</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20240710">July 10, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S338">Mr. Manchin</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S288">Ms. Murkowski</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSEG00" added-display-style="italic" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Energy and Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><action stage="Reported-in-Senate"><action-date date="20241121">November 21, 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported by <sponsor name-id="S338">Mr. Manchin</sponsor>, with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Energy to establish a program to promote the use of artificial intelligence to support the missions of the Department of Energy, and for other purposes. </official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Energy AI Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="idcbf9b0f843ae4328a21415a0ff07801b" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="idf6c5479f981b4bf2b00408b728fc6ec8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Department has a leading role to play in making the most of the potential of artificial intelligence to advance the missions of the Department relating to national security, science, and energy (including critical materials);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8fec325f0db44659941e2cffabc23f8b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the 17 National Laboratories employ over 40,000 scientists, engineers, and researchers with decades of experience developing world-leading advanced computational algorithms, computer science research, experimentation, and applications in machine learning that underlie artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1ba53e807da24ca5931c9da45b566246"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the NNSA manages the Stockpile Stewardship Program established under section 4201 of the Atomic Energy Defense Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/2521">50 U.S.C. 2521</external-xref>), which includes the Advanced Simulation and Computing program, that provides critical classified and unclassified computing capabilities to sustain the nuclear stockpile of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id903db0d313214a7b8fb08d66f8563c19"><enum>(4)</enum><text>for decades, the Department has led the world in the design, construction, and operation of the preeminent high-performance computing systems of the United States, which benefit the scientific and economic competitiveness of the United States across many sectors, including energy, critical materials, biotechnology, and national security; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id75AFD7F4E1504F1A98CF0744D0954C17"><enum>(5)</enum><text>across the network of 34 user facilities of the Department, scientists generate tremendous volumes of high-quality open data across diverse research areas, while the NNSA has always generated the foremost datasets in the world on nuclear deterrence and strategic weapons;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0CAEED91B46443B2824D3C20262A2A0D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the unrivaled quantity and quality of open and classified scientific datasets of the Department is a unique asset to rapidly develop frontier AI models;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idA333E3734B6A418C8E1B4DF5AE1BDF33"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Department already develops cutting-edge AI models to execute the broad mission of the Department, including AI models of the Department that are used to forecast disease transmission for COVID–19, and address critical material issues and emerging nuclear security missions; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7A2552E3BDF44E9E9534CCD7480FB04C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the AI capabilities of the Department will underpin and jumpstart a dedicated, focused, and centralized AI program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idaed786e894a94a3aa8536dd4ecccc6fd"><enum>(9)</enum><text>under section 4.1(b) of Executive Order 14110 (88 Fed. Reg. 75191 (November 1, 2023)) (relating to the safe, secure, and trustworthy development and use of artificial intelligence), the Secretary is tasked to lead development in testbeds, national security protections, and assessment of artificial intelligence applications. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd86e5378903649c79dea2c6fc68600e5" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="id3ef3cfcbff5346d0a11281196882c43e"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI; artificial intelligence</header><text>The terms <term>AI</term> and <term>artificial intelligence</term> have the meaning given the term <term>artificial intelligence</term> in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id02bd3525c024431696d48ba0acda4e30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alignment</header><text>The term <term>alignment</term> means a field of AI safety research that aims to make AI systems behave in line with human intentions.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5758632362D042D89D39765FF2A2BA92"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Energy, including the NNSA.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf90231109422484eb46bc80799e80ed3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><text>The term <term>foundation model</term> means an AI model that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3DE5BB898D0F4A62B07AE1329C8058E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is trained on broad data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id5C41A3C1D6F2486AB462674788504F34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>generally uses self-supervision;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id267098D17BA5477A92840AD23CF1441B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>contains at least tens of billions of parameters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id9237F80A406D4BF58F915C4B9A096563"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is applicable across a wide range of contexts; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idD05B64C4EE304E0F8EBED800A2F1FACB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>exhibits, or could be easily modified to exhibit, high levels of performance at tasks that pose a serious risk to the security, national economic security, or national public health or safety of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idABAF2136F0D54C14ADDA517C931354A4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Frontier AI</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id28A4645DEC9C440EB80BD48C3D8ACC95"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>frontier AI</term> means the leading edge of AI research that remains unexplored and is considered to be the most challenging, including models—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7AB0FC2006C44DB39B4AC0329D84C8CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that exceed the capabilities currently present in the most advanced existing models; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id480748E9EF614BB78E314836DC346A3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>many of which perform a wide variety of tasks.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4C14CFF6CA64485EA3EBD78EFE47B72E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>frontier AI</term> includes AI models with more than 1,000,000,000,000 parameters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5ADF9361D2B3476AB171AE0DAFD71F42"><enum>(6)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8c89355ef18c4a0293c6001298a6b41e"><enum>(7)</enum><header>NNSA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>NNSA</quote> means the National Nuclear Security Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idebee994203a544d78750461c873cb30d"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id013ea9138ae84405a27cf79e610387a2"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means any platform, facility, or environment that enables the testing and evaluation of scientific theories and new technologies, including hardware, software, or field environments in which structured frameworks can be implemented to conduct tests to assess the performance, reliability, safety, and security of a wide range of items, including prototypes, systems, applications, AI models, instruments, computational tools, devices, and other technological innovations. </text></paragraph></section><section id="ida3bfdf7f0a0648c9bfd08563b14d4274" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>4.</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research to deployment</header><subsection id="id7c571cc989b14fcb860582ea78e13175"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program To develop and deploy frontiers in artificial intelligence for science, security, and technology (FASST)</header><paragraph id="id516e03f56b404765a731c8e7f3674955"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a centralized AI program to carry out research on the development and deployment of advanced artificial intelligence capabilities for the missions of the Department (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>program</quote>), consistent with the program established under section 5501 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9461">15 U.S.C. 9461</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id704f86a2fed74dc2a79c98c6239a4ca3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program components</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5bf9b3c598c749ea9b5447cd878a5773"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program shall advance and support diverse activities that include the following components:</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id53016ba3284345c0906254cf258bbd09"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Aggregation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4f188605cbfc4fb79b91f3f8ef5dacd3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Development and deployment of next-generation computing platforms and infrastructure.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5dbf896d67cf4ee68e848eab5f9401eb"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Development and deployment of safe and trustworthy AI models and systems.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd9c6ce58d441484cae32285b06c8b306"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Tuning and adaptation of AI models and systems for pressing scientific, energy, and national security applications.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3224165f5e6d4f5584993c1f098883a1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Aggregation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(i), the Secretary shall develop methods, platforms, protocols, and other tools required for efficient, safe, and effective aggregation, generation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets, including—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idF930194943DD42CF91E1B6A5B12E4DCA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assembling, aggregating, and curating large-scale training data for advanced AI, including outputs from research programs of the Department and other open science data, with the goal of developing comprehensive scientific AI training databases and testing and validation data;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id3E8FA33994314811941FB6C05899536F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing and executing appropriate data management plan for the ethical, responsible, and secure use of classified and unclassified scientific data;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idDE9050DB5EB547F490CE1B78D0C1B06E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifying, curating, and safely distributing, as appropriate based on the application—</text><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idB5EB85A194644D3CB666AD2A5F577D6D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>scientific and experimental Departmental datasets; and </text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idAD24341505B3495FA042AC82D779907A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>sponsored research activities that are needed for the training of foundation and adapted downstream AI models; and</text></subclause></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id70B9485E49E1440B9086B5C822D74B7E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>partnering with stakeholders to curate critical datasets that reside outside the Department but are determined to be critical to optimizing the capabilities of open-science AI foundation models, national security AI foundation models, and other AI technologies developed under the program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id7E7239BCE3E14346A5954C9E272FF69E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Development and deployment of next-generation computing platforms and infrastructure</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id184AC4ED5857486EAED7A96D4E42BBBD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop early-stage AI testbeds to test and evaluate new software, hardware, algorithms, and other AI-based technologies and applications;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idFE7626BB9D2941F09CEC0DC7EDC4A201"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop and deploy new energy-efficient AI computing hardware and software infrastructure necessary for developing and deploying trustworthy frontier AI systems that leverage the high-performance computing capabilities of the Department and the National Laboratories;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id6D37323063894501B22ACA0AF18F1B69"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>facilitate the development and deployment of unclassified and classified high-performance computing systems and AI platforms through Department-owned infrastructure data and computing facilities;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id1FAF35C6412B45F9A7A90D8C48BB4A93"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>procure high-performance computing and other resources necessary for developing, training, evaluating, and deploying AI foundation models and AI technologies; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id6E4AD304B5FB476680DEF4D5FB266D6A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>use appropriate supplier screening tools available through the Department to ensure that procurements under clause (iv) are from trusted suppliers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idE886C5AF774F4D0EBC69DF296565BC56"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Development and deployment of safe and trustworthy AI models and systems</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(iii), not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idB3FF6290AC324C9586090FAFC895E364"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop innovative concepts and applied mathematics, computer science, engineering, and other science disciplines needed for frontier AI;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id8A0D795330C0463C85BA7FEA870FD7FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop best-in-class AI foundation models and other AI technologies for open-science and national security applications;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idE9990E42389C476B963F2B5B839477B9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>research and deploy counter-adversarial artificial intelligence solutions to predict, prevent, mitigate, and respond to threats to critical infrastructure, energy security, and nuclear nonproliferation, and biological and chemical threats;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id0185061343114FC29318F2631BB9FEA0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>establish crosscutting research efforts on AI risks, reliability, safety, trustworthiness, and alignment, including the creation of unclassified and classified data platforms across the Department; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id537E9B4DDC594948A5A56B43C7FA46FD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>develop capabilities needed to ensure the safe and responsible implementation of AI in the private and public sectors that—</text><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id38C7D03FBCA64D8C959CDAABC00A5782"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may be readily applied across Federal agencies and private entities to ensure that open-science models are released responsibly, securely, and in the national interest; and</text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id119EC328BD3F41DA8408E8B4F25A35CE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensure that classified national security models are secure, responsibly managed, and safely implemented in the national interest. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idA1A21BB08B97444F873536C76A948BAE"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Tuning and adaptation of AI models and systems for pressing scientific and national security applications</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(iv), the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id02678B404A264A77853FC44395FF1ED8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use AI foundation models and other AI technologies to develop a multitude of tuned and adapted downstream models to solve pressing scientific, energy, and national security challenges;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idC66EEE243A2249668E94072CF003853D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carry out joint work, including public-private partnerships, and cooperative research projects with industry, including end user companies, hardware systems vendors, and AI software companies, to advance AI technologies relevant to the missions of the Department;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idEE586C189C7043DA941DA75051452482"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>form partnerships with other Federal agencies, institutions of higher education, and international organizations aligned with the interests of the United States to advance frontier AI systems development and deployment; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idC6EB5257021547DAAC3B24EAD945EAF1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>increase research experiences and workforce development, including training for undergraduate and graduate students in frontier AI for science, energy, and national security.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id081b6d724e4e48839b08caa3b8396103"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall develop a strategic plan with specific short-term and long-term goals and resource needs to advance applications in AI for science, energy, and national security to support the missions of the Department, consistent with—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id222FE12E453749C2803595EB16E86C90"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 2023 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>Advanced Research Directions on AI for Science, Energy, and Security</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id5798EADC91C9447EA9B83FFDD220493F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the 2024 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>AI for Energy</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6ec250111a0749b0afc7130faaff7d3b"><enum>(b)</enum><header>AI Research and Development Centers</header><paragraph id="idda43cca068fb4f739daf763600c7d326"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall select, on a competitive, merit-reviewed basis, National Laboratories to establish and operate not fewer than 8 multidisciplinary AI Research and Development Centers (referred to in this subsection as <quote>Centers</quote>)—</text><subparagraph id="id5182c5b010f948deb29e871f8bc44752"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to accelerate the safe and trustworthy deployment of AI for science, energy, and national security missions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0ab3993193724d00851b9d8013a2a4aa"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to demonstrate the use of AI in addressing key challenge problems of national interest in science, energy, and national security; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida0191033ea7643b69a906573f949511a"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to maintain the competitive advantage of the United States in AI.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2fad2830fda1409eb529359121291061"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Focus</header><text>Each Center shall bring together diverse teams from National Laboratories, academia, and industry to collaboratively and concurrently deploy hardware, software, numerical methods, data, algorithms, and applications for AI and ensure that the frontier AI research of the Department is well-suited for key Department missions, including by using existing and emerging computing systems to the maximum extent practicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idebead8523d254820b221432f9124d1b9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administration</header><subparagraph id="idad9e19634ad046c58fa8b6263f0491c5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>National laboratory</header><text>Each Center shall be established as part of a National Laboratory.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idBC318F993F79478C8AFD15835F1AD864"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for selection to establish and operate a Center under paragraph (1), a National Laboratory shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id89d9194f427f4db29b8e1af167b21ba3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Director</header><text>Each Center shall be headed by a Director, who shall be the Chief Executive Officer of the Center and an employee of the National Laboratory described in subparagraph (A), and responsible for—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida813233b7a524a15bf3d4d2cfb726639"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">successful execution of the goals of the Center; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd5a07c8e4ab34b0e879355088fa41314"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating with other Centers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1e22a79d291846d9aece52b1e8154dcf"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Technical roadmap</header><text>In support of the strategic plan developed under subsection (a)(3), each Center shall—</text><clause id="idfdd647a4974046b9a28d77dcd87e342f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>set a research and innovation goal central to advancing the science, energy, and national security mission of the Department; and</text></clause><clause id="ida67ecd4b6558417d8e7c6d98a5cadc42"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish a technical roadmap to meet that goal in not more than 7 years.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id986D0FD3BEFC4BE2A11FB0A2A298379D"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate, minimize duplication, and resolve conflicts between the Centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idaba845824c9a460c9189362fef50f365"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Of the amounts made available under subsection (h), each Center shall receive not less than $30,000,000 per year for a duration of not less than 5 years but not more than 7 years, which yearly amount may be renewed for an additional 5-year period.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida3c3f5e982b64cd79fd21f3725d8b888"><enum>(c)</enum><header>AI risk evaluation and mitigation program</header><paragraph id="id47664C54FFB448789AE608612BA61C8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI risk program</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), and consistent with the missions of the Department, the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Secretary of Commerce, shall carry out a comprehensive program to evaluate and mitigate safety and security risks associated with artificial intelligence systems (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>AI risk program</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfc4873ee2fcd43b28e48ad93e52a870b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Risk taxonomy</header><subparagraph id="id882bf91d7c2b45dd8e8e027da7c13f3e"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the AI risk program, the Secretary shall develop a taxonomy of safety and security risks associated with artificial intelligence systems relevant to the missions of the Department, including, at a minimum, the risks described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf542368bf40e45ab8dba8c0292fbc07b"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Risks described</header><text>The risks referred to in subparagraph (A) are the abilities of artificial intelligence—</text><clause id="idfa9bef0d745c4b719315b58b342aa009"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to generate information at a given classification level;</text></clause><clause id="idf88f13954f5848eca6f5a3c1011d3e78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to assist in generation of nuclear weapons information;</text></clause><clause id="id5d1a0772808a423d99dbc23e98a55b3e"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to assist in generation of chemical, biological, radiological, nuclear, nonproliferation, critical infrastructure, and energy security threats or hazards;</text></clause><clause id="idf978ebf49b5a4780b6f9f1f20427a9d1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to assist in generation of malware and other cyber and adversarial threats that pose a significant national security risk, such as threatening the stability of critical national infrastructure;</text></clause><clause id="idb96632f2646d4e1d83a86b09f43a0243"><enum>(v)</enum><text>to undermine public trust in the use of artificial intelligence technologies or in national security; </text></clause><clause id="ide8fe5c2f13284a83bd4d14426fc0c273"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>to deceive a human operator or computer system, or otherwise act in opposition to the goals of a human operator or automated systems; and</text></clause><clause id="id41ed418d33cb4d16ba64bf095078f0b5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>to act autonomously with little or no human intervention in ways that conflict with human intentions.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id495c8013f0f442a9a19853b01b8c0983"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Shared resources for AI</header><paragraph id="id7afb46bad04b4525b091940eedc73554"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall identify, support, and sustain shared resources and enabling tools that have the potential to accelerate the pace of scientific discovery and technological innovation with respect to the missions of the Department relating to science, energy, and national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4c9100b49a754be4be97fccd51c0d1d2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with relevant experts in industry, academia, and the National Laboratories. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id932c3d9150fd43969a50e74ae62201b6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Focus</header><text>Shared resources and enabling tools referred to in paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="id1576b6b4e6c84e46a02d2b7932251fd8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Scientific data and knowledge bases for training AI systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id613f83e3713043a4b7f41058e3830a9c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Benchmarks and competitions for evaluating advances in AI systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd09c93f4b7d141799358830c123bc45d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Platform technologies that lower the cost of generating training data or enable the generation of novel training data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbc09f7f6be944b7697d19d696b2d7900"><enum>(D)</enum><text>High-performance computing, including hybrid computing systems that integrate AI and high-performance computing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide9ab381108f04946b4a8638e2885cce8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The combination of AI and scientific automation, such as cloud labs and self-driving labs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab63d58bcd6040e69b39f0e084cccfcf"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Tools that enable AI to solve inverse design problems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide2a4f9aa59c440dd94fdfb96fd893254"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Testbeds for accelerating progress at the intersection of AI and cyberphysical systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id03aa18c4eb554f68baa52dc17faef095"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="id49d75a0be426417da3de85faaede387a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research security</header><text>The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id44c04c526514493fbe8ddc40a616fa79"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cybersecurity</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure the integration of robust cybersecurity measures into all AI research-to-deployment efforts authorized under this section to protect the integrity and confidentiality of collected and analyzed data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc5e9a52300f24a26937e39a9823c026a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Partnerships with private entities</header><subparagraph id="id5A2D38BE9C69442B9AD18C9441C9C8C4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to establish partnerships with private companies and nonprofit organizations in carrying out this Act, including with respect to the research, development, and deployment of each of the 4 program components described in subsection (a)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4D5D25DA99FE401DBE7BDC8C251010E3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall protect any information submitted to or shared by the Department consistent with applicable laws (including regulations).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idbe8800e40fa24720a317902e53a11b37"><enum>(f)</enum><header>STEM education and workforce development</header><paragraph id="idABF70D6310C6483B9C1235ABAF499FEC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Of the amounts made available under subsection (h), not less than 10 percent shall be used to foster the education and training of the next-generation AI workforce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1BD084A622D44CACB63D4AB54491658C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>AI talent</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall develop the required workforce, and hire and train not fewer than 500 new researchers to meet the rising demand for AI talent—</text><subparagraph id="idc7af065d18c7475bb4dbf3c8ce6c8505"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with a particular emphasis on expanding the number of individuals from underrepresented groups pursuing and attaining skills relevant to AI; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id006ec3d092eb4d9f9efc2b59b20739a2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>including by—</text><clause id="id7a4920d5b91d4a3b83e9c8f82e089e6e"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing training, grants, and research opportunities;</text></clause><clause id="idf367c0cc882d4f5794e82770459e7dbb"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carrying out public awareness campaigns about AI career paths; and</text></clause><clause id="id65027a06256b4ed5a230ba5b3ceaa43f"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>establishing new degree and certificate programs in AI-related disciplines at universities and community colleges.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id691e8a6fba134cce8a9049b789a2e7bf"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress an annual report describing—</text><paragraph id="id9a63cd08f6944db4bf75c66fd7b07ef4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the progress, findings, and expenditures under each program established under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8b1f6edfdff1468488e8f9768b1bdb30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any legislative recommendations for promoting and improving each of those programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id014b0de81cc445c29bd56044331e2899"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $2,400,000,000 each year for the 5-year period following the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="id1fa2558970b64fe9acfa4e9c696c74c9" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal permitting</header><subsection id="id345503691e704d1eb318540ed468d93b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a program to improve Federal permitting processes for energy-related projects, including critical materials projects, using artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="idef8a62a0cba04a3e8cea9203de590665"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall carry out activities, including activities that—</text><paragraph id="idd57f9bcd6db8497d94236dd7182a8150"><enum>(1)</enum><text>analyze data and provide tools from past environmental and other permitting reviews, including by—</text><subparagraph id="idb1b8aa8f8f3d4b31b535bd881e1e000f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>extracting data from applications for comparison with data relied on in environmental reviews to assess the adequacy and relevance of applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idAA599AAB76A042E0915C737BBF47AF8D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>extracting information from past site-specific analyses in the area of a current project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ide33184797e4a4aec835a8d1e785123b1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>summarizing key mitigation actions that have been successfully applied in past similar projects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4e4b73be831c4ae98dd694cb86409400"><enum>(D)</enum><text>using AI for deeper reviews of past determinations under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) to inform more flexible and effective categorical exclusions; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id46bb99efdc074915b7398e68fef42a83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>build tools to improve future reviews, including—</text><subparagraph id="id6825d78f7e304696888eeb6193e9bdb6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>tools for project proponents that accelerate preparation of environmental documentation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf7248e58c2a24e1e94f6ed2d06b37785"><enum>(B)</enum><text>tools for government reviewers such as domain-specific large language models that help convert geographic information system or tabular data on resources potentially impacted into rough-draft narrative documents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7fffc4d288c543c08a4f50b5397e45ca"><enum>(C)</enum><text>tools to be applied in nongovernmental settings, such as automatic reviews of applications to assess the completeness of information; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4e4c7541f6d24a6995284cd3bda223fa"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a strategic plan to implement and deploy online and digital tools to improve Federal permitting activities, developed in consultation with—</text><clause id="idF226AE1F146F4981B5D9F8985AF4A737"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior;</text></clause><clause id="id3F059C5D53604747857D3FEAF65497A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System land;</text></clause><clause id="id3CD662E125564DDBA746DC646A12440D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Executive Director of the Federal Permitting Improvement Steering Council established by section 41002(a) of the FAST Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4370m-1">42 U.S.C. 4370m–1(a)</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="idADCC1D8DA384405BA2C9650231721D6F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the heads of any other relevant Federal department or agency, as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id002db0dcb4594036ad4938b89904a93d" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rulemaking on AI standardization for grid interconnection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission shall initiate a rulemaking to revise the pro forma Large Generator Interconnection Procedures promulgated pursuant to section 35.28(f) of title 18, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), to require public utility transmission providers to share and employ, as appropriate, queue management best practices with respect to the use of computing technologies, such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, or automation, in evaluating and processing interconnection requests, in order to expedite study results with respect to those requests.</text></section><section id="idb7fd1e1e872b4a7ca7362796ae77abc5" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>7.</enum><header>Ensuring energy security for datacenters and computing resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><paragraph id="ida928b501c27441f59598bf78f1263581"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assesses—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfa6456eac22e487ea4fc58c6d03463a0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the growth of computing data centers and advanced computing electrical power load in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1995fcb054ca47e28569d92fafb3067f"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">potential risks of growth in computing centers or growth in the required electrical power to United States energy and national security; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idef82c57adade43b2b0fc2e04bc3ac530"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the extent to which emerging technologies, such as artificial intelligence and advanced computing, may impact hardware and software systems used at data and computing centers; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0141a58853c54561bfe9ab09e1ee8673"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides recommendations for—</text><subparagraph id="id71af8fd5bfe343e58e6ea65498333345"><enum>(A)</enum><text>resources and capabilities that the Department may provide to promote access to energy resources by data centers and advanced computing; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id97b4294e595d49f381da5a17aeb815d2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>policy changes to ensure domestic deployment of data center and advanced computing resources prevents offshoring of United States data and resources; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8ac1fff6ee3446bb9d81b7983afa2372"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improving the energy efficiency of data centers, advanced computing, and AI. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="id16e7adcc0cac4937a2886377ac43d2eb" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>8.</enum><header>Office of Critical and Emerging Technology</header><subsection id="id44a6483258d147c49e456df8ade20c8a"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Department of Energy Organization Act is amended by inserting after section 215 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7144b">42 U.S.C. 7144b</external-xref>) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id20464E3E0E124209A49A53167FE8CDE4" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><section id="idf0c36edd47364abb967f7e98001b4e42"><enum>216.</enum><header>Office of Critical and Emerging Technology</header><subsection id="idfde2ec61e5a54b98adc8a1527b15de59"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id94983d1f77f84e7cb3d2dae3b34b915d"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical and emerging technology</header><text>The term <term>critical and emerging technology</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idab318a28074147fdb219ff144833bcec"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advanced technology that is potentially significant to United States competitiveness, energy security, or national security, such as biotechnology, advanced computing, and advanced manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbd61923de9e449ba8ce3fda6ce8aef2b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>technology that may address the challenges described in subsection (b) of section 10387 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddd646a523d5e4e4ba3496273f2d32269"><enum>(C)</enum><text>technology described in the key technology focus areas described in subsection (c) of that section (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id1d553f8823444158937713c76d7adfc9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department capabilities</header><text>The term <term>Department capabilities</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id4fe026b0bf984cfbad2c93dbeb17c791"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each of the National Laboratories (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9258ffba629243d38a8af5ce1270f171"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each associated user facility of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id17533e024a2940cb95bbaf1445644f5c"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of Critical and Emerging Technology described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd9c587a3d8024c5eaf5873a91f6af7ec"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <term>Office</term> means the Office of Critical and Emerging Technology established by subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf06c14f156eb4f46b9f1b02d9dad7313"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There shall be within the Office of the Under Secretary for Science and Innovation an Office of Critical and Emerging Technology. </text></subsection><subsection id="idf106daa476c04123a9644e546b4bf984"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Office shall be—</text><paragraph id="id36ab7482d1674093bf9f1827f62d0401"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to work across the entire Department to assess and analyze the status of and gaps in United States competitiveness, energy security, and national security relating to critical and emerging technologies, including through the use of Department capabilities; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9b5eb9b6ecb444be922174f85c9d8079"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to leverage Department capabilities to provide for rapid response to emerging threats and technological surprise from new emerging technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idea80f49f0c45473cbabeac61adda7511"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to promote greater participation of Department capabilities within national science policy and international forums; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id042ed2856bd84bd8bef12fb7f8c12468"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to inform the direction of research and policy decisionmaking relating to potential risks of adoption and use of emerging technologies, such as inadvertent or deliberate misuses of technology. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd8db58a88e7d47039b3a0b734769f25f"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Director of critical and emerging technology</header><text>The Office shall be headed by a director, to be known as the <quote>Director of Critical and Emerging Technology</quote>, who shall—</text><paragraph id="idf1cc560150574feda3906d2f3890a4e0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be appointed by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide2f494e873114a1aa9554b20ef446aa5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be an individual who, by reason of professional background and experience, is specially qualified to advise the Secretary on matters pertaining to critical and emerging technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idcf3b5f045fd74c6fb19e57ca4581bdb7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In carrying out the mission and activities of the Office, the Director shall closely collaborate with all relevant Departmental entities, including the National Nuclear Security Administration and the Office of Science, to maximize the computational capabilities of the Department and minimize redundant capabilities. </text></subsection><subsection id="id76ff0a5eb5c44f3c95a30894a56329a7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the mission and activities of the Office, the Director—</text><paragraph id="idC89767D9B9054540B12EE32E293132E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall coordinate with senior leadership across the Department and other stakeholders (such as institutions of higher education and private industry);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0BF0BDD0D88F4F409675FE3CA32F6F3D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall ensure the coordination of the Office of Science with the other activities of the Department relating to critical and emerging technology, including the transfer of knowledge, capabilities, and relevant technologies, from basic research programs of the Department to applied research and development programs of the Department, for the purpose of enabling development of mission-relevant technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id543535583AA84AAB8FDD0F5B1C361DAA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall support joint activities among the programs of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idFDFD7D32EDEF46D79F86F35746411C9D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall coordinate with the heads of other relevant Federal agencies operating under existing authorizations with subjects related to the mission of the Office described in subsection (c) in support of advancements in related research areas, as the Director determines to be appropriate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id87D6A84FDD9F4E4782C0808EB9B9346B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>may form partnerships to enhance the use of, and to ensure access to, user facilities by other Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id72d7562281394d75a19f4aa9ba5abc32"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Planning, assessment, and reporting</header><paragraph id="ide3f157dc78ea468c9f923016a181c784"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Department of Energy AI Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a critical and emerging technology action plan and assessment, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="id6d4417d7b82d49b386c6915fa9b715d7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a review of current investments, programs, activities, and science infrastructure of the Department, including under National Laboratories, to advance critical and emerging technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbe7fc1940afc438982c2a161dbff9be1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of any shortcomings of the capabilities of the Department that may adversely impact national competitiveness relating to emerging technologies or national security; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd6591dc724af485c9d7fc6d52f8ae510"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a budget projection for the subsequent 5 fiscal years of planned investments of the Department in each critical and emerging technology, including research and development, infrastructure, pilots, test beds, demonstration projects, and other relevant activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id687dd9472c554ec28ac1eaa4a8f41ae7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Every 2 years after the submission of the plan and assessment under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to Congress—</text><subparagraph id="id20774379f79a41c480a482bca8c30338"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an updated emerging technology action plan and assessment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6ffc0404e8b849e7abcb04be2f0cb55e" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a report that describes the progress made toward meeting the goals set forth in the emerging technology action plan and assessment submitted previously.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="id6228f2e899c042cda817caa311ea3815"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for the Department of Energy Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/91">Public Law 95–91</external-xref>; 91 Stat. 565; 119 Stat. 764; 133 Stat. 2199) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 215 the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id139D323BF09F4512873FE471F4B91D3B" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><toc changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSEG00"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 216. Office of Critical and Emerging Technology.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body><legis-body display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause"><section id="idc9da9ce2-f78b-483a-92f2-f76f5a925604" section-type="section-one" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Energy AI Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="idfe3c9883-0ec8-4cda-829f-dc9ea229939d" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="ida4a726da-6abf-42d8-b254-53f3a0c2de4f"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Department has a leading role to play in making the most of the potential of artificial intelligence to advance the missions of the Department relating to national security, science, and energy (including critical materials);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida9c144ef-e5de-44da-99ea-715edb3e817f"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the 17 National Laboratories employ over 40,000 scientists, engineers, and researchers with decades of experience developing world-leading advanced computational algorithms, computer science research, experimentation, and applications in machine learning that underlie artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id50f95ad2-b7ff-4351-b2e1-f93a70ef44ea"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the NNSA manages the Stockpile Stewardship Program established under section 4201 of the Atomic Energy Defense Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/2521">50 U.S.C. 2521</external-xref>), which includes the Advanced Simulation and Computing program, that provides critical classified and unclassified computing capabilities to sustain the nuclear stockpile of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id258d06ad-2096-4529-9b44-8c74716fb4a1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>for decades, the Department has led the world in the design, construction, and operation of the preeminent high-performance computing systems of the United States, which benefit the scientific and economic competitiveness of the United States across many sectors, including energy, critical materials, biotechnology, and national security; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7524f124-0bda-4c53-938b-5757f5e96b5f"><enum>(5)</enum><text>across the Department's network of 34 user facilities, scientists generate tremendous volumes of high-quality open data across diverse research areas, while the NNSA has always generated the foremost datasets in the world on nuclear deterrence and strategic weapons;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5c7416c3-d2ee-4ff6-92d2-df781f6b85f4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the unrivaled quantity and quality of open and classified scientific datasets of the Department is a unique asset to rapidly develop frontier AI models;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb5443673-1549-4f6d-ac46-0e8a6105fb03"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Department already develops cutting-edge AI models to execute the broad mission of the Department, including AI models developed by the Department that are used to forecast disease transmission for COVID–19, and address critical material issues and emerging nuclear security missions; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7a41a255-e66a-4b1d-9ba8-b98e98861cd0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the AI capabilities of the Department will underpin and jumpstart a dedicated, focused, and centralized AI program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6ad254d0-5444-4714-9a8c-fc1b1cd97678"><enum>(9)</enum><text>under section 4.1(b) of Executive Order 14110 (88 Fed. Reg. 75191 (November 1, 2023)) (relating to the safe, secure, and trustworthy development and use of artificial intelligence), the Secretary is tasked to lead development in testbeds, national security protections, and assessment of artificial intelligence applications. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida627f51b-b4bf-47cc-a4c1-a772c8eddd8e" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="id8f6c4783-84ee-489d-b398-26f91507b14e"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI; artificial intelligence</header><text>The terms <term>AI</term> and <term>artificial intelligence</term> have the meaning given the term <term>artificial intelligence</term> in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4e119f34-c403-4624-81d0-5456697a03f4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alignment</header><text>The term <term>alignment</term> means a field of AI safety research that aims to make AI systems behave in line with human intentions.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6d0dfe43-ae92-438a-84d5-c6685a23429a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Energy, including the NNSA.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id226dc19f-43d9-45b8-a29b-923410e57695"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><text>The term <term>foundation model</term> means an AI model that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5bd56095-1afd-4d0b-8b62-a38eaafad5ce"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is trained on broad data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id245ea797-5381-4f57-85e9-9b88e4eab560"><enum>(B)</enum><text>generally uses self-supervision;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id6054ef7c-60a9-45f2-8533-3677bb4c057d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>contains at least tens of billions of parameters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id92714e01-d862-4323-ba36-81956889151c"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is applicable across a wide range of contexts; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idda731a2e-7a82-4981-9cc0-dba6ad4a709d"><enum>(E)</enum><text>exhibits, or could be easily modified to exhibit, high levels of performance at tasks that pose a serious risk to the security, national economic security, or national public health or safety of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8f58505c-1d0e-486d-9ef1-bb3841fc5a5b"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Frontier AI</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id585822fe-37e0-4196-a906-29b212c9af1f"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>frontier AI</term> means the leading edge of AI research that remains unexplored and is considered to be the most challenging, including models—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idab9a57f0-011c-4d6c-9ec0-ecbb52564fb6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that exceed the capabilities currently present in the most advanced existing models; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0ce5c035-753e-4761-af6a-3c67696cf3a1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>many of which perform a wide variety of tasks.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfeed3e63-ae10-4427-bdf7-3a648c83e86c"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The term <term>frontier AI</term> includes AI models with more than 1,000,000,000,000 parameters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7848a5f4-763d-4bbb-adc2-45fda1845cb9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id971f65b9-4552-4837-a94e-4d37af14dc2d"><enum>(7)</enum><header>NNSA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>NNSA</quote> means the National Nuclear Security Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc2c67c8f-84dc-42de-a90b-2a246b1ce1fd"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ideba7c29f-2606-4163-a2b6-7bddd7c6ca5d"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means any platform, facility, or environment that enables the testing and evaluation of scientific theories and new technologies, including hardware, software, or field environments in which structured frameworks can be implemented to conduct tests to assess the performance, reliability, safety, and security of a wide range of items, including prototypes, systems, applications, AI models, instruments, computational tools, devices, and other technological innovations. </text></paragraph></section><section id="id1e5f99ae-80d1-4aac-8884-112c207036b2" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>4.</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research to deployment</header><subsection id="id8ee5ac11-eaf6-4f4c-863a-d15b04210ee5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program to develop and deploy frontiers in artificial intelligence for science, security, and technology (FASST)</header><paragraph id="id325c8766-3dde-46eb-a3ee-c42309803fdf"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a centralized AI program to carry out research on the development and deployment of advanced artificial intelligence capabilities for the missions of the Department (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>program</quote>), consistent with the program established under section 5501 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9461">15 U.S.C. 9461</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id76c3e67a-a9c6-4698-b9a4-80d23c771490"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program components</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3e9341e8-f2d9-4ada-924c-e0348c704a65"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program shall advance and support diverse activities that include the following components:</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6e141990-336d-4592-aa54-e5ab8d637f0d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Aggregation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddc7c07a3-40e7-46f6-8dec-7468420a67ed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Development and deployment of next-generation computing platforms and infrastructure.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id400b6e94-29cb-48e5-9c0e-32ad48fac8aa"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Development and deployment of safe and trustworthy AI models and systems.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0b19e111-a892-4ae2-97c6-060a595ef16a"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Tuning and adaptation of AI models and systems for pressing scientific, energy, and national security applications.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id665349f3-0b11-43d6-9978-881d7f2ca643"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Aggregation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(i), the Secretary shall develop methods, platforms, protocols, and other tools required for efficient, safe, secure, and effective aggregation, generation, curation, and distribution of AI training datasets, including—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide962bd79-59b1-464a-ba4e-700a30998f37"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assembling, aggregating, and curating large-scale training data for advanced AI, including outputs and synthetic data from research programs of the Department and other open science data, with the goal of developing comprehensive scientific AI training databases and testing and validation data;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idedcaaf3d-65cb-40e6-83c9-23d8a5c64126"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing and executing appropriate data management plan for the ethical, responsible, and secure use of classified and unclassified scientific data;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id4c435da8-5427-4604-9fd9-8b604e053388"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifying, restricting, securing, curating, and safely distributing, as appropriate based on the application—</text><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id137a8b9a-2d9a-4e6b-96aa-4de3e79699f9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>scientific and experimental Departmental datasets; and </text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="ida5f3aba3-6e58-41e0-9387-d020a4833ad0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>sponsored research activities that are needed for the training of foundation and adapted downstream AI models; and</text></subclause></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idb29c514e-35bb-4305-8741-03c0f04cd037"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>partnering with stakeholders to identify, secure, and curate critical datasets that reside outside the Department but are determined to be critical to optimizing the capabilities of open-science AI foundation models, national security AI foundation models, applied energy AI foundation models, and other AI technologies developed under the program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idfb00b3e4-f6ad-4e48-9618-942a87dbbd2d"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Development and deployment of next-generation computing platforms and infrastructure</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(ii), the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id119b8852-ecb8-4ae9-9f10-902d5899b5e8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop early-stage and application-stage AI testbeds to test and evaluate new software, hardware, algorithms, and other AI-based technologies and applications;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idabedd252-a7e5-4702-8eb6-dacff248a022"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop and deploy new energy-efficient AI computing hardware and software infrastructure necessary for developing and deploying trustworthy and secure interoperable frontier AI systems that leverage the high-performance computing capabilities of the Department and the National Laboratories;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idf9bf12f4-148b-4119-80c2-f5f98bf844a7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>facilitate the development and deployment of unclassified and classified high-performance computing systems and AI platforms through Department-owned infrastructure data and computing facilities;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idfa93706a-b629-410f-a6d0-8ece55e19916"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>procure interoperable high-performance computing and other resources necessary for developing, training, evaluating, and deploying AI foundation models and AI technologies; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id77aefee9-d7fb-4d9f-a74b-5744b8ffe060"><enum>(v)</enum><text>use appropriate supplier screening tools available through the Department to ensure that procurements under clause (iv) are from trusted suppliers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id74db616c-f07b-4e2c-a6c6-cd6c1f3baa0a"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Development and deployment of safe, secure, and trustworthy AI models and systems</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(iii), not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id5747f714-cbd9-46f2-a37f-8d1cc1151e70"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop innovative concepts and applied mathematics, computer science, engineering, and other science disciplines needed for frontier AI;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id2f4342ee-3d53-41a5-9276-70480a046160"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>develop best-in-class AI foundation models and other AI technologies for open-science, applied energy, and national security applications;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id7d04f7a5-3c60-4653-b6c7-7bfab7008066"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>research, develop, and deploy counter-adversarial artificial intelligence solutions to predict, prevent, mitigate, and respond to threats to critical infrastructure, energy security, nuclear nonproliferation, biological and chemical threats, and cyber threats;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id641ed7d2-a18e-4736-a143-75aac4960532"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>establish crosscutting research efforts on AI risks, reliability, safety, cybersecurity, trustworthiness, and alignment, including the creation of unclassified and classified data platforms across the Department; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id323a55aa-26b2-480f-aa8c-ec50269f3f86"><enum>(v)</enum><text>develop capabilities needed to ensure the safe, secure, and responsible implementation of AI in the private and public sectors that—</text><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idbac61f44-148a-4429-bcf6-7c55637b70c3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may be readily applied across Federal agencies and private entities to ensure that open-science models are released, operated, and managed responsibly, securely, and in the national interest; and</text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id3d311c08-59ea-4b37-82e4-ca451494dd99"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensure that classified national security models are secure, responsibly-managed, and safely implemented in the national interest. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id35135bf2-f731-41dc-add9-ec3aa8ddb69a"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Tuning and adaptation of AI models and systems for pressing scientific, applied energy, and national security applications</header><text>In carrying out the component of the program described in subparagraph (A)(iv), the Secretary shall—</text><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="idd75c88ab-c9f5-4a9e-9061-859595bd9367"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use AI foundation models and other AI technologies to develop a multitude of tuned and adapted downstream models to solve pressing scientific, applied energy, and national security challenges;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id1f1e4ec2-9cac-480e-8969-2659f6d6be8b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carry out joint work, including public-private partnerships, and cooperative research projects with industry, including end user companies, hardware systems vendors, and AI software companies, to advance AI technologies relevant to the missions of the Department;</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id9fdc22fb-9a34-4c60-85d4-c503dbf34cd0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>form partnerships with other Federal agencies, institutions of higher education, and international organizations aligned with the interests of the United States to advance frontier AI systems development and deployment; and</text></clause><clause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id80394851-f3b0-4239-b118-2a006e681966"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>increase research experiences and workforce development, including training for undergraduate and graduate students in frontier AI for science, energy, and national security.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida63c498c-01d0-4cc4-a02c-be172bdb394a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program, the Secretary shall develop a strategic plan with specific short-term and long-term goals and resource needs to advance applications in AI for science, energy, and national security to support the missions of the Department, consistent with—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id267844cd-1300-4f15-9780-881dea1f8980"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the 2023 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>Advanced Research Directions on AI for Science, Energy, and Security</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id6efd92d1-165c-4ed4-9f0b-40851262b2ad"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the 2024 National Laboratory workshop report entitled <quote>AI for Energy</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4d31ba65-6c77-4a8a-9a7f-8c48ba5527bf"><enum>(4)</enum><header>AI talent</header><text>As part of the program, the Secretary shall develop the required workforce, and hire and train not fewer than 500 new researchers to meet the rising demand for AI talent—</text><subparagraph id="idd41a9935-2e32-4562-80ed-0170d1b972f4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with a particular emphasis on expanding the number of individuals from underrepresented groups pursuing and attaining skills relevant to AI; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc9c7d686-f13f-459d-baa3-e92ae46629af"><enum>(B)</enum><text>including by—</text><clause id="id2561d0b0-29e5-4a82-b9bb-d63f7c4514a7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>providing training, grants, and research opportunities;</text></clause><clause id="id476bff41-d13c-455e-a46d-ed665a161906"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>carrying out public awareness campaigns about AI career paths; and</text></clause><clause id="id25b636b8-b937-427e-be32-5bfcef1dfbbe" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>establishing new degree and certificate programs in AI-related disciplines at universities and community colleges. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd720e07e-ad55-458a-86c9-5ee38ea3ec8f"><enum>(b)</enum><header>AI Research and Development Centers</header><paragraph id="id8ed30a22-3693-4a31-9f87-9798778bd5b3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall select, on a competitive, merit-reviewed basis, National Laboratories to establish and operate not fewer than 8 multidisciplinary AI Research and Development Centers (referred to in this subsection as <quote>Centers</quote>)—</text><subparagraph id="id662df458-a276-4076-a49b-11c782b37260"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to accelerate the safe, secure, and trustworthy deployment of AI for science, energy, and national security missions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id00adee91-bd14-4245-ab7e-aaa2eb70d686"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to demonstrate the use of AI in addressing key challenge problems of national interest in science, energy, and national security; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id52e595fa-64e8-4a9b-bb7f-771abf5c33e3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to maintain the competitive advantage of the United States in AI.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idc11c0f38a56549479be7283dd3421c00" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations for selection</header><text>In selecting National Laboratories under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall, to the maximum extent practicable—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0665c3750ec948188e4c6d172a1ae778"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that at least 1 Center focuses on applied energy activities carried out by the Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, the Office of Fossil Energy and Carbon Management, or the Office of Nuclear Energy; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2373f6480ad34679a74132d10ace100a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider geographic diversity to leverage resources and facilities of National Laboratories and partners in different regions. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idccb33701-618d-4284-9054-4035ff1b7d9d"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Focus</header><text>Each Center shall bring together diverse teams from National Laboratories, Department user facilities, academia, and industry to collaboratively and concurrently deploy hardware, software, numerical methods, data, algorithms, and applications for AI and ensure that the frontier AI research of the Department is well-suited for key Department missions, including by using existing and emerging computing systems and datasets to the maximum extent practicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb7cad9f8-7724-452d-89e0-7686c604af2b"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Administration</header><subparagraph id="id76a5eb85-afce-4e9d-8b1f-6881b0fd0fae"><enum>(A)</enum><header>National laboratory</header><text>Each Center shall be established as part of a National Laboratory.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id58ae2f53-175d-41e4-b811-3eda23836946"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for selection to establish and operate a Center under paragraph (1), a National Laboratory shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0d5cc9a6-e6c5-46e1-a7b9-7fb263417f95"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Director</header><text>Each Center shall be headed by a Director, who shall be the Chief Executive Officer of the Center and an employee of the National Laboratory described in subparagraph (A), and responsible for—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf3410ad8-d3fd-4839-bb1d-4074a6a9b685"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">successful execution of the goals of the Center; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddb56a3cd-bfe9-4fbf-9fc5-314377dd61ff"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating with other Centers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf23abf4f-2824-4088-9c00-d5abebf08373"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Technical roadmap</header><text>In support of the strategic plan developed under subsection (a)(3), each Center shall—</text><clause id="id9cb40edf-7f55-4748-9786-81e4fb2590a9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>set a research and innovation goal central to advancing the science, energy, and national security mission of the Department; and</text></clause><clause id="id8a557dec-24de-4af1-8b1c-7e7afa4656ef"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish a technical roadmap to meet that goal in not more than 7 years.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id16563bdc-d8e6-4671-acf7-24dbedef7b76"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall coordinate, minimize duplication, and resolve conflicts between the Centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf988b0f9-dea1-4e12-b8a6-9f22e151c9f9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>AI risk evaluation and mitigation program</header><paragraph id="id041c9357-064c-4931-becc-e598d94c6808"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI risk program</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), and consistent with the missions of the Department, the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of Defense, the Director of National Intelligence, the Director of the National Security Agency, and the Secretary of Commerce, shall carry out a comprehensive program to evaluate and mitigate safety and security risks associated with artificial intelligence systems (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>AI risk program</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3e49128a-4462-4715-93e5-01056bf5a810"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Risk taxonomy</header><subparagraph id="id60e6af8e-3a76-490d-b94d-cc8b4ceb0f83"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the AI risk program, the Secretary shall develop a taxonomy of safety and security risks associated with artificial intelligence systems and datasets relevant to the missions of the Department, including, at a minimum, the risks described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9b6e65c8-9daf-41cc-b22a-01d3c5af3106"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Risks described</header><text>The risks referred to in subparagraph (A) are the abilities of artificial intelligence—</text><clause id="id27ef968a-ece4-42f9-b3a0-546cf2eb5ad2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to generate information at a given classification level;</text></clause><clause id="id509533f9-8764-40fe-a510-b3a196220f4c"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to assist in generation of nuclear weapons information;</text></clause><clause id="id57603365-b498-456c-8603-e884d6900b3e"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to assist in generation of chemical, biological, radiological, nuclear, nonproliferation, critical infrastructure, and other economic, security, or energy threats;</text></clause><clause id="id897a9ae7-25e1-4b23-b280-4e7005fe71e1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to assist in generation of malware and other cyber and adversarial tactics, techniques, and procedures that pose a significant national security risk, such as threatening the stability of critical national infrastructure;</text></clause><clause id="idad7fd0ec-0b60-465f-8307-e75dc1a90931"><enum>(v)</enum><text>to undermine public trust in the use of artificial intelligence technologies or in national security; </text></clause><clause id="idc808f997-fa61-4e52-bcca-cbe074a19879"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>to deceive a human operator or computer system, or otherwise act in opposition to the goals of a human operator or automated systems;</text></clause><clause id="id40212d80-dc8c-42f5-bcb2-e66a6276d5b1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>to act autonomously with little or no human intervention in ways that conflict with human intentions;</text></clause><clause id="id1c807073ae9044e7a6dd8c4e857346a6"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>to be vulnerable to data compromise by malicious cyber actors; and</text></clause><clause id="id30a214485f924f2c98ace6dfe043ff89"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>to be vulnerable to other emerging or unforeseen risk, as determined by the Secretary. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id97dbdb4f-5b59-4137-8737-bff224dd14e1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Shared resources for AI</header><paragraph id="id4a749362-9845-4fcd-b575-fc95eb494e7c"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As part of the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall identify, support, and sustain shared resources and enabling tools that have the potential to reduce cost and accelerate the pace of scientific discovery and technological innovation with respect to the missions of the Department relating to science, energy, and national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9bc365fc-e0cc-4d7c-ae1f-cb9038433367"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with relevant experts in industry, academia, and the National Laboratories. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1a58606a-e4ef-431a-8c22-7dec69b78f89"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Focus</header><text>Shared resources and enabling tools referred to in paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="idcd8490a7-4dcf-4ffc-abd3-3c1ce687f27f"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Scientific data and knowledge bases for training AI systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id33904f7a-adbe-4913-82b8-36770587036b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Benchmarks and competitions for evaluating advances in AI systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idccd072c0-7cba-40b5-a927-b332f56e24a7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Platform technologies that lower the cost of generating training data or enable the generation of novel training data.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id876b11e1-ccd7-4a77-a5c7-de4c20e0c0aa"><enum>(D)</enum><text>High-performance computing, including hybrid computing systems that integrate AI and high-performance computing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd821c2e1-0942-4768-9ca9-cecaa560f43c"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The combination of AI and scientific automation, such as cloud labs and self-driving labs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf0b54196-03ce-4442-aa22-394a3defa91f"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Tools that enable AI to solve inverse design problems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2a1c3a37-547c-4518-952e-524e694a2479"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Testbeds for accelerating progress at the intersection of AI and cyberphysical systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida9cfad10-e83f-4a01-9fd5-0ffb6caa474f"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="id298fe0c2-bcc3-406e-b29e-2e890d0135a2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research security</header><text>The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id38f14f47-72e5-4fff-8a19-9cb66d60bcdf"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cybersecurity</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure the integration of robust cybersecurity and data security measures into all AI research-to-deployment efforts authorized under this section to protect the integrity and confidentiality of collected and analyzed data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb722207f-31a6-4ff8-91e0-8597ac774772"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Partnerships with private entities</header><subparagraph id="id0ab43936-112a-4a10-99d0-b37211242bcc"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to establish partnerships with private companies and nonprofit organizations in carrying out this Act, including with respect to the research, development, and deployment of each of the 4 program components described in subsection (a)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id42c7513f-471f-4213-bea6-5b96598b43c1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall protect any information submitted to or shared by the Department consistent with applicable laws (including regulations).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id55f86442edb042fa925ee49c025b1b24"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary shall, to the maximum extent practicable, consider leveraging existing resources from public and private sectors. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idedd6a7d4-c18b-4093-b929-9704404fd089"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress an annual report describing—</text><paragraph id="ida497b7d5-e376-4e8c-8289-75b95e28e16d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the progress, findings, and expenditures under each program established under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb284462a-2a20-4488-961b-b0004e1b34b1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any legislative recommendations for promoting and improving each of those programs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id5193327d-303d-463d-a2b2-406d18f706ba" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal permitting</header><subsection id="id202f72d1-3317-49f7-9f5e-70d9e5e9a22c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a program to improve Federal permitting processes for energy-related projects, including critical materials projects using artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="id444eedc4-fe31-4de7-a5c7-679f147087a7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program components</header><text>In carrying out the program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall carry out activities, including activities that—</text><paragraph id="id02773a59-3846-4431-a6a9-d6d81ac06634"><enum>(1)</enum><text>generate, collect, and analyze data and provide tools from past environmental and other permitting reviews, including by—</text><subparagraph id="id8b752006-4e21-4139-864f-76768f41f7cc"><enum>(A)</enum><text>extracting data from applications for comparison with data relied on in environmental reviews to assess the adequacy and relevance of applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idb170eaac-ed70-4499-af30-f2109a8b4d67"><enum>(B)</enum><text>extracting information from past site-specific analyses in the area of a current project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id00c92f20-d307-4c42-96a6-919a1c4aa12e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>summarizing key mitigation actions that have been successfully applied in past similar projects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id34928ee4-b9d3-418a-9c6e-e34ffd580ac1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>using AI for deeper reviews of past determinations under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) to inform more flexible and effective categorical exclusions; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id41e9e1da-66bc-41ce-b604-7425d8b94661"><enum>(2)</enum><text>build tools to improve future reviews, including—</text><subparagraph id="idb9a4f9d2-2712-4c00-86dd-b97761533c6a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>tools for project proponents that accelerate preparation of environmental documentation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab666c58-ba9b-44e1-8d48-54b02c86f7ee"><enum>(B)</enum><text>tools for government reviewers such as domain-specific large language models that help convert geographic information system or tabular data on resources potentially impacted into rough-draft narrative documents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id96bcc00c-fc7d-4996-baf3-1830a2aaaa54"><enum>(C)</enum><text>tools to be applied in nongovernmental settings, such as automatic reviews of applications to assess the completeness of information; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id076ee56e-cde4-4587-b169-675e3b1b7a7e"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a strategic plan to implement and deploy online and digital tools to improve Federal permitting activities, developed in consultation with—</text><clause id="idbe970f8c-c482-40cd-9650-83b16b4197c4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior;</text></clause><clause id="id97853ad0-ecdc-400f-85a1-ebd3997a6ba6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System land;</text></clause><clause id="idd125cba5-5801-438b-80e1-d2b0a6bb8925"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Executive Director of the Federal Permitting Improvement Steering Council established by section 41002(a) of the FAST Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4370m-1">42 U.S.C. 4370m–1(a)</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="ida2108724-d3b4-4a71-8711-bb7f83aea888"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the heads of any other relevant Federal department or agency, as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb9fcbd01eb364cac822a3d8643c81921"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interagency access</header><text>The Secretary shall make available to Federal agencies—</text><paragraph id="id47c64eed9dfc4f609ce5e68153e99e0d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the code for any artificial intelligence developed in furtherance of the program established under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id99fa282bd1474ce4b41f3cb5b0bbfdeb"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the training dataset curated under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1358185ce6544d6a8237ce1ac863d77b"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the particular environmental documents used in that training dataset. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idf03ed588-9761-4f49-a2a9-cd87f5b2ce3e" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rulemaking on AI standardization for grid interconnection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission shall initiate a rulemaking to revise the pro forma Large Generator Interconnection Procedures promulgated pursuant to section 35.28(f) of title 18, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), to require public utility transmission providers to share and employ, as appropriate, queue management best practices with respect to the use of computing technologies, such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, or automation, in evaluating and processing interconnection requests, in order to expedite study results with respect to those requests.</text></section><section id="id45263344-3d9c-4d79-903b-88e3ea8f41f8" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>7.</enum><header>Ensuring energy security for datacenters and computing resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><paragraph id="id02281e88-e6f6-420d-bd5b-b4b98171de25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assesses—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7835b3fe-1ddf-4487-93dd-16ad4f975dad"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the growth of computing data centers and advanced computing electrical power load in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9b6b6769-61d6-4fce-b581-48307dee3dd0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">potential risks of growth in computing centers or growth in the required electrical power to United States energy and national security;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc11cc1e0bdd74804b873cbbca3018f12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the national security impacts of computing data centers being manipulated through nefarious means to cause broad impacts to energy reliability; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf8150eac-8488-4e03-9ae4-22b0f6724f8a"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the extent to which emerging technologies, such as artificial intelligence and advanced computing, may impact hardware and software systems used at data and computing centers; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9ec365d4-d138-407f-9f12-7007007c7029"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides recommendations for—</text><subparagraph id="id28005d10-5c86-4f59-b680-ff71e981fe0a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>resources and capabilities that the Department may provide to promote access to energy resources by data centers and advanced computing; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id8a5d736d-605a-4a04-9b7d-56c549b49ec5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>policy changes to ensure domestic deployment of data center and advanced computing resources prevents offshoring of United States data and resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idccab7cdb-9770-436a-8515-b995811aab10"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improving the energy efficiency of data centers, advanced computing, and AI; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2838634a65d34964bce5843c9dd55840"><enum>(D)</enum><text>enhancing collaboration and resource sharing between National Laboratories and other applicable entities to maximize scientific output and accelerate AI innovation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="id3bbab56f-62ac-463e-bd3d-c4b21d7bf6b9" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>8.</enum><header>Office of Critical and Emerging Technology</header><subsection id="id449f57c7-35db-4cd7-b17c-7be7cb9dd2d8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Department of Energy Organization Act is amended by inserting after section 215 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7144b">42 U.S.C. 7144b</external-xref>) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide18cd053-e577-4c27-b604-1b40d843fdf2" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><section id="ida5484d1f-e451-47d0-9bb4-c436c671745a"><enum>216.</enum><header>Office of Critical and Emerging Technology</header><subsection id="id08d44302-6b4b-46fe-9bc9-24dea7108b17"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id5de7852b-c689-4ce7-8f23-430efd1c5f6b"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical and emerging technology</header><text>The term <term>critical and emerging technology</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id4eb08b57-9cbd-4396-9e1e-d759ebadf0c3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advanced technology that is potentially significant to United States competitiveness, energy security, or national security, such as biotechnology, advanced computing, and advanced manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3a190c1a-6fa7-458b-ab96-3abd2fb25668"><enum>(B)</enum><text>technology that may address the challenges described in subsection (b) of section 10387 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd4b6e646-f05f-4edc-a38e-0734da43c6ee"><enum>(C)</enum><text>technology described in the key technology focus areas described in subsection (c) of that section (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd346b19f-642c-42ff-9e7b-2113e12a96b7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department capabilities</header><text>The term <term>Department capabilities</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id74df8e0e-ae5f-4897-8732-bdb49c951515"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each of the National Laboratories (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf3399f2e-f7a9-41d7-b854-6cba5a2a00d0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each associated user facility of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id23721888-cd6e-4070-83de-a0a624606e3e"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of Critical and Emerging Technology described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbf0f5449-e7c7-4c21-992e-428cc443b3c7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <term>Office</term> means the Office of Critical and Emerging Technology established by subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idce0cd4be-0882-41ff-acac-a71d4a1b5bfc"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There shall be within the Office of the Under Secretary for Science and Innovation an Office of Critical and Emerging Technology. </text></subsection><subsection id="id22337a1a-2344-4e94-aaf4-6590874907d9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Office shall be—</text><paragraph id="idc7c50ba0-2870-4dfa-962c-d3ebbeea3391"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to work across the entire Department to assess and analyze the status of and gaps in United States competitiveness, energy security, and national security relating to critical and emerging technologies, including through the use of Department capabilities; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8ba9eea8-b320-4295-9f72-427738f08787"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to leverage Department capabilities to provide for rapid response to emerging threats and technological surprise from new emerging technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id06338836-c661-4eba-b224-d437451c95da"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to promote greater participation of Department capabilities within national science policy and international forums; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf62acbbb-45f1-4a09-ae70-f651129a5cf0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to inform the direction of research and policy decisionmaking relating to potential risks of adoption and use of emerging technologies, such as inadvertent or deliberate misuses of technology. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id5b5a6fb7-ca5c-4d05-9d34-85568d05ba10"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Director of critical and emerging technology</header><text>The Office shall be headed by a director, to be known as the <quote>Director of Critical and Emerging Technology</quote>, who shall—</text><paragraph id="id9f92af65-1a00-4c98-9b3b-534517264efa"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be appointed by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id862e396a-b9ac-49b2-ba5b-af379b2446fb"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be an individual who, by reason of professional background and experience, is specially qualified to advise the Secretary on matters pertaining to critical and emerging technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id56a13f9a-1b8d-4056-858b-7a7b70196461"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In carrying out the mission and activities of the Office, the Director shall closely collaborate with all relevant Departmental entities, including the National Nuclear Security Administration, the applied energy offices, and the Office of Science, to maximize the computational capabilities of the Department and minimize redundant capabilities. </text></subsection><subsection id="id36b9d751-ab12-4579-80f1-f15108457e9c"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the mission and activities of the Office, the Director—</text><paragraph id="idebd9c7c5-0498-424f-bdfa-c668be4faf10"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall coordinate with senior leadership across the Department and other stakeholders (such as institutions of higher education and private industry);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd6f2e3fb-72e1-47b4-a7c2-a9ec15b3e19b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall ensure the coordination of the Office of Science with the other activities of the Department relating to critical and emerging technology, including the transfer of knowledge, capabilities, and relevant technologies, from basic research programs of the Department to applied research and development programs of the Department, for the purpose of enabling development of mission-relevant technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id982ad204-f0b6-462b-81ef-21e2fa9b5ee2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall support joint activities among the programs of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf11b1deb-e727-4221-a4c6-7bbe5943cd8a"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall coordinate with the heads of other relevant Federal agencies operating under existing authorizations with subjects related to the mission of the Office described in subsection (c) in support of advancements in related research areas, as the Director determines to be appropriate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id242c7f40-d755-47a6-a850-8456c8133aa9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>may form partnerships to enhance the use of, and to ensure access to, user facilities by other Federal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd6e3c3c4-d9cd-48c2-b884-19bc7b13170b"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Planning, assessment, and reporting</header><paragraph id="id369cb052-d324-4ecf-b8cf-ea64e49b8e3c"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Department of Energy AI Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a critical and emerging technology action plan and assessment, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="id55121432-3394-4f0c-8ac9-865e41aa52c2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a review of current investments, programs, activities, and science infrastructure of the Department, including under National Laboratories, to advance critical and emerging technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida0f0a7dd-a195-4b4b-81c6-884ad6976434"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of any shortcomings of the capabilities of the Department that may adversely impact national competitiveness relating to emerging technologies or national security; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7f10a681-465b-45e1-9621-a09decf6950a"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a budget projection for the subsequent 5 fiscal years of planned investments of the Department in each critical and emerging technology, including research and development, infrastructure, pilots, test beds, demonstration projects, and other relevant activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida8121164-966b-44c3-bc2a-ea66549d436c"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Every 2 years after the submission of the plan and assessment under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to Congress—</text><subparagraph id="id86b9813a-c459-4624-bd23-a817b60a6882"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an updated emerging technology action plan and assessment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf8e63aed-ed7b-442e-81a9-8865aa57226a" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a report that describes the progress made toward meeting the goals set forth in the emerging technology action plan and assessment submitted previously.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="ide2b9ac5e-f1a1-4a69-8494-2ab3ce7c6b96"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for the Department of Energy Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/91">Public Law 95–91</external-xref>; 91 Stat. 565; 119 Stat. 764; 133 Stat. 2199) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 215 the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id515eeb92-aafb-4ca2-8b39-d3cc47eca81a" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 216. Office of Critical and Emerging Technology.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="ided885bf2d9704332b5ed487e434fc1c2" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSEG00"><enum>9.</enum><header>Office of Intelligence and Counterintelligence review of visitors and assignees</header><subsection id="ida21035ba18fd45248bb86f107a57390a"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id8a01de9a4a8448d1a966aac69df32938"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="idb3f43d216cf849b8b9dfab63d8dabbb5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the congressional intelligence committees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7303c387add7428188fd685ff98d6e17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id88e7575123554a9d9b4a72a1001e6ea1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id29ae4dc6dc1941789642a6bde838cd16"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Country of risk</header><text>The term <term>country of risk</term> means a country identified in the report submitted to Congress by the Director of National Intelligence in 2024 pursuant to section 108B of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3043b">50 U.S.C. 3043b</external-xref>) (commonly referred to as the <quote>Annual Threat Assessment</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id83263079a6c5423495e7b9ca7e6917a5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered assignee; covered visitor</header><text>The terms <quote>covered assignee</quote> and <quote>covered visitor</quote> mean a foreign national from a country of risk that is <quote>engaging in competitive behavior that directly threatens U.S. national security</quote>, who is not an employee of either the Department or the management and operations contractor operating a National Laboratory on behalf of the Department, and has requested access to the premises, information, or technology of a National Laboratory.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida22ad778d60d4d799e998b3a99cfe743"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office of Intelligence and Counterintelligence of the Department (or their designee).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide5f73fb064ec485691d8f1fcc9961bbe"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foreign national</header><text>The term <term>foreign national</term> has the meaning given the term <term>alien</term> in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id195bce895ea84ba8939804c463550490"><enum>(6)</enum><header>National laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfb5a06b5ea304574846c24d6c2731950"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Nontraditional intelligence collection threat</header><text>The term <term>nontraditional intelligence collection threat</term> means a threat posed by an individual not employed by a foreign intelligence service, who is seeking access to information about a capability, research, or organizational dynamics of the United States to inform a foreign adversary or nonstate actor.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id58be748de11d4a1dabcd29e0b26bd702"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>The Senate finds the following:</text><paragraph id="id8876954c0548471092906aa8cbb185e8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The National Laboratories conduct critical, cutting-edge research across a range of scientific disciplines that provide the United States with a technological edge over other countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcaab47a336e84e158271e775c94c3108"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The technologies developed in the National Laboratories contribute to the national security of the United States, including classified and sensitive military technology and dual-use commercial technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc728d8b330934d768d11efcbf556c39d"><enum>(3)</enum><text>International cooperation in the field of science is critical to the United States maintaining its leading technological edge.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4de289ea81524bb18df6b85d6e215106"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The research enterprise of the Department, including the National Laboratories, is increasingly targeted by adversarial nations to exploit military and dual-use technologies for military or economic gain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3c747c7235254174926a655460b153c3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Approximately 40,000 citizens of foreign countries, including more than 8,000 citizens from China and Russia, were granted access to the premises, information, or technology of National Laboratories in fiscal year 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id98c89497295e4f888c88066c012b5dfe"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Office of Intelligence and Counterintelligence of the Department is responsible for identifying counterintelligence risks to the Department, including the National Laboratories, and providing direction for the mitigation of such risks.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id667f3465f17f46a4841de5f07e2e57e3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sense of the senate</header><text>It is the sense of the Senate that—</text><paragraph id="idd17cd7654dd646e28dbfb2e36f0f01b6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>before being granted access to the premises, information, or technology of a National Laboratory, citizens of foreign countries identified in the 2024 Annual Threat Assessment of the intelligence community as <quote>engaging in competitive behavior that directly threatens U.S. national security</quote> should be appropriately screened by the National Laboratory to which they seek access, and by the Office of Intelligence and Counterintelligence of the Department, to identify risks associated with granting the requested access to sensitive military, or dual-use technologies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id945885ec0c054e1e80a910c69bd63e0a"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identified risks should be mitigated.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide6b2c1592eee409eafce0d9f8a44948c"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Review of country of risk covered visitor and covered assignee access requests</header><text>The Director shall, in consultation with the applicable Under Secretary of the Department that oversees the National Laboratory, or their designee, promulgate a policy to assess the counterintelligence risk that covered visitors or covered assignees pose to the research or activities undertaken at a National Laboratory.</text></subsection><subsection id="id09e3f8ef3266441c972c4f35e37f71f2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advice with respect to covered visitors or covered assignees</header><paragraph id="id395fd845623643199d0957bc61835eca"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall provide advice to a National Laboratory on covered visitors and covered assignees when 1 or more of the following conditions are present:</text><subparagraph id="id3c8e1f2155df4c5a9dddd63249f14dba"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Director has reason to believe that a covered visitor or covered assignee is a nontraditional intelligence collection threat.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idfceaad86514c4ed798a9ccc6ec82198d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Director is in receipt of information indicating that a covered visitor or covered assignee constitutes a counterintelligence risk to a National Laboratory.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id801e674f55004aa4b67a572f2b4c10f6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Advice described</header><text>Advice provided to a National Laboratory in accordance with paragraph (1) shall include a description of the assessed risk.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id64c14df2c7354ff58a115ae2d86ac6ca"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Risk mitigation</header><text>When appropriate, the Director shall, in consultation with the applicable Under Secretary of the Department that oversees the National Laboratory, or their designee, provide recommendations to mitigate the risk as part of the advice provided in accordance with paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida7dd79535f254e51aa0be2e16669e25e"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and quarterly thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report, which shall include—</text><paragraph id="idc42de15d564542cf8e6838c3d08d3b8d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of covered visitors or covered assignees permitted to access the premises, information, or technology of each National Laboratory;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc570bbc6b9514223871d537c66f70b1d"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of instances in which the Director provided advice to a National Laboratory in accordance with subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf8822701802e41f6ae7063f97c2977b7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of instances in which a National Laboratory took action inconsistent with advice provided by the Director in accordance with subsection (e).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idfe65d15352d44928a5779915a2479fd4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2032.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20241121">November 21, 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

