<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2095DD0B4E87402581A85920B84DC82D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 8005 IH: Child Exploitation and Artificial Intelligence Expert Commission Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-04-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 8005</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20240415">April 15, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000478">Mr. Fry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Commission of Experts on Child Exploitation and Artificial Intelligence.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC533568F19E7409FA5466FE61F9D0F4E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H624EA41A14974906AAD4786C25E85D0E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Child Exploitation and Artificial Intelligence Expert Commission Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H064D44FD9B0046059DA63A2318E3FA05"><enum>2.</enum><header>Commission of Experts on Child Exploitation and Artificial Intelligence</header> <subsection id="HF7B2980B0F8E4799BA3069541ABD40E3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a commission, to be known as the <quote>Commission of Experts on Child Exploitation and Artificial Intelligence</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>), which shall investigate and make recommendations on solutions to improve the ability of a law enforcement agency to prevent, detect, and prosecute child exploitation crimes committed using artificial intelligence.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5A991C41892642DB9A71203763D99B1C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties of Commission</header><text>The Commission shall—</text> <paragraph id="H3171FE556B1F4A209B135B5571CB9217"><enum>(1)</enum><text>investigate and assess how artificial intelligence may be used in the commission of a child exploitation crime;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE7CE3A50F984BE7A65CB444D60DA995" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the ability of a law enforcement agency to prevent, detect, and prosecute child exploitation crimes committed using artificial intelligence under the law in effect during the period of the evaluation of the Commission, including by identifying any statutory language, constitutional provision, or court decision that impedes such prosecutions; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39A00E2EE6C343EDB0AA67ABEBFC4F53"><enum> (3)</enum><text>recommend solutions to improve the ability of a law enforcement agency to prevent, detect, and prosecute child exploitation crimes committed using artificial intelligence, including recommendations for statutory or constitutional amendments to address the statutory language, constitutional provisions, or court decisions identified under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H301F9E80E92B4E249DAC7419E4252C43" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<paragraph id="H911AAC25CFF64057867242A1DEB9BB2F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may submit interim reports to the Congress containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations as have been agreed to by the Commission. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H711F0634277246C29D695670CF889444" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date on which 13 members have been appointed to the Commission under subsection (d), the Commission shall submit a final report to the Congress containing such findings, conclusions, and recommendations as have been agreed to by the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H85BE06083C48455F9C60821FCF04B83A" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<paragraph id="H210C868621DD497794DBBCDA65F5222A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number and appointment</header><text>The Commission shall be composed of 13 members appointed as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H9E7C8BE183914970BD6E670CFFE55902"><enum>(A)</enum><text>7 members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H65A855C5379B452ABF736E0E7FD87145"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 members appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC47468372914731AA6901B447014704"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 members appointed by the majority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD5E63715235F4AF4B11FB4F341623B7D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 members appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H4ECB607A2CD44E488CC7C2B4B112614C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual appointed to the Commission shall have expertise in law enforcement, artificial intelligence, technology ethics, child psychology, or a related field. </text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE47114A42F614490A2193CF236F85E84"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nongovernmental appointees</header><text>An individual appointed to the Commission may not be an officer or employee of the Federal Government or any State or unit of local government. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5E415A45FFB746E8A481C7BAE672D8F3" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall be appointed for the life of the Commission.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HECA812A1A4C6458BAEE2122E833717C4" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall be appointed not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D46F0CC740A4680961C732CF0FA2AE5" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>No compensation</header><text>Members shall serve without pay, but shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4972275C02E74AFFB4567E8E11EB46FD" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Chairperson; Vice Chairperson</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall elect a Chairperson and Vice Chairperson from among the members of the Commission. The term of office of the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson shall be for the life of the Commission. </text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H9EF5374102CB4D598CF9E8E5D0E67D51" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Procedures of Commission</header> <paragraph id="H8C81B33CCD1C4F5FB1B49CD214B3BE17" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date on which 13 members have been appointed to the Commission under subsection (d), the Commission shall hold an initial meeting, at which the members of the Commission shall elect the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson. Thereafter, the Commission shall meet—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4D166786FC25464DB09571A9972BCF3B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>quarterly; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA848460EC9D4F89BD5C835A814E680B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at the call of a majority of its members. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE3A108D79BCC4225904C2E4C9B77BE64" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A majority of the members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum to conduct business, but the Commission may establish a lesser quorum for conducting hearings scheduled by the Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B9B60E514FB4698BE4C61771192C838"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Voting</header><text>No proxy voting shall be allowed on behalf of a member of the Commission.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H59310736375E4E1281F4DD96CC541AD5" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rules</header><text>The Commission may establish by majority vote any other rules for the conduct of Commission business, if such rules are not inconsistent with this section or any other applicable law.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HDF0443088F7F449DBF3089652CD9BD98" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Staff of commission; experts and consultants</header> <paragraph id="HA6B7508F0DD14842B3C8320EE1EF9B4B" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>Subject to rules prescribed by the Commission, the Chairperson may appoint and fix the pay of a staff director and additional personnel as the Chairperson considers appropriate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2DC48CF922464BAFA35C434C8E973AB9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of certain civil service laws</header><text>The staff director and personnel of the Commission may be appointed without regard to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service, and may be paid without regard to the provisions of chapter 51 and subchapter III of chapter 53 of that title relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates, except that an individual so appointed may not receive pay in excess of the annual rate of basic pay for level V of the Executive Schedule.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H362726437AD7474B9F6E769BBDA177CE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Personnel as Federal employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The staff director and any employee of the Commission shall be employees under section 2105 of title 5, United States Code, for purposes of chapters 63, 81, 83, 84, 85, 87, 89, and 90 of that title.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD8C59A323A03494A8BC17429757C2AEE" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Detailees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any Federal Government employee may be detailed to the Commission without reimbursement from the Commission, and such detail shall be without interruption or loss of civil service status or privilege.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H889BDD7D968D4305BEA0CC24094859EE" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Volunteer services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 1342 of title 31, United States Code, the Commission may accept and use voluntary and uncompensated services as the Commission determines necessary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4DE2919584F94485AD5E75B1F36ACCB8" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Experts and consultants</header><text>The Commission may procure temporary and intermittent services under section 3109(b) of title 5, United States Code, but at rates for individuals not to exceed the daily rate paid to a person occupying a position at level IV of the Executive Schedule.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H1C7F8545E49948AF9F6D520E2A52AA04"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header> <paragraph id="H2BBEE3DC5B54422294AAC026244F8A06"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hearings and sessions</header><text>The Commission may, for the purposes of carrying out this section, hold hearings, sit and act at times and places, take testimony, and receive evidence as the Commission considers appropriate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95A966BD08BD4F838C94F78D9DA00EBD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Obtaining official data</header><text>The Commission may secure directly from any department or agency of the United States information necessary to enable it to carry out this section. Upon the request of the Chairperson, the head of that department or agency shall furnish that information to the Commission. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49E49D069F844C9992E932FC4A2F4DC3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gifts, bequests, and devises</header><text>To the extent or in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts, the Commission may accept, use, and dispose of gifts, bequests, or devises of services or property, both real and personal, for the purposes of aiding or facilitating the work of the Commission. Gifts, bequests, or devises of money and proceeds from sales or other property received as gifts, bequests, or devises shall be deposited in the Treasury and shall be available for disbursement upon order of the Chairperson. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3753C44F4B59495999FE4ED94BFA43AB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Mails</header><text>The Commission may use the United States mails in the same manner and under the same conditions as departments and agencies of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80A6D0D78F044B03ADC4FBE95B0FDD94" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Administrative support services</header> <subparagraph id="H8EF097F203384D15A2EF60FF53620419" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>General services administration</header><text>Upon the request of the Commission, the Administrator of General Services shall provide to the Commission, on a reimbursable basis, the administrative support services necessary for the Commission to carry out its responsibilities under this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H390E1A7123E446D9998B2E2D45CCAB91" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other departments and agencies</header><text>In addition to the assistance prescribed in subparagraph (A), the head of a department or agency of the United States may provide to the Commission, on a reimbursable basis, such services, funds, facilities, staff, or other support services as such head may determine advisable and as may be authorized by law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H244251FC66FA40D894D843C2B6099D86"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><text>To the extent or in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts, the Commission may contract with and compensate government and private agencies or persons for any purpose necessary to enable it to carry out this section. </text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H7A39F48DCDF04DAA95699BC46E313D00" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header> 
<paragraph id="H671E093F712740EA95CDE9083D864175" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Chapter 10 of part I of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC6491FCB761D48EDB08B7B60DAD332E6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public meetings and release of public versions of reports</header><text>The Commission shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H46020AA63AE34257BB72E886101FA63F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hold public hearings and meetings to the extent appropriate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95CFF41D5B914E46B86C0CEE2993293F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>release a public version of each report submitted under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89278C41404249EF83E0B5C939AED0C7" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conduct of public hearings</header><text>Any public hearing of the Commission shall be conducted in a manner consistent with the protection of information provided to or developed for or by the Commission as required by any applicable statute, regulation, or Executive order.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H846F819EC1B14E669A49B560513D6F39" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Commission shall terminate 60 days after the date on which the Commission submits the final report under subsection (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H96FA3CD4F1F94268B23A0F093006BC0F"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HEFE27B5DAB9444648242E35CBC65F1FB" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> includes a machine-based system that uses data, references, or machine or human-based inputs to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4AD0426A53F94789B9297250FF01C964" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>create a visual depiction, including an image or video;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DB78BEDEE8B419093E11ECDD83145A0" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognize a pattern; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA9BA7C2CA47C45F0AD1B743449E1ACE5" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make a recommendation, prediction, or decision.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A6A486294AD4C2B88026275EB91A889"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Child exploitation crime</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>child exploitation crime</term> means a crime under any Federal, State, local, or Tribal law relating to the sexual exploitation of children.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF811D90A1744479E9E2BC78F1739B519"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Law enforcement agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>law enforcement agency</term> means any Federal, State, Tribal, or local governmental agency that is engaged in or supervises the prevention, detection, investigation, or prosecution of a violation of criminal law.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H482AECC41E0B4EB38F95E7804F19EE40"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, and any commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States. </text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

