<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BAG24E97-H52-8S-7W8"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>105 S4178 RS: Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-12-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 725</calendar><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 4178</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20240418">April 18, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S275">Ms. Cantwell</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S391">Mr. Young</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S408">Mr. Hickenlooper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S396">Mrs. Blackburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S318">Mr. Wicker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S409">Mr. Luján</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S403">Ms. Sinema</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S381">Mr. Rounds</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S270">Mr. Schumer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00" added-display-style="italic" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation</committee-name></action-desc></action><action stage="Reported-in-Senate"><action-date date="20241218" legis-day="20241216">December 18 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported by <sponsor name-id="S275">Ms. Cantwell</sponsor>, with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To establish artificial intelligence standards, metrics, and evaluation tools, to support artificial intelligence research, development, and capacity building activities, to promote innovation in the artificial intelligence industry by ensuring companies of all sizes can succeed and thrive, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb14ab0aef9114d75a89624568bc7f91f"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id8350c40fdf774513a6f80f289f2d70e5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc-entry level="section" idref="S1">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id60BEDC1E3E6A48ADA565EA8D973B3F90">Sec. 2. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id7288940c7fe74ac2a42093c51f762f00">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="id76483cb063f54e898bac70654370d31a">TITLE I—Voluntary artificial intelligence standards, metrics, evaluation tools, testbeds, and international cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="id960634b045b54773b0c2afabd7377e25">Subtitle A—Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute and testbeds</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="ida55b5f3d23684d2ba4979979d1f985b3">Sec. 101. Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id51e355273fb74377844c29e2776053e8">Sec. 102. Program on artificial intelligence testbeds.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idb8f4f3950559490b83e531e5da785fcb">Sec. 103. National Institute of Standards and Technology and Department of Energy testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idf5f20448fbb943399e8d75e86939f95e">Sec. 104. National Science Foundation and Department of Energy collaboration to make scientific discoveries through the use of artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id225d13e260a44ea8a75c78a823db9590">Sec. 105. Progress report.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="ide04b6fac777041ac914cd33806f9cb47">Subtitle B—International cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id3a3da24192d5481da71fd1bd11ece877">Sec. 111. International coalition on innovation, development, and harmonization of standards with respect to artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id49ebc682d2b44c2eb06bd87229ac215a">Sec. 112. Requirement to support bilateral and multilateral artificial intelligence research collaborations.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="ide672f82475cd4029b426da34c3d9d1e4">Subtitle C—Identifying regulatory barriers to innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idfcba1f603d1f4db297d86f5ea0f3e591">Sec. 121. Comptroller General of the United States identification of risks and obstacles relating to artificial intelligence and Federal agencies.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="id2f82f14e45a84b1494409b239ba637de">TITLE II—Artificial intelligence research, development, capacity building activities</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id9f26c79c63f4493d9663218910a83bb2">Sec. 201. Public data for artificial intelligence systems.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="ida6ed8675147d46dea082cdb2027b71e1">Sec. 202. Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id60BEDC1E3E6A48ADA565EA8D973B3F90" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that policies governing artificial intelligence should maximize the potential and development of artificial intelligence to benefit all private and public stakeholders.</text></section><section id="id7288940c7fe74ac2a42093c51f762f00" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="id804e95ea67784329875943533f472396"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3502 of title 44, United States Code, except such term shall include an independent regulatory agency, as defined in such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idda9661264d4149eb998e82c153fa26aa"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb7c19a1ad05e43eba5284facccdb319a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence blue-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence blue-teaming</term> means an effort to conduct operational network vulnerability evaluations and provide mitigation techniques to entities who have a need for an independent technical review of the network security posture of an artificial intelligence system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6d415a8c57e44143aec2d4b7a37a73bd"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence model</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence model</term> means a component of an artificial intelligence system that is a model—</text><subparagraph id="idecc6b8cd84d547c098897dafa7a396bc"><enum>(A)</enum><text>derived using mathematical, computational, statistical, or machine-learning techniques; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf2c8e4a3674e40f0b6d87f83f1c27484"><enum>(B)</enum><text>used as part of an artificial intelligence system to produce outputs from a given set of inputs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9c73b978cbb848e095be697cfee106cf"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence red-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence red-teaming</term> means structured adversarial testing efforts of an artificial intelligence system to identify risks, flaws, and vulnerabilities of the artificial intelligence system, such as harmful outputs from the system, unforeseen or undesirable system behaviors, limitations, or potential risks associated with the misuse of the system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idea0e449514224a21a6f70c6c291a83a2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework</header><text>The term <term>Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework</term> means the most recently updated version of the framework developed and updated pursuant to section 22A(c) of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id198baabafd2f4205b097e2d583807649"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence system</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence system</term> has the meaning given such term in section 7223 of the Advancing American AI Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/40/11301">40 U.S.C. 11301</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4bee5da2b34b471b9b6adbd9e05af7fb"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1016(e) of the Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism (USA PATRIOT ACT) Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id00136653EE324750A6DACEAA60FE9199"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Federal laboratory</header><text>The term <term>Federal laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3703">15 U.S.C. 3703</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbdb4881ce0ad48939e3e7a2470c3686e"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><text>The term <term>foundation model</term> means an artificial intelligence model trained on broad data at scale and is adaptable to a wide range of downstream tasks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4a80741623b449488a32a9d3b47bb574"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Generative artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>generative artificial intelligence</term> means the class of artificial intelligence models that utilize the structure and characteristics of input data in order to generate outputs in the form of derived synthetic content. Such derived synthetic content can include images, videos, audio, text, software, code, and other digital content.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4EF1B1A43EAE4D43B447FCF14513B3F9"><enum>(12)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd6499e7ce27d46e8ac780877fbbb0a2c"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Synthetic content</header><text>The term <term>synthetic content</term> means information, such as images, videos, audio clips, and text, that has been significantly modified or generated by algorithms, including by artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1181b386a56442ea8bea0a6ef7e04d01"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means a facility or mechanism equipped for conducting rigorous, transparent, and replicable testing of tools and technologies, including artificial intelligence systems, to help evaluate the functionality, trustworthiness, usability, and performance of those tools or technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idec0c6917923143eb8c94e17c18d3b8eb"><enum>(15)</enum><header>TEVV</header><text>The term <term>TEVV</term> means methodologies, metrics, techniques, and tasks for testing, evaluating, verifying, and validating artificial intelligence systems or components.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0688c60408f24b77bdf12e7cf9d49a3a" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Watermarking</header><text>The term <term>watermarking</term> means the act of embedding information that is intended to be difficult to remove, into outputs generated by artificial intelligence, including outputs such as text, images, audio, videos, software code, or any other digital content or data, for the purposes of verifying the authenticity of the output or the identity or characteristics of its provenance, modifications, or conveyance. </text></paragraph></section><title id="id76483cb063f54e898bac70654370d31a" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>I</enum><header>Voluntary artificial intelligence standards, metrics, evaluation tools, testbeds, and international cooperation </header><subtitle id="id960634b045b54773b0c2afabd7377e25"><enum>A</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute and testbeds</header><section id="ida55b5f3d23684d2ba4979979d1f985b3"><enum>101.</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</header><subsection id="idab970ceb0ab14018a4e7c7a237018023"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Institute</header><paragraph id="iddaa93ab7590b4317bd8e5937b4bb56df"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology (in this section referred to as the <quote>Under Secretary</quote>) shall establish an institute on artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf73da9ae5aef4f6784f90558dc737428"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The institute established pursuant to paragraph (1) shall be known as the <quote>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Institute</quote>). </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6ed1abc7a5c34610893e600330f93705"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Institute is as follows:</text><subparagraph id="id737ccb01bb9c438fb15f754d8e3e4a37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To assist the private sector and agencies in developing voluntary best practices for the robust assessment of artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3ccda1cd34e04f9b9a06bfedd0c350ef" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To provide technical assistance for the adoption and use of artificial intelligence across the Federal Government to improve the quality of government services. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide96a733f0e7e4fe7b47d64ed920f5040"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To develop guidelines, methodologies, and best practices to promote—</text><clause id="id9eb872d13f2646ed8cadd12a822f3159"><enum>(i)</enum><text>development and adoption of voluntary, consensus-based technical standards or industry standards; </text></clause><clause id="id3e2568f3aa4a433da1d1d4b703e99fb2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>long-term advancements in artificial intelligence technologies; and</text></clause><clause id="idc5ba44d382b2448a80d91802782e6c5c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>innovation in the artificial intelligence industry by ensuring that companies of all sizes can succeed and thrive.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id51ed83291f884469b4cf40be3b907736"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Under Secretary shall appoint a director of the Institute, who shall be known as the <quote>Director of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>) and report directly to the Under Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="idfc69927d813f458b98cbf4a80fb31c68"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staff and authorities</header><paragraph id="id87529f6127124b9fb0fdd2f7a60bf5a8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The Director may hire such full-time employees as the Director considers appropriate to assist the Director in carrying out the functions of the Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id142921983a604d57a5c7d32098ab6aa4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of authority to hire critical technical experts</header><text>In addition to making appointments under paragraph (1) of this subsection, the Director, in coordination with the Secretary of Commerce, may make appointments of scientific, engineering, and professional personnel, and fix their basic pay, under subsection (b) of section 6 of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/275">15 U.S.C. 275</external-xref>) to hire critical technical experts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idda287acebf0e42b687bf6ba61bffe269"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expansion of authority to hire critical technical experts</header><text>Such subsection is amended, in the second sentence, by striking <quote>15</quote> and inserting <quote>30</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1d6f8a8c32e1436fadbffdcabf247e9d"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Modification of sunset</header><text>Subsection (c) of such section is amended by striking <quote>the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this section</quote> and inserting <quote>December 30, 2035</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8147290a86564e2f950ef4b47e5511d9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>The Director may enter into such agreements, including contracts, grants, cooperative agreements, and other transactions, as the Director considers necessary to carry out the functions of the Institute and on such terms as the Under Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id760f3a03649c490a8afe3edd0039a55d"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation and coordination</header><text>In establishing the Institute, the Under Secretary shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb3ce1956ce9b4a11aa555b238950b42d"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate with—</text><subparagraph id="id2a315d97bda1455dae35d067e0b0f07d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6909a757366248b0bef55c52ca88d91a"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id28128f893fff41a5903ab2f03e7001df"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4152dd152aa34b7ba0a096337c519bab"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Director of the National Science Foundation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id832797a608074c53a9c158db3bdbfa2a"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id770ab2a0742e4658b38ec27fa5144d9d"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consult with the heads of such other Federal agencies as the Under Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id98db7565326548be933fcec41c010edf"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The functions of the Institute, which the Institute shall carry out in coordination with the laboratories of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, are as follows:</text><paragraph id="id016bb264eed3453797a4f6ff18f2b11c"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research, evaluation, testing, and standards</header><text>The following functions relating to research, evaluation, testing, and standards:</text><subparagraph id="id167290c8000045069330907b03766094"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Conducting measurement research into system and model safety, validity and reliability, security, capabilities and limitations, explainability, interpretability, and privacy. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ideb9c850e59b946eda35a02a206f20945"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Working with the Department of Energy, the National Science Foundation, public-private partnerships, including the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute Consortium established under subsection (f), and other private sector organizations to develop testing environments and perform regular benchmarking and capability evaluations, including artificial intelligence red-teaming as the Director considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9e8dd82563414739bc701a8552baeec3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Working with consensus-based, open, and transparent standards development organizations (SDOs) and relevant industry, Federal laboratories, civil society, and academic institutions to advance development and adoption of clear, implementable, technically sound, and technology-neutral voluntary standards and guidelines that incorporate appropriate variations in approach depending on the size of the entity, the potential risks and potential benefits of the artificial intelligence system, and the role of the entity (such as developer, deployer, or user) relating to artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ided996e1406a944abad9ee4e2a06d4232"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Building upon the Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework to incorporate guidelines on generative artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3eaee57371d34c58b90f0af35e27019b"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Developing a companion resource to the Secure Software Development Framework to incorporate secure development practices for generative artificial intelligence and for foundation models. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2ba0f30ccc564f30b2b48a097fbdfd88"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Developing and publishing cybersecurity tools, methodologies, best practices, voluntary guidelines, and other supporting information to assist persons who maintain systems used to create or train artificial intelligence models to discover and mitigate vulnerabilities and attacks.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id85690551b4444435a17fcade623908db"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Coordinating or developing guidelines, metrics, benchmarks, and methodologies for evaluating artificial intelligence systems, including the following:</text><clause id="id4e4dd03640ce498d8f6ca4cdb659eb0a"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Cataloging existing artificial intelligence metrics, benchmarks, and evaluation methodologies used in industry and academia.</text></clause><clause id="idd91c6b791f904c33be397a509948b7a1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Testing and validating the efficacy of existing metrics, benchmarks, and evaluations, as well as TEVV tools and products.</text></clause><clause id="idb3aa54d4c578444eb4eaa57fbad8fb64"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Funding and facilitating research and other activities in a transparent manner, including at institutions of higher education and other nonprofit and private sector partners, to evaluate, develop, or improve TEVV capabilities, with rigorous scientific merit, for artificial intelligence systems.</text></clause><clause id="idd951f241038f4d06a0350ecc24d79ad8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Evaluating foundation models for their potential effect in downstream systems, such as when retrained or fine-tuned.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id823b15865035499587edda0dd6247789"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Coordinating with counterpart institutions of international partners and allies to promote global interoperability in the development of research, evaluation, testing, and standards relating to artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9332015031b248b4889a0bd9e6bd4562"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Developing tools, methodologies, best practices, and voluntary guidelines for identifying vulnerabilities in foundation models.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id01d685c073d646d8a6d5771fe5c91686"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Developing tools, methodologies, best practices, and voluntary guidelines for relevant agencies to track incidents resulting in harm caused by artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7507dfb832a94cadbf6b2aadb83891b9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The following functions relating to implementation:</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc3af067e411442dcbd37e5b62a75b2ac"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using publicly available and voluntarily provided information, conducting evaluations to assess the impacts of artificial intelligence systems, and developing guidelines and practices for safe development, deployment, and use of artificial intelligence technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbb7fb745c5ed4b71b8fd9cc3a6fc6fb7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Aligning capability evaluation and red-teaming guidelines and benchmarks, sharing best practices, and coordinating on building testbeds and test environments with allies of the United States and international partners and allies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id299b688231964a648cd0f6a298e62869"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Coordinating vulnerability and incident data sharing with international partners and allies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1a07e6be738f44d9aae4a9c99254f8d7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Integrating appropriate testing capabilities and infrastructure for testing of models and systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id99acd363bf0f4ad6a17cd6d59fc10d0f"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Establishing blue-teaming capabilities to develop mitigation approaches and partner with industry to address risks and negative impacts.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida7fd40d576864a2eaad8ebcc558256d2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Developing voluntary guidelines on—</text><clause id="id8e0dd60bcfd94f13b3515f79ec0f8ca2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>detecting synthetic content, authenticating content and tracking of the provenance of content, labeling original and synthetic content, such as by watermarking, and evaluating software and systems relating to detection and labeling of synthetic content;</text></clause><clause id="id43c19127aab941199cd3e9210c88e1ca"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensuring artificial intelligence systems do not violate privacy rights or other rights; and</text></clause><clause id="id44130e1dd8194f61a01115065e891a9f"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>transparency documentation of artificial intelligence datasets and artificial intelligence models.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1007f05d11aa4223948db582fade5267"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Coordinating with relevant agencies to develop or support, as the heads of the agencies determine appropriate, sector- and application-specific profiles of the Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework for different use cases, integrating end-user experience and on-going development work into a continuously evolving toolkit. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idde750bca9ad04771a938f9601587d48b"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Operations and engagement</header><text>The following functions relating to operations and engagement:</text><subparagraph id="id49ca331823b44b1cae9f986599a09da6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Managing the work of the Institute, developing internal processes, and ensuring that the Institute meets applicable goals and targets.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc82007deac9b4a0a96745d21b0f2661e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Engaging with the private sector to promote innovation and competitiveness.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcccb6b7c0cb54dc7a911c18a34d30c1b"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Engaging with international standards organizations, multilateral organizations, and similar institutes among allies and partners.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id24b2a3362da3464caa5940f8113726ee"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute Consortium</header><paragraph id="id7a215920ab0d43a6a95197ac47118118"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><subparagraph id="idfa87317be4ef4443965d97eee625a9ac"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary shall establish a consortium of stakeholders from academic or research communities, Federal laboratories, private industry, including companies of all sizes with different roles in the use of artificial intelligence systems, including developers, deployers, and users, and civil society with expertise in matters relating to artificial intelligence to support the Institute in carrying out the functions set forth under subsection (e).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd4ba607a63c34448af380562c3b89cd4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The consortium established pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be known as the <quote>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute Consortium</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id95d0670e5f2b4823b8299dc104a3fec7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Under Secretary, acting through the Director, shall consult with the consortium established under this subsection not less frequently than quarterly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9f1952021526439e9164608ae397b8a9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report summarizing the contributions of the members of the consortium established under this subsection in support the efforts of the Institute.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ide9cd7045e6654d86a08649dd042d82cb"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence system testing</header><text>In carrying out the Institute functions required by subsection (a), the Under Secretary shall support and contribute to the development of voluntary, consensus-based technical standards for testing artificial intelligence system components, including, as the Under Secretary considers appropriate, the following:</text><paragraph id="idea9e1f2f641f408d813fa4382e251ddb"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Physical infrastructure for training or developing artificial intelligence models and systems, including cloud infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5a5bb5aee0074643a212bfb2b8f76114"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Physical infrastructure for operating artificial intelligence systems, including cloud infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd3060a8eee264d1090ff481d30fa4f49"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Data for training artificial intelligence models.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id453922c803c541f6a8306d0a2abb5bb0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Data for evaluating the functionality and trustworthiness of trained artificial intelligence models and systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4bf757ddbce241678d5eea6504feb423"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Trained or partially trained artificial intelligence models and any resulting software systems or products.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf8d79c43bc4f4cc18e58203de54c030d"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Gifts</header><paragraph id="id6378dd2d8eb644b28c3eee3178854873"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Director may seek, accept, hold, administer, and use gifts from public and private sources whenever the Director determines it would be in the interest of the United States to do so.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc562d29d85ab4be7895ee06794a17518"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Director, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, shall ensure that authority under this subsection is exercised consistent with all relevant ethical constraints and principles, including—</text><subparagraph id="id86451e28d76a4633b6f3bd26961e7af8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the avoidance of any prohibited conflict of interest or appearance of impropriety; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idc43d646bbe544e26bc46dc455415717f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a prohibition against the acceptance of a gift from a foreign government or an agent of a foreign government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id77bd8e9081544106ba5d39f1212e92ab"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to provide the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology any enforcement authority that was not in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="id51e355273fb74377844c29e2776053e8"><enum>102.</enum><header>Program on artificial intelligence testbeds</header><subsection id="id21ba54eb772641efa330bca45010af77"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="ida9d437a3e745401a8661b0d47e81586e"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id2ecdbf6107674a24906c561fda360eab"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idaf41f5141571477696d56b3be41e90f4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id40feecbf59774b2fab33bd6b028b053b"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Science Foundation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id706147dbb0db4308a58503a2184f885a"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institute</header><text>The term <term>Institute</term> means the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute established by section 101.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9175c7069fb84ae08d454c00c65e7944"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5485ea2c05e347a4ae210dcefaa56a21"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Under Secretary</term> means the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id00d8549b6cb4469086d22b71a83fdaf0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary shall, in coordination with the Secretary and the Director, establish and commence carrying out a testbed program to encourage collaboration and support partnerships between the National Laboratories, the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource pilot program established by the Director of the National Science Foundation, or any successor program, and public and private sector entities, including companies of all sizes, to conduct research and development, tests, evaluations, and risk assessments of artificial intelligence systems, including measurement methodologies developed by the Institute.</text></subsection><subsection id="id7ae16ace0c964a0ea983ad6e2ee86550"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out this program, the Under Secretary shall, in coordination with the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="idb3f225c049b84935ab9ea3354ff46231"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use the advanced computing resources, testbeds, and expertise of the National Laboratories, the Institute, the National Science Foundation, and private sector entities to run tests and evaluations on the capabilities and limitations of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddc4ab83941eb4e5e9dda55e0255f24ad"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use existing solutions to the maximum extent practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id43b38950feab4722a8bc5ac49030e691"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop automated and reproducible tests, evaluations, and risk assessments for artificial intelligence systems to the extent that is practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id704c14085bfb4c259db9fbda107dd110"><enum>(4)</enum><text>assess the computational resources necessary to run tests, evaluations, and risk assessments of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb20e9f07eed34f169823df6eb3fdd932"><enum>(5)</enum><text>research methods to effectively minimize the computational resources needed to run tests, evaluations, and risk assessments of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5cf3c70dd7b64612acfbbadea6d33a2a"><enum>(6)</enum><text>consider developing tests, evaluations, and risk assessments for artificial intelligence systems that are designed for high-, medium-, and low-computational intensity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd6da19ee667b46b287cd081fe39dd8c4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>prioritize identifying and evaluating scenarios in which the artificial intelligence systems tested or evaluated by a testbed could be deployed in a way that poses security risks, and either establishing classified testbeds, or utilizing existing classified testbeds, at the National Laboratories if necessary, including with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="id49e8ec555d4a47e895406c44b1fa7a34"><enum>(A)</enum><text>autonomous offensive cyber capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcd3ad472a0824e889d84cc5267e12041"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cybersecurity vulnerabilities in the artificial intelligence software ecosystem and beyond;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7fb977a9ad89475f8fd3babe5f4d8680"><enum>(C)</enum><text>chemical, biological, radiological, nuclear, critical infrastructure, and energy-security threats or hazards; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida2fa5fd5928646a28397447de2c63a26"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other capabilities as the Under Secretary determines necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id33b10b874d0e494487e7e6594cee9651"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consideration given</header><text>In carrying out the activities required by subsection (c), the Under Secretary shall, in coordination with the Secretary, take under consideration the applicability of any tests, evaluations, and risk assessments to artificial intelligence systems trained using primarily biological sequence data, including those systems used for gene synthesis. </text></subsection><subsection id="id45794b50ad534b1480bca598b5be8150"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text>The Under Secretary, in collaboration with the Secretary, shall develop metrics—</text><paragraph id="idd8352739aaba49669b2891610bd8adf2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to assess the effectiveness of the program in encouraging collaboration and supporting partnerships as described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2c726a86fa7c43fea8752cf7159e6e09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to assess the impact of the program on public and private sector integration and use of artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id89e8e9f0644948cc8f9f0cd70bbb39e3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of existing program</header><text>In carrying out the program required by subsection (a), the Under Secretary may, in collaboration with the Secretary and the Director, use a program that was in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="idd9a8818a41c4472e86c1885682f7b812"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluation and findings</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the start of this program, the Under Secretary shall, in collaboration with the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="id766d6914381c4591a9f17068750d2067"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the success of the program in encouraging collaboration and supporting partnerships as described in subsection (b), using the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (e); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfa8c5c8c41f3403ab24c94f7e5e3d50b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the success of the program in encouraging public and private sector integration and use of artificial intelligence systems by using the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id309bca786f2f463aa1301cab2728c34d"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate committees of Congress the evaluation supported pursuant to paragraph (1) and the findings of the Under Secretary, the Secretary, and the Director with respect to the testbed program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id99b0b2d762ee4573a961e173da0fb81a"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out subsection (b), the Under Secretary shall consult, as the Under Secretary considers appropriate, with the following:</text><paragraph id="id828be42f6eb747e1b2ccbec822872305"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Industry, including private artificial intelligence laboratories, companies of all sizes, and representatives from the United States financial sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc21c07f2f8a34c25884a0b1861d45d8e"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Academia and institutions of higher education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4f230e4418224157a65315a9615c640e"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Civil society.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb705d456013d46ccb1bd5cca9366cbee"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Third-party evaluators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id13f9bcd9007141b2abcba9402ac709a2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Establishment of foundation models test program</header><text>In carrying out the program under subsection (b), the Under Secretary shall, acting through the Director of the Institute and in coordination with the Secretary of Energy, carry out a test program to provide vendors of foundation models the opportunity to voluntarily test foundation models across a range of modalities, such as models that ingest and output text, images, audio, video, software code, and mixed modalities, relative to the Artificial Intelligence Risk Management Framework, by—</text><paragraph id="id5432aab0a8e14c5c96188406bd8c96d3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conducting research and regular testing to improve and benchmark the accuracy, efficacy, and bias of foundation models;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5908995ad3e4428798b1a49c017737bd"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conducting research to identify key capabilities, limitations, and unexpected behaviors of foundation models;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc3a0df59e7aa44048e17a3f81a6ff804"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identifying and evaluating scenarios in which these models could pose risks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfed47a0a080d44538d188eafcaa8fc2d"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establishing reference use cases for foundation models and performance criteria for assessing each use case, including accuracy, efficacy, and bias metrics;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida2265131f7694c2eb4e76973e194df90"><enum>(5)</enum><text>enabling developers and deployers of foundation models to evaluate such systems for risks, incidents, and vulnerabilities if deployed in such use cases;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida8c5adf86688415681419aabe2e06cb7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>coordinating public evaluations, which may include prizes and challenges, to evaluate foundation models; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id64b64c7f52154c5f993c53dd79dee71b"><enum>(7)</enum><text>as the Under Secretary and the Secretary consider appropriate, producing public-facing reports of the findings from such testing for a general audience.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id397850d786474072867c6d22b10c187e"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a person to disclose any information, including information—</text><paragraph id="idba068a16efc44159938b8314b15ee6fa"><enum>(1)</enum><text>relating to a trade secret or other protected intellectual property right;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7f9d3dfa503a4a0b91519820ba8f793b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is confidential business information; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9bff6633903b4e3ca18cf0d4e5489363"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that is privileged.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idb8f4f3950559490b83e531e5da785fcb"><enum>103.</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology and Department of Energy testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials</header><subsection id="idb29416eeaa8a47429479c27611d1312f"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Testbed authorized</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and the Secretary of Energy shall jointly establish a testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials to advance materials science and to support advanced manufacturing for the benefit of the United States economy through the use of artificial intelligence, autonomous laboratories, and artificial intelligence integrated with emerging technologies, such as quantum hybrid computing and robotics.</text></subsection><subsection id="id2cc10dd5033a4bb696231b5f328b7a7d"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Support for accelerated technologies</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall ensure that technologies accelerated using the testbed established pursuant to subsection (a) are supported by advanced algorithms and models, uncertainty quantification, and software and workforce development tools to produce benchmark data, model comparison tools, and best practices guides.</text></subsection><subsection id="idd6521be8d8c74e519d5a6ea7f5caa8dd"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public-Private partnerships</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall, in consultation with industry, civil society, and academia, enter into such public-private partnerships as the Secretaries jointly determine appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="id499b4b7900f44618a62bce7cf58075da"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretaries may use resources from National Laboratories and the private sector.</text></subsection></section><section id="idf5f20448fbb943399e8d75e86939f95e"><enum>104.</enum><header>National Science Foundation and Department of Energy collaboration to make scientific discoveries through the use of artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="id85234f9a9032494097bd9ec037f69e5c"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation (referred to in this section as the <quote>Director</quote>) and the Secretary of Energy (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall collaborate to support new translational scientific discoveries and advancements for the benefit of the economy of the United States through the use of artificial intelligence, including artificial intelligence integrated with emerging technologies, such as quantum hybrid computing and robotics.</text></subsection><subsection id="id6f2569f29e0c497d860d316eeb71a8fa"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public-Private partnerships</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Director and the Secretary shall enter into such public-private partnerships as the Director and the Secretary jointly determine appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="id1ca902066b624847b9e6e9255b31d710"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Director and the Secretary may accept and use resources from the National Laboratories, resources from the private sector, and academic resources.</text></subsection></section><section id="id225d13e260a44ea8a75c78a823db9590"><enum>105.</enum><header>Progress report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute shall, in coordination with the Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy, submit to Congress a report on the implementation of this subtitle. </text></section></subtitle><subtitle id="ide04b6fac777041ac914cd33806f9cb47"><enum>B</enum><header>International cooperation </header><section id="id3a3da24192d5481da71fd1bd11ece877"><enum>111.</enum><header>International coalition on innovation, development, and harmonization of standards with respect to artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="idf7796ea05cec4eecb6c744ad89fd4104"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of State, and the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy (in this section referred to as the “Director”), in consultation with the heads of relevant agencies, shall jointly seek to form an alliance or coalition with like-minded governments of foreign countries—</text><paragraph id="idc755b7dbcabf417a89a711a360335895"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to cooperate on approaches to innovation and advancements in artificial intelligence and ecosystems for artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb0e8e84c18f046ed9db263b23087a86c"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to coordinate on development and use of interoperable international standards or harmonization of standards with respect to artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2c24efb61b9b450cb442e8238e2eb9ef"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to promote adoption of common artificial intelligence standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcbe6820acacc445591ed4d6775064c2b"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to develop the government-to-government infrastructure needed to facilitate coordination of coherent global application of artificial intelligence safety standards, including, where appropriate, putting in place agreements for information sharing between governments; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0d4eed6491d641ca800ca182e1480b8c"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to involve private-sector stakeholders from partner countries to help inform coalition partners on recent developments in artificial intelligence and associated standards development.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd6ffc5fb639043d88c0c375773de1092"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criteria for participation</header><text>In forming an alliance or coalition of like-minded governments of foreign countries under subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of State, and the Director, in consultation with the heads of relevant agencies, shall jointly establish technology trust criteria—</text><paragraph id="id74f02d50c3a94f609459af25fb087098"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to ensure all participating countries that have a high level of scientific and technological advancement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idaeec0544f10247db9326bbb430794590"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to ensure all participating countries commit to using open international standards; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida1eedc2ec4af404abb30cea33d5e1d16"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to support the governance principles for international standards as detailed in the World Trade Organization Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade, done at Geneva April 12, 1979, on international standards, such as transparency, openness, and consensus-based decision-making.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida3cf1066f1504d28b3589335bc0c1739"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation on innovation and advancements in artificial intelligence</header><text>In forming an alliance or coalition under subsection (a), the Director, the Secretary of Commerce, and the Secretary of State shall consult with the Secretary of Energy and the Director of the National Science Foundation on approaches to innovation and advancements in artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="idec1907bbd67a470b8f0dcc3835e3c96b"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Security and protection of intellectual property</header><text>The Director, the Secretary of Commerce, and the Secretary of State shall jointly ensure that an alliance or coalition formed under subsection (a) is only formed with countries that—</text><paragraph id="id7f9fc305d5b44bdc8741475a6841586d"><enum>(1)</enum><text>have in place sufficient intellectual property protections, safety standards, and risk management approaches relevant to innovation and artificial intelligence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7ef3976e2ec74d329c0258adc2ea72a1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and coordinate research security measures, export controls, and intellectual property protections relevant to innovation, development, and standard-setting relating to artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9fc9baa18699481ebeb4ba6a2603df1d"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit anyone from participating in other international standards bodies.</text></subsection></section><section id="id49ebc682d2b44c2eb06bd87229ac215a"><enum>112.</enum><header>Requirement to support bilateral and multilateral artificial intelligence research collaborations</header><subsection id="idc50a9fc03d9b42709f5d039db622eb3d"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation shall support bilateral and multilateral collaborations to facilitate innovation in research and development of artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb97a4e9f41a646a2904a498e870a9d04"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Alignment with priorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall ensure that collaborations supported under subsection (a) align with the priorities of the Foundation and United States research community and have the potential to benefit United States prosperity, security, health, and well-being.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb3a354c0ce47408091d8c3338c619c57"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall ensure that collaborations supported under subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="id9ef1a8f349424eb2af55fc6abd44e469"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support innovation and advancement in research on the development and use of artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idaec504aa150844a1b2c9721bc2dc950a"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate international collaboration on innovation and advancement in artificial intelligence research and development, including data sharing, expertise, and resources; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7a8c11c01fef4ed4a5a682ba2f0921a1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>leverage existing National Science Foundation programs, such as the National Science Foundation-supported National Artificial Intelligence Research Institutes and Global Centers programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id1866281c957d4161b6e0d5cebf568656" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination of security measures and export controls</header><text>When entering into agreements in order to support collaborations pursuant to subsection (a)<italic></italic>, the Director shall ensure that participating countries have developed and coordinated security measures and export controls to protect intellectual property and research and development. </text></subsection></section></subtitle><subtitle id="ide672f82475cd4029b426da34c3d9d1e4" style="OLC"><enum>C</enum><header>Identifying regulatory barriers to innovation</header><section id="idfcba1f603d1f4db297d86f5ea0f3e591"><enum>121.</enum><header>Comptroller General of the United States identification of risks and obstacles relating to artificial intelligence and Federal agencies</header><subsection id="id7cd3037c0929414ead5a357ea6dcc122"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on regulatory impediments to innovation in artificial intelligence systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="ide7a8856c415f45a8bdf508a48b55acea"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="id6f3bd4b83bf04b38bf530c51b65f0e9b"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Significant examples of Federal statutes and regulations that directly affect the innovation of artificial intelligence systems, including the ability of companies of all sizes to compete in artificial intelligence, which should also account for the effect of voluntary standards and best practices developed by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3a5f139c184645038add1ebe64e8eea9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of challenges that Federal agencies face in the enforcement of provisions of law identified pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id030c38f823df4a718b98f4070a35f28e"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An evaluation of the progress in government adoption of artificial intelligence and use of artificial intelligence to improve the quality of government services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbc50bb774cda45d9923403368906193f" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Based on the findings of the Comptroller General with respect to paragraphs (1) through (4), such recommendations as the Comptroller General may have for legislative or administrative action to increase the rate of innovation in artificial intelligence systems. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></subtitle></title><title id="id2f82f14e45a84b1494409b239ba637de" changed="deleted" reported-display-style="strikethrough" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>II</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research, development, capacity building activities</header><section id="id9f26c79c63f4493d9663218910a83bb2"><enum>201.</enum><header>Public data for artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="id64ee27c1773045b2a6480f51b6cd626b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>List of priorities</header><paragraph id="idff809723524d4e4c9ba574cb96e8957a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To expedite the development of artificial intelligence systems in the United States, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall, acting through the National Science and Technology Council and the Interagency Committee established or designated pursuant to section 5103 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413</external-xref>), develop a list of priorities for Federal investment in creating or improving curated, publicly available Federal Government data for training and evaluating artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idfa525c9b1c0349708922dcb38f9c8e32"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf305adc66e69402ea81d4a1f39cf2bfe"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The list developed pursuant to paragraph (1) shall—</text><clause id="idd812474834b84df98062c9b4a3e59478"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prioritize data that will advance novel artificial intelligence systems in the public interest; and</text></clause><clause id="id01fab618c0a34679a0c5c330fa8b2713"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prioritize datasets unlikely to independently receive sufficient private sector support to enable their creation, absent Federal funding.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb7db8df5de8c4f579aeb3531dbc6a14b"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Datasets identified</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A)(ii), the Director shall identify 20 datasets to be prioritized.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2fbb006f4ec5476d8c979a0cf3f71341"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In developing the list under paragraph (1), the Director shall consider the following:</text><subparagraph id="id355f3025fcf544dd88db417bf3eb377d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Applicability to the initial list of societal, national, and geostrategic challenges set forth by subsection (b) of section 10387 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>), or any successor list.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6d1609f9811a45068e94f073e637a782"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Applicability to the initial list of key technology focus areas set forth by subsection (c) of such section, or any successor list.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id852623c1220c42219179787953afc8d7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Applicability to other major United States economic sectors, such as agriculture, health care, transportation, manufacturing, communications, weather services, and positive utility to small and medium United States businesses.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id411f61787e8245318a1f444361091ef4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Opportunities to improve datasets in effect before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4ba215c7f25d4252ac147f9aa092fd36"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Inclusion of data representative of the entire population of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id634c7e548ff5468282ea069b6bdd5b17"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Potential national security threats to releasing datasets, consistent with the United States Government approach to data flows.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2e3fc5d3d8ac4020a92fc5034c017c2a"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Requirements of laws in effect.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id910cc68c312643b0b2113a42bbaac8b9"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Applicability to the priorities listed in the National Artificial Intelligence Research and Development Strategic Plan of the National Science and Technology Council, dated October 2016.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9ab5f8e89ca7452c8f72ec21e09ad7c4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Ability to use data already made available to the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource Pilot program or any successor program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0721a30fe1b741a6aef260e7a55d3822"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public input</header><text>Before finalizing the list required by paragraph (1), the Director shall implement public comment procedures for receiving input and comment from private industry, academia, civil society, and other relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id72c98de1fb05434d831bdb33bb089799"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Science and Technology Council agencies</header><text>The head of each agency with a representative included in the Interagency Committee pursuant to section 5103(c) of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413(c)</external-xref>) or the heads of multiple agencies with a representative included in the Interagency Committee working cooperatively, consistent with the missions or responsibilities of each Executive agency—</text><paragraph id="id616bf2b7c057413fb81550dbb46a7476"><enum>(1)</enum><text>subject to the availability of appropriations, shall award grants or otherwise establish incentives, through new or existing programs, for the creation or improvement of curated datasets identified in the list developed pursuant to subsection (a)(1), including methods for addressing data scarcity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc823530d672841cbb31cd80e9156da82"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may establish or leverage existing initiatives, including public-private partnerships, to encourage private sector cost-sharing in the creation or improvement of such datasets;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id35ca0f6f47b5424cbb7c156d22cc9a83"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may apply the priorities set forth in the list developed pursuant to subsection (a)(1) to the enactment of Federal public access and open government data policies; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idca1c46d7ad414a188ff2c70bd349e4e1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in carrying out this subsection, shall ensure consistency with Federal provisions of law relating to privacy, including the technology and privacy standards applied to the National Secure Data Service under section 10375(f) of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19085">42 U.S.C. 19085(f)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id891cde3f1a8e4c94927b7b0e6c543036"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in carrying out this subsection, shall ensure data sharing is limited with any country that the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of State, and the Director of National Intelligence, determines to be engaged in conduct that is detrimental to the national security or foreign policy of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7cbde49fbc434d44ac886b02510e02d1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of datasets</header><text>Datasets that are created or improved by Federal agencies may be made available to the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource pilot program established by the Director of the National Science Foundation in accordance with Executive Order 14110 (88 Fed. Reg. 75191; relating to safe, secure, and trustworthy development and use of artificial intelligence), or any successor program.</text></subsection><subsection id="ide09e033970b145478910225031bbfe09"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to require the Federal Government or other contributors to disclose any information—</text><paragraph id="id782b6107a766489fb430e547f8a09160"><enum>(1)</enum><text>relating to a trade secret or other protected intellectual property right;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc12dcd46f42e4ada9deaa63da19f70af"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is confidential business information; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9280124d05594e04a0b274dc45cf84ea"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that is privileged.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="ida6ed8675147d46dea082cdb2027b71e1"><enum>202.</enum><header>Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="ide59736097e6a447bbf2a7845f06f1cad"><enum>(a)</enum><header>List of priorities for Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence</header><paragraph id="idb8d63abc8ac044fbbbb933860bfce7f9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>List required</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall, acting through the National Science and Technology Council and the Interagency Committee established or designated pursuant to section 5103 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413</external-xref>), in consultation with industry, civil society, and academia, establish a list of priorities for Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence that seek—</text><subparagraph id="idd88f537e9b634d0793a7560bfe20b77c"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to expedite the development of artificial intelligence systems in the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcf744474175e46a78bcf369a221c5072"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to stimulate artificial intelligence research, development, and commercialization that solves or advances specific, well-defined, and measurable challenges.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id4fecd34bd212456dad9812fcd8800875"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The list established pursuant to paragraph (1) may include the following priorities:</text><subparagraph id="id4e151220e2c948e2822e09f2cdfbf212"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To overcome challenges with engineering of and applied research on microelectronics, including through integration of artificial intelligence with emerging technologies, such as machine learning and quantum computing, or with respect to the physical limits on transistors, electrical interconnects, and memory elements.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id178b2e058f5a4cdfb2319ff128b71cc5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To promote transformational or long-term advancements in computing and artificial intelligence technologies through—</text><clause id="idcf30b0f977314aabad6d9f24a0863e99"><enum>(i)</enum><text>next-generation algorithm design;</text></clause><clause id="idbe823d267291427bb07f3a1792761c16"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>next-generation compute capability;</text></clause><clause id="idb34a9090e6a14d9593de8dd0779a7cc9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>generative and adaptive artificial intelligence for design applications;</text></clause><clause id="id2e92f0517a434aea8170b7c9500c7517"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>photonics-based microprocessors and optical communication networks, including electrophotonics;</text></clause><clause id="idf0d4afef919e4965973949a38ebe30fb"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the chemistry and physics of new materials;</text></clause><clause id="ide73117fba7c942cfb11c94b00c193ad6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>energy use or energy efficiency;</text></clause><clause id="iddafc20105eb84635a82f5278bccc6998"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>techniques to establish cryptographically secure content provenance information; or</text></clause><clause id="ideac6bd12984444878661ba6c1dbf4532"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>safety and controls for artificial intelligence applications.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6e84499781f44d27b67bf7dfc045ca3d"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions, including through integration among emerging technologies such as quantum computing and machine learning, to overcome barriers relating to innovations in advanced manufacturing in the United States, including areas such as—</text><clause id="id1da81c7ff3934fada8cf8d7366d2ba29"><enum>(i)</enum><text>materials, nanomaterials, and composites;</text></clause><clause id="id90fce46299a84a6ca986d6e6423aae4d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>rapid, complex design;</text></clause><clause id="id366dc5ddfadd4d86b703f1f13d03b4db"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>sustainability and environmental impact of manufacturing operations;</text></clause><clause id="idc7072dbf097844819f743653429435fd"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>predictive maintenance of machinery;</text></clause><clause id="id1c5bf2927f4348e59b2b8e691b64fa27"><enum>(v)</enum><text>improved part quality;</text></clause><clause id="idbe62634588aa43ae8cb6d4ed2ed44327"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>process inspections;</text></clause><clause id="id954ebbd8374f40f7a32f01a954a8ef8c"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>worker safety; and</text></clause><clause id="id328e22d985bf4523ad308e3e04a674e9"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>robotics.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6b325e71512542ae8aed81a3967f1035"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions in sectors of the economy, such as expanding the use of artificial intelligence in maritime vessels, including in navigation and in the design of propulsion systems and fuels.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5cfdf3421f3b44d3a49364f4345f97c3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions to improve border security, including solutions relevant to the detection of fentanyl, illicit contraband, and other illegal activities. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id2d0d685375484314ab7a9bd851901192"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Periodic updates</header><text>The Director shall update the list established pursuant to paragraph (1) periodically as the Director determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idd1f7ff929a54414593c165edcd483b2a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal investment initiatives required</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the head of each agency with a representative on the Interagency Committee pursuant to section 5103(c) of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9413">15 U.S.C. 9413(c)</external-xref>) or the heads of multiple agencies with a representative on the Interagency Committee working cooperatively, shall, consistent with the missions or responsibilities of each agency, establish 1 or more prize competitions under section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>), challenge-based acquisitions, or other research and development investments that each agency head deems appropriate consistent with the list of priorities established pursuant to subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="idbfc9d0a071c44c9c9e6c6028542907a6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Timing and announcements of Federal investment initiatives</header><text>The President, acting through the Director, shall ensure that, not later than 1 year after the date on which the Director establishes the list required by subsection (a)(1), at least 3 prize competitions, challenge-based acquisitions, or other research and development investments are announced by heads of Federal agencies under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="id393284e2a9a74586b49b56f21d769a01"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Each head of an agency carrying out an investment initiative under subsection (b) shall ensure that—</text><paragraph id="id8869713aa88e4db5abd11457ebf1392e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for each prize competition or investment initiative carried out by the agency under such subsection, there is—</text><subparagraph id="id7fcd5c0933d946379bcc9c90fb6a25e6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a positive impact on the economic competitiveness of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd27bb6bba5284b3dbd9010752dc3ee2b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a benefit to United States industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4c87df971ed54cbf8a632e83fce59bc9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to the extent possible, leveraging of the resources and expertise of industry and philanthropic partners in shaping the investments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id2e112ede796c4bfabd3192fa8a31af88" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in a case involving development and manufacturing, use of advanced manufacturing in the United States; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id02a594485b364399b9c4959d88fc173b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>all research conducted for purposes of the investment initiative is conducted in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body><legis-body display-enacting-clause="no-display-enacting-clause"><section id="iddf912b3e-570c-45a1-907a-48b4117721f0" section-type="section-one" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id033a509d93bb47d8b5c0338a023f7dc7"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb49144a159c2445784ab326c5b375652"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc-entry level="section" idref="S1">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id60BEDC1E3E6A48ADA565EA8D973B3F90">Sec. 2. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id7288940c7fe74ac2a42093c51f762f00">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="id76483cb063f54e898bac70654370d31a">TITLE I—Voluntary artificial intelligence standards, metrics, evaluation tools, testbeds, and international cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="id960634b045b54773b0c2afabd7377e25">Subtitle A—Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute and testbeds</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="ida55b5f3d23684d2ba4979979d1f985b3">Sec. 101. Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id51e355273fb74377844c29e2776053e8">Sec. 102. Program on artificial intelligence testbeds.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idb8f4f3950559490b83e531e5da785fcb">Sec. 103. National Institute of Standards and Technology and Department of Energy testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idf5f20448fbb943399e8d75e86939f95e">Sec. 104. National Science Foundation and Department of Energy collaboration to make scientific discoveries through the use of artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id225d13e260a44ea8a75c78a823db9590">Sec. 105. Progress report.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="ide04b6fac777041ac914cd33806f9cb47">Subtitle B—International cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id3a3da24192d5481da71fd1bd11ece877">Sec. 111. International coalition on innovation, development, and harmonization of standards with respect to artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id49ebc682d2b44c2eb06bd87229ac215a">Sec. 112. Requirement to support bilateral and multilateral artificial intelligence research collaborations.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="ide672f82475cd4029b426da34c3d9d1e4">Subtitle C—Identifying regulatory barriers to innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idfcba1f603d1f4db297d86f5ea0f3e591">Sec. 121. Comptroller General of the United States identification of risks and obstacles relating to artificial intelligence and Federal agencies.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="id2f82f14e45a84b1494409b239ba637de">TITLE II—Artificial intelligence research, development, capacity building activities</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id9f26c79c63f4493d9663218910a83bb2">Sec. 201. Public data for artificial intelligence systems.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="ida6ed8675147d46dea082cdb2027b71e1">Sec. 202. Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="iddf912b3e-570c-45a1-907a-48b4117721f0">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id2a77b98c-4e25-4206-ba79-4895f6246899">Sec. 2. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="ide41db5dd-cf44-4a60-ab76-3defc4c00e72">TITLE I—Voluntary artificial intelligence standards, metrics, evaluation tools, testbeds, and international cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id2d7ec6f0-92ae-4602-8942-13237b21f392">Sec. 100. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="idc9a8b867-91c9-47f6-b208-f7e1ea9f3e0f">Subtitle A—Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute and testbeds</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id9f2f73d9-e8d8-4c3f-be02-35ccaeb8e557">Sec. 101. Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idfa476c74-8027-4009-a639-cd8d10f2caf2">Sec. 102. Interagency coordination and program to facilitate artificial intelligence testbeds.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id4fee803d-1b53-4d21-be8c-fb07158f2f3f">Sec. 103. National Institute of Standards and Technology and Department of Energy testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id05d2a92a-0cf4-429f-bdf2-793124e79f55">Sec. 104. Coordination, reimbursement, and savings provisions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id6fbf7f5e-3387-4dcb-adb4-72a4d7b55437">Sec. 105. Progress report.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="id8ad41d26-0acf-4cb0-ae50-a3f544e84918">Subtitle B—International cooperation </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id48b7fcc8-cf86-4ee4-933b-24a13f95e8c1">Sec. 111. International coalitions on innovation, development, and alignment of standards with respect to artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="subtitle" idref="id2a8afd16-4370-4af2-b6ab-d817111acb3a">Subtitle C—Identifying regulatory barriers to innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id800f236e-a8c4-45d9-9441-e076397df7c0">Sec. 121. Comptroller General of the United States identification of risks and obstacles relating to artificial intelligence and Federal agencies.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="idc4d2d4ae-6e16-4d50-9776-c7627429e97e">TITLE II—Artificial intelligence research, development, capacity building activities</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id9a790732-fc8e-42a8-8ef6-eaab3c4dc6bc">Sec. 201. Public data for artificial intelligence systems.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id673d1112-c8f3-419d-a098-59a3857f8bed">Sec. 202. Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="id308d74c36abb48aa942cf08561a8ac18">TITLE III—Research security and other matters</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id138a3e60ef794e65a1ffa512c4e7c24a">Sec. 301. Research security.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id42c57a5fb6124a3f9d733be0f2612aa4">Sec. 302. Expansion of authority to hire critical technical experts.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF81C49A4F3254011AF33E6368247CE91">Sec. 303. Foundation for Standards and Metrology.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="idF9496B99D7E74118966A626FB1FFC2CD">Sec. 304. Prohibition on certain policies relating to the use of artificial intelligence or other automated systems.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="id772f95e3f1694f05be018864924151a5">Sec. 305. Certifications and audits of temporary fellows.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="id2a77b98c-4e25-4206-ba79-4895f6246899" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that policies affecting artificial intelligence should maximize the potential, development, and use of artificial intelligence to benefit all private and public stakeholders. </text></section><title id="ide41db5dd-cf44-4a60-ab76-3defc4c00e72" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>I</enum><header>Voluntary artificial intelligence standards, metrics, evaluation tools, testbeds, and international cooperation </header><section id="id2d7ec6f0-92ae-4602-8942-13237b21f392"><enum>100.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph id="id5d4e0804-95ad-4a67-ae21-74679b3c935c"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id219ff3fc-bc20-4fb1-81d7-2733b07f7c54"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence model</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence model</term> means a component of an artificial intelligence system that is—</text><subparagraph id="id01ca8c65-e5f1-488e-8cfd-dbe154b52f7d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>derived using mathematical, computational, statistical, or machine-learning techniques; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida8356100-374d-4290-b4b1-2938d2502fe3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>used as part of an artificial intelligence system to produce outputs from a given set of inputs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id25e27f5c-66f6-4020-9241-39bbe02c13ed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence system</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence system</term> means an engineered or machine-based system that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1848def3db1745b5878a92398a4aae47"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">can, for a given set of objectives, generate outputs such as predictions, recommendations, or decisions influencing real or virtual environments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2777f3e71f034bf3a60085494d2a2af6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is designed to operate with varying levels of autonomy. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idc14558da-b9b1-472e-96a9-de3bc146b573"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1016(e) of the Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism (USA PATRIOT ACT) Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id25fe49dc-92ac-4894-baad-64559445fb4b"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federal laboratory</header><text>The term <term>Federal laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3703">15 U.S.C. 3703</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id56fa7863-ea66-4ab8-999a-93e24de13459"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><text>The term <term>foundation model</term> means an artificial intelligence model trained on broad data at scale and is adaptable to a wide range of downstream tasks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2fd54618-34ad-4481-aceb-09666606f13f"><enum>(7)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <term>National Laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idac32f630-00e1-471c-8d0d-8f5dae2acc72"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means a facility or mechanism equipped for conducting rigorous, transparent, and replicable testing of tools and technologies, including artificial intelligence systems, to help evaluate the functionality, trustworthiness, usability, and performance of those tools or technologies.</text></paragraph></section><subtitle id="idc9a8b867-91c9-47f6-b208-f7e1ea9f3e0f"><enum>A</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute and testbeds</header><section id="id9f2f73d9-e8d8-4c3f-be02-35ccaeb8e557"><enum>101.</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/271">15 U.S.C. 271 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 22A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278h-1">15 U.S.C. 278h–1</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id37469A88AE454C0A8D6B27E68A6005B2" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><section id="id8cd0c9d27e7f4126ab826d2c70b61dc0"><enum>22B.</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddc285ba5bc72407bbba94cdaa3a4244e"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="id7EC79F79F98042E1BB4C4C361D0F93CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>Executive agency</quote> in section 105 of title 5, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7AA65393F8074364B6456900E7FBAB5E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id650A5319A15B4EFABADE29D21956F72D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence blue-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence blue-teaming</term> means an effort to conduct operational vulnerability evaluations and provide mitigation techniques to entities who have a need for an independent technical review of the security posture of an artificial intelligence system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idFDD36994AC894E609F59683F3B251ABF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Artificial intelligence red-teaming</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence red-teaming</term> means structured adversarial testing efforts of an artificial intelligence system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1D831E6E653F4A089615D85F736F2593"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federal laboratory</header><text>The term <term>Federal laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3703">15 U.S.C. 3703</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7B0F0715832A4671B8C077A452E77B8D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Foundation model</header><text>The term <term>foundation model</term> means an artificial intelligence model trained on broad data at scale and is adaptable to a wide range of downstream tasks. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idCFD5F01572354052A2806EC587FF4BC6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Synthetic content</header><text>The term <term>synthetic content</term> means information, such as images, videos, audio clips, and text, that has been significantly modified or generated by algorithms, including by an artificial intelligence system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3FE816DDC72F45DE8C3E10B04A7A972A"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Testbed</header><text>The term <term>testbed</term> means a facility or mechanism equipped for conducting rigorous, transparent, and replicable testing of tools and technologies, including artificial intelligence systems, to help evaluate the functionality, trustworthiness, usability, and performance of those tools or technologies. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idAFD5B556E79B4D3F9DD8F9E7016C85A8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Watermarking</header><text>The term <term>watermarking</term> means the act of embedding information that is intended to be difficult to remove, into outputs generated by artificial intelligence systems or in original content, including outputs such as text, images, audio, videos, software code, or any other digital content or data, for the purposes of verifying the authenticity of the output or the identity or characteristics of its provenance, modifications, or conveyance. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id37b7147c49a5430cabc99e023ef7bc98"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</header><paragraph id="idfdfd34ec8a284a9e98c336caff56e15d"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>, the Director shall establish an institute on artificial intelligence within the Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9a58a6d8180042d4bc2fe53380db0c15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The institute established pursuant to paragraph (1) shall be known as the <quote>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id039232e3ae4d4311b93f46663d515d50"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute is to assist the private sector and agencies in developing voluntary best practices for the robust assessment of artificial intelligence systems, which may be contributed to or inform the work on such practices in standards development organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id2972320d2dbf4c0998b7a94755bbb268"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5cda6fd47b4f45f5b622e47271bbc33f"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The functions of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute, which the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute shall carry out in coordination with the laboratories of the Institute, include the following:</text><subparagraph id="id6673c364191a4f2a90c5c2ec8915a6c8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Using publicly available or voluntarily provided information, assessing artificial intelligence systems and developing best practices for reliable and secure development, deployment, and use of artificial intelligence technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id451e01d7b4734bfc96890bf325a48fdc"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Supporting artificial intelligence red-teaming, sharing best practices, and coordinating on building testbeds and test environments with allies and international partners of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddd3f89f319614fa0b722e2d4132a8561"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Developing and publishing physical and cybersecurity tools, methodologies, best practices, voluntary guidelines, and other supporting information to assist persons who maintain systems used to create or train artificial intelligence models with discovering and mitigating vulnerabilities and attacks, including manipulation through data poisoning, including those that may be exploited by foreign adversaries.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6483f0e7bb2f46ab97a81cbc8d31b984"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Establishing artificial intelligence blue-teaming capabilities to support mitigation approaches and partnering with industry to address the reliability of artificial intelligence systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idafe42ef870714cc4922a2bdd89429921"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Developing tools, methodologies, best practices, and voluntary guidelines for detecting synthetic content, authenticating content and tracking of the provenance of content, labeling original and synthetic content, such as by watermarking, and evaluating software and systems relating to detection and labeling of synthetic content.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id0c7491bdc8394b7cbf5f449aadb1c0d1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Coordinating or developing metrics and methodologies for testing artificial intelligence systems, including the following:</text><clause id="id30292ce8a8b343cb8ad20ba8c9dfb85f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Cataloging existing artificial intelligence metrics and evaluation methodologies used in industry and academia.</text></clause><clause id="id0b9ab28051464f7fb5c146bcab94c284"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Testing the efficacy of existing metrics and evaluations.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbf5a37cfa7b24e119cb58164966c73c8"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Coordinating with counterpart international institutions, partners, and allies, to support global interoperability in the development of research and testing of standards relating to artificial intelligence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id00b8325c30fe4a41914bebe3d7421625"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute Consortium</header><paragraph id="idbd87583ded5a469f9b015cc88249a90d"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><subparagraph id="id1f01ebd77246486fa8da27f00288dcb9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall establish a consortium of stakeholders from academic or research communities, Federal laboratories, private industry, including companies of all sizes with different roles in the use of artificial intelligence systems, including developers, deployers, evaluators, users, and civil society with expertise in matters relating to artificial intelligence to support the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute in carrying out the functions set forth under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id44aeec534fea4143b4e48755a09f338b"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The consortium established pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall be known as the <quote>Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute Consortium</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id245e884633064c7f99a04dd0cf11e90a"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Director shall consult with the consortium established under this subsection not less frequently than quarterly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide88e2a1c0f51498a8e942709815ccab0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual reports to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title> and not less frequently than once each year thereafter, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report summarizing the contributions of the members of the consortium established under this subsection in support the efforts of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id8fb6406f19e2431995b893a7652feb16"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Voluntary artificial intelligence testing standards</header><text>In carrying out the functions under subsection (c), the Director shall support and contribute to the development of voluntary, consensus-based technical standards for testing artificial intelligence system components, including by addressing, as the Director considers appropriate, the following:</text><paragraph id="id195481ceed65487bb8a97ad5088b2362"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Physical infrastructure for training or developing artificial intelligence models and systems, including cloud infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide496c335d4bc4b4886edf78898a9ee7b"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Physical infrastructure for operating artificial intelligence systems, including cloud infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idea8f5443fdeb4cedbf38a4c8c3233176"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Data for training artificial intelligence models.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id236359135984496da106602de1820431"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Data for evaluating the functionality and trustworthiness of trained artificial intelligence models and systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd9b447f01dfd47079175254ffc6d551d"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Trained or partially trained artificial intelligence models and any resulting software systems or products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4b923f7595454b1da273f4b8a3377fdf"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Human-in-the-loop testing of artificial intelligence models and systems.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id4d7dcf2acd5240249677b7fc3397ed5a"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Matters relating to disclosure and access</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id543091e255ac4156802790be2c7b7cf5"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">FOIA exemption</header><text>Any confidential content, as deemed confidential by the contributing private sector person, shall be exempt from public disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id684af3982a5840a39506249afe384f34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on access to content</header><text>Access to a contributing private sector person’s voluntarily provided confidential content, as deemed confidential by the contributing private sector person shall be limited to the private sector person and the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id76b83e41a2b448579345cb8db80d3fbf"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Aggregated information</header><text>The Director may make aggregated, deidentified information available to contributing companies, the public, and other agencies, as the Director considers appropriate, in support of the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idf97549eb24fa492fbd7db0ae0ae1df78" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to provide the Director any enforcement authority that was not in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>.</text></subsection><subsection id="id87d2700435634be39329ddef44e68e4b"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Prohibition on access to resources for entities under control of certain foreign governments</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbaa5497f93a24aa7b9bf8d8730c54465"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>An entity under the ownership, control, or influence of the government of a covered nation may not access any of the resources of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc9ee6fd8df134ddfa924b3c63a38090c"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for identification</header><text>The Director, working with the heads of the relevant Federal agencies, shall establish criteria to determine if any entity that seeks to utilize the resources of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute is under the ownership, control, or influence of the government of a covered nation.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0e1277ebd1924ccb92370dc917328022"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="idc1e06eae00af4ef081d3f8f649defbaf"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered nation</header><text>The term <term>covered nation</term> has the meaning given that term in section 4872 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9386d912ffaa48d08d2dac10c4bdbde6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ownership, control, or influence of the government of a covered nation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>ownership, control, or influence of the government of a covered nation</term>, with respect to an entity, means the government of a covered nation—</text><clause id="id7eccfc19ed72411fab80faa6f39f29bb"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has the power to direct or decide matters affecting the entity's management or operations in a manner that could—</text><subclause id="id291a2c593cb449a8a207dd10d9b614a3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>result in unauthorized access to classified information; or</text></subclause><subclause id="ideeeeac9b8b8540fa86123ad65c2b5017"><enum>(II)</enum><text>adversely affect performance of a contract or agreement requiring access to classified information; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idddb052ef75e5452abbfda5be04930202"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>exercises that power—</text><subclause id="id68fc2a88307a4724acbf81d4792f66ff"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly or indirectly;</text></subclause><subclause id="id699452a00b114a9d851a79f778f98565"><enum>(II)</enum><text>through ownership of the entity's securities, by contractual arrangements, or other similar means;</text></subclause><subclause id="id5d39f875beaf46fd884483ff313c49fb"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by the ability to control or influence the election or appointment of one or more members to the entity's governing board (such as the board of directors, board of managers, or board of trustees) or its equivalent; or</text></subclause><subclause id="id28472413a66d4c6181ca8ed4f645dcb9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>prospectively (such as by not currently exercising the power, but could). </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="idfa476c74-8027-4009-a639-cd8d10f2caf2"><enum>102.</enum><header>Interagency coordination and program to facilitate artificial intelligence testbeds</header><subsection id="idea29325c-c634-4311-baa3-f11d0108c79b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="idf11c3317-dd25-4393-9cd6-691e79161020"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id6e1cfa19-3081-4b1f-b69c-2bf77c220593"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id644dd542-90b0-4e5b-8073-9145f005393d"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd6c2e599-bdad-4f37-a7df-987f5522740d"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Science Foundation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3da850a1089b40d1bd9610e4ab3a27f8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institute</header><text>The term <term>Institute</term> means the National Institute of Standards and Technology. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3033369c-5641-4539-81c3-531300221115"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id128f5737-648a-4852-90ea-6cf4f147f17c"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Under Secretary</term> means the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida08f60fa-d0a6-43fe-9dcc-0bb1667495b6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program required</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary and the Secretary, in coordination with the Director, shall jointly establish a testbed program to encourage collaboration and support partnerships between the National Laboratories, Federal laboratories, the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource pilot program established by the Director, or any successor program, and public and private sector entities, including companies of all sizes, to conduct tests, evaluations, and security or vulnerability risk assessments, and to support research and development, of artificial intelligence systems, including measurement methodologies developed by the Institute, in order to develop standards and encourage development of a third-party ecosystem.</text></subsection><subsection id="id1a88bdef-41d2-4de2-92b9-47f15141d1ba"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out the program required by subsection (b), the Under Secretary and the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="id0f5cceeb-6329-4bba-a24e-7cb842b2aaf7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may use the advanced computing resources, testbeds, and expertise of the National Laboratories, Federal laboratories, the Institute, the National Science Foundation, and private sector entities to run tests and evaluations on the capabilities and limitations of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7ea40104-14aa-4e96-a06d-cd00676c2cb4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall use existing solutions to the maximum extent practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbd924a8d-8274-4add-b848-207a4a817075"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall develop automated and reproducible tests and evaluations for artificial intelligence systems to the extent that is practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbe3e49d7-de69-4323-8d46-72b2b75d5575"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall assess the computational resources necessary to run tests and evaluations of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida474d29f-ae4d-4b69-b47a-dc86eed371ce"><enum>(5)</enum><text>shall research methods to effectively minimize the computational resources needed to run tests, evaluations, and security assessments of artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2738b7a3-7837-40b3-8436-b18595bf1c26"><enum>(6)</enum><text>shall where practicable, develop tests and evaluations for artificial intelligence systems that are designed for high-, medium-, and low-computational intensity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idce2824ab-e7ae-4420-86be-fd626f6c2dc2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>shall prioritize assessments by identifying security vulnerabilities of artificial intelligence systems, including the establishment of and utilization of existing classified testbeds, at the National Laboratories if necessary, including with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="idbb8774a2-cdb0-4772-935c-fdbf1bc6a2cf"><enum>(A)</enum><text>autonomous offensive cyber capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcaba9a6d-1984-4ced-bf4f-9fbb63538ce8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cybersecurity vulnerabilities in the artificial intelligence software ecosystem and beyond;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ided8dcec4-f097-4ee0-a504-a485a43c8023"><enum>(C)</enum><text>chemical, biological, radiological, nuclear, critical infrastructure, and energy-security threats or hazards; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id07c9da61-e725-436e-abc5-cb5315f6e542"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other capabilities as the Under Secretary or the Secretary determines necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="ida5bf2fa7-4221-4807-bb4c-46e443de4110"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consideration given</header><text>In carrying out the activities required by subsection (c), the Under Secretary and the Secretary shall take under consideration the applicability of any tests, evaluations, and risk assessments to artificial intelligence systems trained using primarily biological sequence data that could be used to enhance an artificial intelligence system’s ability to contribute to the creation of a pandemic or biological weapon, including those systems used for gene synthesis. </text></subsection><subsection id="id942b8090-9856-4b7a-b28e-e2ea0d7d32f8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text>The Under Secretary and the Secretary shall jointly develop metrics to assess—</text><paragraph id="ide8be2e57-5120-4d0f-91b7-4f8ef4f65c9e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the program in encouraging collaboration and supporting partnerships as described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd3b992db-57ff-4945-83fc-3ee2f769f8b7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the impact of the program on public and private sector integration and use of artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb7046930-a544-4442-985c-c322d51296a0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of existing program</header><text>In carrying out the program required by subsection (b), the Under Secretary, the Secretary, and the Director may use a program that was in effect on the day before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="id5631fc66-61ca-40de-8540-699802edb6ce"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluation and findings</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the start of the program required by subsection (b), the Under Secretary and the Secretary shall jointly—</text><paragraph id="idb4218510-f032-46ba-bbb3-f4171a7c41c9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>evaluate the success of the program in encouraging collaboration and supporting partnerships as described in subsection (b), using the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (e); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc37ccf8e-52e9-4bdb-9dde-664a7583ad73"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the success of the program in encouraging public and private sector integration and use of artificial intelligence systems by using the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id793e9edc-5e98-4c9f-9ab7-5bac80cd0426"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate committees of Congress the evaluation supported pursuant to paragraph (1) and the findings of the Under Secretary, the Secretary, and the Director with respect to the testbed program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idae3447d0-24cc-40c9-abb3-5b18da736938"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out subsection (b), the Under Secretary and the Secretary shall consult, as the Under Secretary and the Secretary consider appropriate, with the following:</text><paragraph id="idd269f7f7-9e99-4475-ac57-dba7c1b906f3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Industry, including private artificial intelligence laboratories, companies of all sizes, and representatives from the United States financial sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida84a2558-c1af-403a-b7ce-ee42ef13fd24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Academia and institutions of higher education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9d1828e3-efa7-461e-a753-567ef0ff9b65"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Civil society.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9ea841c0-b4e5-46eb-9287-e1e822bc40cd"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Establishment of voluntary foundation models test program</header><text>In carrying out the program under subsection (b), the Under Secretary and the Secretary shall, jointly carry out a test program to provide vendors of foundation models, as well as vendors of artificial intelligence virtual agents and robots that incorporate foundation models, the opportunity to voluntarily test foundation models across a range of modalities, such as models that ingest and output text, images, audio, video, software code, and mixed modalities. </text></subsection><subsection id="idd5f17ad7f619457797266b6c87f49a83"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Matters relating to disclosure and access</header><paragraph id="id9ef3fd2ae3874d77a79a23d8b901ad8b"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation on access to content</header><text>Access to a contributing private sector person’s voluntarily provided confidential content, as deemed confidential by the contributing private sector person, shall be limited to the contributing private sector person and the Institute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id18a117d4797f4a56bf61f619ec06f4ba"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Aggregated information</header><text>The Under Secretary and the Secretary may make aggregated, deidentified information available to contributing companies, the public, and other agencies, as the Under Secretary considers appropriate, in support of the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9eb03b95de5842a99fd40bf8984ba74e"><enum>(3)</enum><header>FOIA exemption</header><text>Any confidential content, as deemed confidential by the contributing private sector person, shall be exempt from public disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb52c6a7a-a8cc-456a-8030-a4318e218753"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require a person to disclose any information, including information—</text><paragraph id="id54a9708d-34e7-48dd-b357-3a7aa7db56d7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>relating to a trade secret or other protected intellectual property right;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6afaa65a-4729-4603-8be9-56f179136b2f"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is confidential business information; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id600697b5-3319-4e27-9be6-3b98fdeb6cd7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that is privileged.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id313cc04e97d445b9ba0c5c02432918a9"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The programs required by subsections (b) and (i) and the requirements of this section shall terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="id4fee803d-1b53-4d21-be8c-fb07158f2f3f"><enum>103.</enum><header>National Institute of Standards and Technology and Department of Energy testbed to identify, test, and synthesize new materials</header><subsection id="ide2bc2526-3022-430b-ac05-505222042c94"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology, and the Secretary of Energy may use the program established under section 102(b) to advance materials science and energy storage and optimization and to support advanced manufacturing for the benefit of the United States economy through the use of artificial intelligence, autonomous laboratories, and artificial intelligence integrated with emerging technologies, such as quantum hybrid computing and robotics.</text></subsection><subsection id="id431addc9-ff2a-4cd5-bf00-d79fb8574067"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Support for accelerated technologies</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall ensure that technologies accelerated under subsection (a) are supported by advanced algorithms and models, uncertainty quantification, and software and workforce development tools to produce benchmark data, model comparison tools, and best practices guides.</text></subsection><subsection id="ida0dd3ce8-be57-4f09-b995-89f6160bc62f"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public-private partnerships</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy shall, in consultation with industry, civil society, and academia, enter into such public-private partnerships as the Secretaries jointly determine appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="id58998754-9424-4d1d-adce-329ab110fbed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretaries may—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id842af3b4ea7d4e9a991cfc35ae8252af"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use science and technology resources from the Manufacturing USA Program, the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership, the National Laboratories, Federal laboratories, and the private sector; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id71e4e6e474694d90a6f9442386da9a32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the program established under section 102(b).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id05d2a92a-0cf4-429f-bdf2-793124e79f55"><enum>104.</enum><header>Coordination, reimbursement, and savings provisions</header><subsection id="id86069bcf393c46e2bc42ed9e54dcd095"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coordination and duplication</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall take such actions as may be necessary to ensure no duplication of activities carried out under this subtitle with the activities of—</text><paragraph id="id4ba4d17d79c24485ab51991c3762f821"><enum>(1)</enum><text>research entities of the Department of Energy, including—</text><subparagraph id="id086be877464d46a989bfe38e38969f35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the National Laboratories; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idec9567154aa9484bac21369511e29a1b"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Advanced Scientific Computing Research program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id8ffc1c9787d442d4a5b5a44051422fe8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>relevant industries.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id6de1795b77cd4501b7f91890e2ff36b4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National laboratory resources</header><text>Any advanced computing resources, testbeds, expertise, or other resources of the Department of Energy or the National Laboratories that are provided to the National Science Foundation, the National Institute of Standards and Technology, or any other applicable entities under this subtitle shall be provided—</text><paragraph id="id31d0ef1209d24a21891aba3c2909319c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>on a reimbursable basis; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6e8558fb29224901ada67b60b6916372"><enum>(2)</enum><text>pursuant to a reimbursable agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id93126ffe94a04f32a2a533b91a3b0e87"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirements set forth in subsection (b) if the Secretary determines the waiver is necessary or appropriate to carry out the missions of the Department of Commerce.</text></subsection><subsection id="id46b98f93dacb4927a501ccbd09a01d9e"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>Nothing in this subtitle shall be construed—</text><paragraph id="id911ae9f3517d42f49f79ec32870adba6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to modify any requirement or authority provided under section 5501 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9461">15 U.S.C. 9461</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida1486d901ad94329a77463b239aaabf6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to allow the Secretary of Commerce (including the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology or the Director of the Artificial Intelligence Safety Institute) or the Director of the National Science Foundation to use monetary resources of the Department of Energy or any National Laboratory.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="id6fbf7f5e-3387-4dcb-adb4-72a4d7b55437"><enum>105.</enum><header>Progress report</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbd53b5dc7aeb4261a1016abc81f325b3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology shall, in coordination with the Secretary of Commerce and the Secretary of Energy, submit to Congress a report on the implementation of sections 102 and 103.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idcdb8ef1e384d4622b2ba1406376dd3f0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report submitted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include the following: </text><paragraph id="idaeb68ef146a04b54894766992c33bd1b"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the reimbursable agreements, statements of work, and associated project schedules and deliverables for the testbed program established pursuant to section 102(b) and section 103(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7f72176edcb74268ad2b512660530bb7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Details on the total amount of reimbursable agreements entered into pursuant to section 104(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3dd291f532cc4ec7bce31f71b6bb2fee"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such additional information as the Under Secretary determines appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></subtitle><subtitle id="id8ad41d26-0acf-4cb0-ae50-a3f544e84918"><enum>B</enum><header>International cooperation </header><section id="id48b7fcc8-cf86-4ee4-933b-24a13f95e8c1"><enum>111.</enum><header>International coalitions on innovation, development, and alignment of standards with respect to artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="id6ca59dfcd058417ea0d1b77e09fd58bb" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology (in this section referred to as the <quote>Under Secretary</quote>) and the Secretary of Energy (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall jointly lead information exchange and coordination among Federal agencies and communication from Federal agencies to the private sector of the United States and like-minded governments of foreign countries to ensure effective Federal engagement in the development and use of international technical standards for artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="id91038e6c30fd40ad921dc9bee8cb6738" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>To support private sector-led engagement and ensure effective Federal engagement in the development and use of international technical standards for artificial intelligence, the Under Secretary shall seek to form alliances or coalitions with like-minded governments of foreign countries—</text><paragraph id="ida05452eec4664ff890bf9914d31ed78e"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to support the private sector-led development and adoption of standards or alignment with respect to artificial intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id86ee9f7cf49e4ec5a0d2bc00a6ab7983"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to encourage the adoption of technical standards developed in the United States to be adopted by international standards organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd8b6ca56bbaf4f41a9682ece92cc04d2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to facilitate international collaboration on innovation, science, and advancement in artificial intelligence research and development, including data sharing, expertise, and resources; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb330a17e6be047d78fc12486a6fe8610"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to develop the government-to-government infrastructure to support the activities described in paragraphs (1) through (3), using existing bilateral and multilateral agreements to the extent practicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id564f9a78-888a-43bd-b14f-619d9b10dbac" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria for participation</header><text>In forming an alliance or coalition of like-minded governments of foreign countries under subsection (b), the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of State, and the Director, in consultation with the heads of relevant agencies, shall jointly establish technology trust criteria—</text><paragraph id="id96af74b8-e891-4a3e-841d-709f48f562f0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to ensure all partner countries have a high level of scientific and technological advancement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3e247c29-9c22-4d26-94f2-8f9b18e039d7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to support the principles for international standards development as detailed in the Committee Decision on World Trade Organization Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade (Annex 2 of Part 1 of G/TBT/1), on international standards, such as transparency, openness, and consensus-based decision-making.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idfb082cef-e0ed-4d24-9e50-7d33e717f88d" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation on innovation and advancements in artificial intelligence</header><text>In forming an alliance or coalition under subsection (b), the Director, the Secretary of Commerce, and the Secretary of State shall consult with the Secretary of Energy and the Director of the National Science Foundation on approaches to innovation and advancements in artificial intelligence.</text></subsection><subsection id="idbfe4848a-d154-45b5-b47e-7593fe628968" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Security and protection of intellectual property</header><text>The Director, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of State shall jointly ensure that an alliance or coalition formed under subsection (b) is only undertaken with countries that—</text><paragraph id="id16178d52-a2c4-4387-bada-f0bbf46a56a7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>have in place sufficient intellectual property protections, safety standards, and risk management approaches relevant to innovation and artificial intelligence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idb43a9de2-76bc-4c8e-912a-105b00e01b46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and coordinate research security measures, export controls, and intellectual property protections relevant to innovation, development, and standard-setting relating to artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id8a2d2e7030d74b6080e690b47b780b0c" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation on eligibility of the People's Republic of China</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide944a83d71e54e249bae5d2356c4f538"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The People’s Republic of China is not eligible to participate in an alliance or coalition of like-minded governments of foreign countries under subsection (b) until the United States Trade Representative determines in a report to Congress required by section 421 of the U.S.-China Relations Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/6951">22 U.S.C. 6951</external-xref>) that the People’s Republic of China has come into compliance with the commitments it made in connection with its accession to the World Trade Organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id93fcfb39464a4184ab8afa3685480c24"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Upon the submission of a report described in paragraph (1), the officials specified in paragraph (3) shall jointly submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfe41d9e33de94f1fa1af03fa6c21f4b3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed justification for why government-to-government information exchange and coordination with the Government of the People’s Republic of China is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id153d50ce1e91481e84c2044b13a6e406"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An assessment of the risks and potential effects of such coordination, including any potential for the transfer under an alliance or coalition described in paragraph (1) of technology or intellectual property capable of harming the national security interests of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7f3b81c0ba494269a00ec8fef35ac738"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A detailed justification for how the officials specified in paragraph (3) intend to address human rights concerns in any scientific and technology collaboration proposed to be conducted by such an alliance or coalition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id916e5bf8d86f461880556f05880274a0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An assessment of the extent to which those officials will be able to continuously monitor the commitments made by the People’s Republic of China in participating in such an alliance or coalition.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd7e3abc28cfa44e2af40ed3b1023e961"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Such other information relating to such an alliance or coalition as those officials consider appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd5479ebe583847aebb8807fdb737c3ab"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Officials specified</header><text>The officials specified in this paragraph are the following: </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc23cd745f295471dbb20ad21a206aca3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfe48fcaadc25447e99364fd1792f5e6f"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Commerce. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1ecd5b930f1f45cd8d77190df30682c2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idedb3abddcd4b451d8314f17bc0dbce00"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb88c9632-d84f-481c-b5a6-d6ea0f557db0" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed—</text><paragraph id="id216e4bc0bdaf473aa6e9814cc55893b9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to prohibit a person (as defined in section 551 of title 5, United States Code) from participating in an international standards body; or </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd7e36887bfd64cf3a6b514eeecd5e20a"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to constrain separate engagement with emerging economies on artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subtitle><subtitle id="id2a8afd16-4370-4af2-b6ab-d817111acb3a" style="OLC"><enum>C</enum><header>Identifying regulatory barriers to innovation</header><section id="id800f236e-a8c4-45d9-9441-e076397df7c0"><enum>121.</enum><header>Comptroller General of the United States identification of risks and obstacles relating to artificial intelligence and Federal agencies</header><subsection id="id0d532167-732a-44ec-99bd-313c66c4cee2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on regulatory impediments to innovation in artificial intelligence systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc8fc3ea0-d6ee-453c-95a0-8dbc0d9bed11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="id7121de30-2485-43c8-8a2b-388cd9fc3fb1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Significant examples of Federal statutes and regulations that directly affect the innovation of artificial intelligence systems, including the ability of companies of all sizes to compete in artificial intelligence, which should also account for the effect of voluntary standards and best practices developed with contributions from the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idecbc851c-f391-459c-b2aa-6d57192e75ba"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An evaluation of the progress in government adoption of artificial intelligence and use of artificial intelligence to improve the quality of government services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbf6b26cc-551e-42d4-82c0-5640b70c125f" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Based on the findings of the Comptroller General with respect to paragraphs (1) and (2), such recommendations as the Comptroller General may have for legislative or administrative action to increase the rate of innovation in artificial intelligence systems. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></subtitle></title><title id="idc4d2d4ae-6e16-4d50-9776-c7627429e97e" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>II</enum><header>Artificial intelligence research, development, capacity building activities</header><section id="id9a790732-fc8e-42a8-8ef6-eaab3c4dc6bc"><enum>201.</enum><header>Public data for artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id557d3ea7b5af43d3b225067e62ad134b"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Title LI of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9411">15 U.S.C. 9411 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0A01A82EF39D401EB06F59E8CC088613" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id92d11337adcd49ada2eda422fa445284"><enum>5103A.</enum><header>Public data for artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="id65f689cc-c940-4ac0-969c-788a843d57b8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>List of priorities</header><paragraph id="idfbd6fa44-e1b6-4ee2-bb16-e09c9b5af243"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To expedite the development of artificial intelligence systems in the United States, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>) shall, acting through the National Science and Technology Council and the Interagency Committee and in consultation with the Advisory Committee on Data for Evidence Building established under section 315 of title 5, United States Code, develop a list of priorities for Federal investment in creating or improving curated, publicly available Federal Government data for training and evaluating artificial intelligence systems and identify an appropriate location to host curated datasets.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1499ddf4-dd88-4fc4-b331-8f88f9cb2d39"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id01e6d1b1-a2d2-4de5-9d6b-d77237e99cad"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The list developed pursuant to paragraph (1) shall—</text><clause id="id8ad76351-3c66-4e5f-8519-8809fc790bc3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prioritize data that will advance novel artificial intelligence systems in the public interest; and</text></clause><clause id="id6232de35-8614-403b-97e9-cde716faba75"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prioritize datasets unlikely to independently receive sufficient private sector support to enable their creation, absent Federal funding.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide5529825-360d-41e1-bb8f-5ab7a4868f78"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Datasets identified</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A)(ii), the Director shall identify 20 datasets to be prioritized.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd7e283dc-3236-4dfc-aa52-282e2fca16fa"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In developing the list under paragraph (1), the Director shall consider the following:</text><subparagraph id="id62467f69-7201-4be0-a542-0873ef0f08fa"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Applicability to the initial list of societal, national, and geostrategic challenges set forth by subsection (b) of section 10387 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19107">42 U.S.C. 19107</external-xref>), or any successor list.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf748e0e1-ae38-4787-a520-6ac73683c53c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Applicability to the initial list of key technology focus areas set forth by subsection (c) of such section, or any successor list.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida446d2d7-c641-4d4e-8352-8839f96df5d8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Applicability to other major United States economic sectors, such as agriculture, health care, transportation, manufacturing, communications, weather services, and positive utility to small- and medium-sized United States businesses.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5aecb356-4deb-4726-b315-4aa9729a6b6d"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Opportunities to improve datasets in effect before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id497596f3-4ffb-47b6-bbf9-a0929ed73708"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Inclusion of data representative of the entire population of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4303800f-4da6-4fd8-ba36-163fbb8156cf"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Potential national security threats to releasing datasets, consistent with the United States Government approach to data flows.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfe7f545e-7571-4413-8f12-13cf1d39f380"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Requirements of laws in effect.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idcc34b9a8-964a-4f01-8d0d-a1995aa37f9c"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Applicability to the priorities listed in the National Artificial Intelligence Research and Development Strategic Plan of the National Science and Technology Council, dated October 2016.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id88ff1eec-df57-401d-8253-6932645e219f"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Ability to use data already made available to the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource Pilot program or any successor program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id34203a59f3c14bcc88c2c36205be1da4"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Coordination with other Federal open data efforts, as applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id240a3681-7b11-44f8-9cd3-e2a00baf96b4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public input</header><text>Before finalizing the list required by paragraph (1), the Director shall implement public comment procedures for receiving input and comment from private industry, academia, civil society, and other relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="iddb9e558a-55a5-4887-9e44-e15c0ac0da35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Interagency Committee</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Interagency Committee—</text><paragraph id="id57446cb4-dabf-4ed8-9c79-3ae194deb08a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may establish or leverage existing initiatives, including through public-private partnerships, for the creation or improvement of curated datasets identified in the list developed pursuant to subsection (a)(1), including methods for addressing data scarcity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9839bdf8-90e2-43e3-8882-0f3d6feaa354"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may apply the priorities set forth in the list developed pursuant to subsection (a)(1) to the enactment of Federal public access and open government data policies; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id53b40e95-22ed-4a58-aafa-595486dd189f"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall ensure consistency with Federal provisions of law relating to privacy, including the technology and privacy standards applied to the National Secure Data Service under section 10375(f) of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19085">42 U.S.C. 19085(f)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9c5c4f39-6679-4b03-8c0e-0d87eca248eb"><enum>(4)</enum><text>shall ensure that no data sharing is permitted with any country that the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Energy, and the Director of National Intelligence, determines to be engaged in conduct that is detrimental to the national security or foreign policy of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id2cbd1ea2-7f52-49e2-b9bd-2a7e889d709e"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of datasets</header><text>Datasets that are created or improved pursuant to this section—</text><paragraph id="ide0d26a0a738146b891b9abc5323b332b"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall, in the case of a dataset created or improved by a Federal agency, be made available to the comprehensive data inventory developed and maintained by the Federal agency pursuant to section 3511(a) of title 44, United States Code, in accordance with all applicable regulations; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="idE33F5188BFC24B60811B2226A354E222"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may be made available to the National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource pilot program established by the Director of the National Science Foundation, and the applicable programs established by the Department of Energy, in accordance with Executive Order 14110 (88 Fed. Reg. 75191; relating to safe, secure, and trustworthy development and use of artificial intelligence), or any successor program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id42a9c895650c49cf81a200808dcbf4ad"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>, the Director shall, acting through the National Science and Technology Council and the Interagency Committee, submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="id33d58673fc874a45a6fc6786f097067a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>best practices in developing publicly curated artificial intelligence datasets;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id91732d691b8d4032a87ffce4841c40d9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>lessons learned and challenges encountered in developing the curated artificial intelligence datasets;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idabf6bc514aaa4d098af11d87ac61fa2a"><enum>(3)</enum><text>principles used for artificial intelligence-ready data; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id39fcb0d664064e259acf8670c393dafc"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations related to artificial intelligence-ready data standards and potential processes for development of such standards.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id05367b64-1a6d-403a-97cf-3e658c2229c0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2269b84f1ea44d04a98a661aa24b065d"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to require the Federal Government or other contributors to disclose any information—</text><subparagraph id="id369d0cb3-57dc-4e97-a5a7-1f86ec4d68e5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>relating to a trade secret or other protected intellectual property right;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id083f5924-03fe-4859-a3f2-e866bd43068e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is confidential business information; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idde4e642b-f8b2-41c9-bb29-5075908aaee7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that is privileged.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idbf111fe5e35b40458063dc24f9ad6353"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disclosure to public datasets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as specifically provided for in this section, nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit the head of a Federal agency from withholding information from a public dataset.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddc9a790d778f490f9f3cc30ddc44e3ed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The table of contents at the beginning of section 2 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 and the table of contents at the beginning of title LI of such Act are both amended by inserting after the items relating to section 5103 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id953740F757FD4B29917AF2A63F6F01E9" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">5103A. Public data for artificial intelligence systems.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="id673d1112-c8f3-419d-a098-59a3857f8bed"><enum>202.</enum><header>Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idDB204FA3C3B64E808A6D5E20429B7624"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Title LI of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9411">15 U.S.C. 9411 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 201, is further amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6337FBCAEC3D4295BB9C61BC6045ED51" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><section id="id8673aa065b0a489e9c751aebe78c8fa6"><enum>5107.</enum><header>Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence</header><subsection id="id55af8c74-e9ce-4317-896c-25ba16e7c492"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><paragraph id="id1e4c2f13603948b7acefdc0bf79b89e9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy (acting through the National Science and Technology Council) and the Interagency Committee may establish a program to award prizes, using the authorities and processes established under section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>), to eligible participants as determined by the co-chairs of the Interagency Committee pursuant to subsection (e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id0537378923514d208a637cbf29aa1934"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the program required by paragraph (1) are as follows:</text><subparagraph id="id5e58fe99c96c4c519abea1fdf4033148"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To expedite the development of artificial intelligence systems in the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id23e000519f0b4c97b5875d06d78e231f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To stimulate artificial intelligence research, development, and commercialization that solves or advances specific, well-defined, and measurable challenges in 1 or more of the categories established pursuant to subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id9bd5b6252ea44807af5e4aeec04e4319"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence</header><paragraph id="idd5ac390c82964c0f96c6572c311bbc68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>List of priorities</header><text>The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy (acting through the National Science and Technology Council) and the Interagency Committee and in consultation with industry, civil society, and academia, identify, and annually review and update as the Director considers appropriate, a list of priorities for Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence pursuant to the purposes set forth under subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddd6115bd4ba14ffbbff53eb67a1c0208"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial list</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfc632dcd6e284f3181d7cbe1586c86aa"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The list established pursuant to paragraph (1) may include the following priorities:</text><clause id="id8861e4e33c7443269bb643b7d080818f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>To overcome challenges with engineering of and applied research on microelectronics, including through integration of artificial intelligence with emerging technologies, such as neuromorphic and quantum computing, or with respect to the physical limits on transistors, advanced interconnects, and memory elements.</text></clause><clause id="id482efe9f91a44108a04e9c10ea26f02b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>To promote transformational or long-term advancements in computing and artificial intelligence technologies through—</text><subclause id="idbc19e94ed69c46c192fca8b0a997e41a"><enum>(I)</enum><text>next-generation algorithm design;</text></subclause><subclause id="idde68d326af534482a96e364ac8d4bdef"><enum>(II)</enum><text>next-generation compute capability;</text></subclause><subclause id="id7240ac2d22c9430fa940b920fd148ace"><enum>(III)</enum><text>generative and adaptive artificial intelligence for design applications;</text></subclause><subclause id="id791e1ce33259425ca73518b009317235"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>photonics-based microprocessors and optical communication networks, including electrophotonics;</text></subclause><subclause id="idcbfeb34e359d45eaa8bc7da63434efbc"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the chemistry and physics of new materials;</text></subclause><subclause id="idc385f1165b0e448a9f17c274c5f1e591"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>energy use or energy efficiency;</text></subclause><subclause id="id7b2c99a712cd439dabb4c76b4fbe8d27"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>techniques to establish cryptographically secure content provenance information; or</text></subclause><subclause id="id15a54c5538a44206aaaaa02c000e8a8f"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>safety and controls for artificial intelligence applications.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id961e8bf9354c461c9890ca42e2f276c6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>To promote explainability and mechanistic interpretability of artificial intelligence systems.</text></clause><clause id="id5d369e8e1be440169f58ca6b64d1dcc5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions, including through integration among emerging technologies such as neuromorphic and quantum computing to overcome barriers relating to innovations in advanced manufacturing in the United States, including areas such as—</text><subclause id="id1b21747170664ea39f0447aea933523b"><enum>(I)</enum><text>materials, nanomaterials, and composites;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide218dfd6c46d402aa34a873e3cf0ed04"><enum>(II)</enum><text>rapid, complex design;</text></subclause><subclause id="id5a2068a6a7d34d8b94f8618ce58e35c4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>sustainability and environmental impact of manufacturing operations;</text></subclause><subclause id="ide13ae0d9f3314d1fa39bc3451514ef9a"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>predictive maintenance of machinery;</text></subclause><subclause id="id60818eeaee4f403ab7924c14c278eda5"><enum>(V)</enum><text>improved part quality;</text></subclause><subclause id="id7bdf06177620464c9c2682ebdff7fe20"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>process inspections;</text></subclause><subclause id="id2f96bdb3844441f2825ab0ba7ce33b03"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>worker safety; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id88e40c60784349a4b352515a28593447"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>robotics.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="idb5effaade1ea4fea8898552437b1f233"><enum>(v)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions in sectors of the economy, such as expanding the use of artificial intelligence in maritime vessels, including in navigation and in the design of propulsion systems and fuels.</text></clause><clause id="id44b7cf0e2c6741cf8c3547538d9393af"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions to improve border security, including solutions relevant to the detection of fentanyl, illicit contraband, and other illegal activities.</text></clause><clause id="id28557f740e0a4361a9d20eef7726aae9"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence for science applications.</text></clause><clause id="id35bb36d284304aeb9fd7736d38119644"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>To develop cybersecurity for artificial intelligence-related intellectual property, such as artificial intelligence systems and artificial intelligence algorithms.</text></clause><clause id="id56db79b7377a4931a381dfde9f0e49ba"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>To develop artificial intelligence solutions to modernize code and software systems that are deployed in government agencies and critical infrastructure and are at risk of maintenance difficulties due to code obsolescence or challenges finding expertise in outdated code bases. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id7f3308209973424c9845b28f999fb935"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation on identification and selection of grand challenges</header><text>The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Director of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, such agency heads as the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy considers relevant, and the National Artificial Intelligence Advisory Committee shall each identify and select artificial intelligence research and development grand challenges in which eligible participants will compete to solve or advance for prize awards under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id38981afc4ca344adb2ed056552a1b053"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public input on identification</header><text>The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall also seek public input on the identification of artificial intelligence research and development grand challenges under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc953c4985d0546bf861f13cf1c201955"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Problem statements; success metrics</header><text>For each priority for a Federal grand challenge identified under paragraph (1) and the grand challenges identified and selected under paragraph (3), the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall—</text><subparagraph id="id57955be3567d4044bb1daadd5dd54cdc"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish a specific and well-defined grand challenge problem statement and ensure that such problem statement is published on a website linking out to relevant prize competition listings on the website Challenge.gov, or successor website, that is managed by the General Services Administration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id08b691b5dbde4df88d115ef7cb117678"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish and publish on the website Challenge.gov, or successor website, clear targets, success metrics, and validation protocols for the prize competitions designed to address each grand challenge, in order to provide specific benchmarks that will be used to evaluate submissions to the prize competition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idfd984935cac94a2d9fcb03114f241d27"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal investment initiatives authorized</header><text>Subject to the availability of amounts appropriated for this purpose, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of Transportation, the Director of the National Science Foundation may, consistent with the missions or responsibilities of each Federal agency, establish 1 or more prize competitions under section 24 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719</external-xref>), challenge-based acquisitions, or other research and development investments that each agency head deems appropriate consistent with the list of priorities established pursuant to subsection (b)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="ide47aa63e65684c7f87e0bf8fee854435"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><paragraph id="id582bf0597619491bbe8d725646133c7a"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall develop requirements for—</text><subparagraph id="ida434892623e44eb1bc663f63bad4571e"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the process for prize competitions under subsections (a) and (c), including eligibility criteria for participants, consistent with the requirements under paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1302632a1c3b451fa8ff30e210b20ff2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>testing, judging, and verification procedures for submissions to receive a prize award under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id8da2b2bb7c52427dacf2a14fa229c401"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility requirement and judging</header><subparagraph id="id75916f8b075a44878cf5a3a71ba8eb83"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>In accordance with the requirement described in section 24(g)(3) of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719(g)(3)</external-xref>), a recipient of a prize award under subsection (c)—</text><clause id="idf85ce18239754bda9aaa9f5d18d6fc71"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is a private entity shall be incorporated in and maintain a primary place of business in the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="idbdd7e38ced4440b9a9ebae5fc1d58fb1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who is an individual, whether participating singly or in a group, shall be a citizen or permanent resident of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id170d9bb67e6a49bead01d1b7e3629803"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Judges</header><text>In accordance with section 24(k) of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3719">15 U.S.C. 3719(k)</external-xref>), a judge of a prize competition under subsection (c) may be an individual from the private sector.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idff74eead114a43d0855beb5f8b68fd7e"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Agency leadership</header><text>Each agency head carrying out an investment initiative under subsection (c) shall ensure that—</text><subparagraph id="id0074cee06e4b443295790b82af1afb03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for each prize competition or investment initiative carried out by the agency head under such subsection, there is—</text><clause id="id357301299b894ba590388514a399b03f"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a positive impact on the economic competitiveness of the United States;</text></clause><clause id="id4e346a03bc2d47c2b846e9d07b39bf3a"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a benefit to United States industry;</text></clause><clause id="idc5a5ccb94bf44827a47c4e6e156ff384"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to the extent possible, leveraging of the resources and expertise of industry and philanthropic partners in shaping the investments; and</text></clause><clause id="id706b07b03943438ebece8257555ec120"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in a case involving development and manufacturing, use of advanced manufacturing in the United States; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id747f2a09476040f28a40f1c8d30ec351"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all research conducted for purposes of the investment initiative is conducted in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idcc394bae42de40048c9cd03d3aab744e"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="idf55391bf0da64caea44be08dfbc0b4b5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification of winning submission</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which a prize is awarded under subsection (c), the agency head awarding the prize shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and such other committees of Congress as the agency head considers relevant a report that describes the winning submission to the prize competition and its benefits to the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2cf515691f534388a3caa50ac5a593d7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Biennial report</header><subparagraph id="id0c00ac7fa66241409ec87ea0f463d324"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>, and biennially thereafter, the heads of agencies described in subsection (c) shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and such other committees of Congress as the agency heads consider relevant a report that includes—</text><clause id="id3c4980f74a0745d282abdf81a7ba650d"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of the activities carried out by the agency heads under this section;</text></clause><clause id="idcd9d7f142c5c4563a26ffb81eafd935c"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the active competitions and the results of completed competitions under subsection (c); and</text></clause><clause id="ida8c20fc7858e4cf2957500b6d294c372"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>efforts to provide information to the public on active competitions under subsection (c) to encourage participation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id331474774af642b08556fe846e5e3dd8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public accessibility</header><text>The agency heads described in subsection (c) shall make the biennial report required under subparagraph (A) publicly accessible, including by posting the biennial report on a website in an easily accessible location, such as the GovInfo website of the Government Publishing Office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id470f38f4feb541a1b900aad50c1fb8e9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Accessibility</header><text>In carrying out any competition under subsection (c), the head of an agency shall post the active prize competitions and available prize awards under subsection (b) to Challenge.gov, or successor website, after the grand challenges are selected and the prize competitions are designed pursuant to subsections (c) and (e) to ensure the prize competitions are widely accessible to eligible participants.</text></subsection><subsection id="idc0f295c4733d4715ac501349d07873fd"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment the <short-title>Future of Artificial Intelligence Innovation Act of 2024</short-title>.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="ida4b1b2a21b2c4bec9c2e2f7f76848c59"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Comptroller General of the United States studies and reports</header><paragraph id="id3fca7ed3569a4a0f8cb9293cf9725c9b"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial study</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6d6b19329f4c4e719a45c089909a498c"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of Federal prize competitions, which shall include an assessment of the efficacy and impact of prize competitions generally.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id932762acd68849a4a80a8bf1734034e6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study conducted under subparagraph (A) shall include, to the extent practicable, the following:</text><clause id="id0e5b0a4fae9f48a184f58a5c7d74a780"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A survey of all existing, current and ongoing Federal prize competitions carried out under authorities enacted before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></clause><clause id="id4d18bc2bc88f4380808abc7df1a24ffd"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An assessment of those existing, current, and ongoing Federal prize competitions that includes addressing—</text><subclause id="idc015f38ac93649ef8fe86c5eb4617e21"><enum>(I)</enum><text>whether and what technology or innovation would have been developed in the absence of the prize competitions;</text></subclause><subclause id="id0ef3d4b3cfd84af2aa03a6074071a596"><enum>(II)</enum><text>whether the prize competitions shortened the timeframe for the development of the technology or innovation;</text></subclause><subclause id="idbad359e3937d4f0a8456e6ebf2f10878"><enum>(III)</enum><text>whether the prize competition was cost effective;</text></subclause><subclause id="id8cfea6d5d2dd43e08ac16d54c26866fb"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>what, if any, other benefits were gained from conducting the prize competitions;</text></subclause><subclause id="id04ce9b9170bb4a67aa78d683d9d90d1e"><enum>(V)</enum><text>whether the use of a more traditional policy tool such as a grant or contract have resulted in the development of a similar technology or innovation;</text></subclause><subclause id="id9b5ce720e039493982a84a3accaf14cf"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>whether prize competitions might be designed differently in a way that would result in a more effective or revolutionary technology being developed;</text></subclause><subclause id="idaef693b0f6624922925e46e5db4a1eba"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>what are appropriate metrics that could be used for determining the success of a prize competition, and whether those metrics differ when evaluating near-term and long-term impacts of prize competitions; and</text></subclause><subclause id="id67c8f1283a634645be7edca80b3c9413"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>suggested best practices of prize competitions.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idd79c06f83c144cc8b3d40cdef91701e4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Congressional briefing</header><text>Not later than 540 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall provide the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a briefing on the findings of the Comptroller General with respect to the study conducted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddb11b3817c2f43849f6547f5acf6654b"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 540 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the congressional committees specified in subparagraph (C) a report on the findings and recommendations of Comptroller General from the study conducted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id9c6f6f72313a4e17910d2b5eeed12e5f"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interim study</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id63cb6c588b8241c58eeb1dc462b0d0e0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of the Federal prize challenges implemented under section 5108 of the of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020, as added by subsection (a), which shall include an assessment of the efficacy and effect of such prize competitions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id4427ba5dad7e4028bc1ea2939cb61689"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The study conducted under subparagraph (A) shall include, to the extent practicable, the following:</text><clause id="idb7db937a6f014aafa57d86fa66c0f4fe"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A survey of all Federal prize competitions implemented under section 5108 of the of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020, as added by subsection (a).</text></clause><clause id="idae8a636f54434a2d870b09a1bc3a3662"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An assessment of the Federal prize competitions implemented such section, which shall include addressing the same considerations as set forth under paragraph (1)(B)(ii).</text></clause><clause id="id1dd705dc8e5a4c9491aaec5ccf71f531"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>An assessment of the efficacy, impact, and cost-effectiveness of prize competitions implemented under section 5108 of the of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020, as added by subsection (a), compared to other Federal prize competitions.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id90fff5b0616e46bb91dfd1c072b0413e"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Congressional briefing</header><text>Not later than 1 year after completing the study required by subparagraph (A), the Comptroller General shall provide the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a briefing on the findings of the Comptroller General with respect to the study conducted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id27e365dda769452a8b84e70995006ddb"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the congressional committees specified in subparagraph (C) a report on the findings and recommendations of the Comptroller General with respect to the study conducted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1B19ED7D8B0541F18AE6FC3096E18E64"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The table of contents at the beginning of section 2 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 and the table of contents at the beginning of title LI of such Act, as amended by section 201, are both amended by inserting after the items relating to section 5107 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9FC4D727429146B9A1949CD693077D18" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">5107. Federal grand challenges in artificial intelligence.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></title><title id="id308d74c36abb48aa942cf08561a8ac18" style="OLC" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>III</enum><header>Research security and other matters</header><section id="id138a3e60ef794e65a1ffa512c4e7c24a" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>301.</enum><header>Research security</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The activities authorized under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provision of subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>; enacted as part of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>) and section 223 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6605">42 U.S.C. 6605</external-xref>).</text></section><section id="id42c57a5fb6124a3f9d733be0f2612aa4" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>302.</enum><header>Expansion of authority to hire critical technical experts</header><subsection id="id2b02aa8d97c04fb3adff7f81c8553330"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 6 of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/275">15 U.S.C. 275</external-xref>) is amended, in the second sentence, by striking <quote>15</quote> and inserting “30</text></subsection><subsection id="idba853c9215e0482690576d00f198c28b"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Modification of sunset</header><text>Subsection (c) of such section is amended by striking <quote>under section (b) shall expire on the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this section</quote> and inserting <quote>under subsection (b) shall expire on December 30, 2035</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF81C49A4F3254011AF33E6368247CE91" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>303.</enum><header>Foundation for Standards and Metrology</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id95bcbc06d124424d8487dad9fd17d624"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle B of title II of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18931">42 U.S.C. 18931 et seq.</external-xref>; relating to measurement research of the National Institute of Standards and Technology for the future; enacted as part of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idF972A7934A1944BDA03CC53C4696F1C8" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><section id="id804e17f91bcf40a78ba108531c7c6864"><enum>10236.</enum><header>Foundation for Standards and Metrology</header><subsection id="H76ADD781982F41AD91F8B582723FD75A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director, shall establish a nonprofit corporation to be known as the <quote>Foundation for Standards and Metrology</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H41F2EC0948EE4749B1735004E5C5F2FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The mission of the Foundation shall be to—</text><paragraph id="HE79B321D110C4590B2ABFC4123B1A435"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support the Institute in carrying out its activities and mission to advance measurement science, technical standards, and technology in ways that enhance the economic security and prosperity of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27BA3DC0E41A49948768F785EB523A96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>advance collaboration with researchers, institutions of higher education, industry, and nonprofit and philanthropic organizations to accelerate the development of technical standards, measurement science, and the commercialization of emerging technologies in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5EBF4B52E7F5476EA5A58856A46FFB25"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out its mission under subsection (b), the Foundation may carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="HAFD1D9623D7A4DF69271DD56FB4BB9FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Support international metrology and technical standards engagement activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5AD29396EA641B8A1217064D87F7CD3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Support studies, projects, and research on metrology and the development of benchmarks and technical standards infrastructure across the Institute’s mission areas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D62DE8EE8454A68839C4BF338B8DAF3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Advance collaboration between the Institute and researchers, industry, nonprofit and philanthropic organizations, institutions of higher education, federally funded research and development centers, and State, Tribal, and local governments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB196008D2E9D4935ADF80FE9984925D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Support the expansion and improvement of research facilities and infrastructure at the Institute to advance the development of emerging technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5529B2BA055241EFA6A68302FA7AC5DA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Support the commercialization of federally funded research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE3334778BC4485FBB9DA07727843492"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Conduct education and outreach activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05A29791B08B491C9F5110FAB07927E6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Offer direct support to NIST associates, including through the provision of fellowships, grants, stipends, travel, health insurance, professional development training, housing, technical and administrative assistance, recognition awards for outstanding performance, and occupational safety and awareness training and support, and other appropriate expenditures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2856E0735B364672965FA93DA53F185D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Conduct such other activities as determined necessary by the Foundation to carry out its mission.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H46D6D9CE68354743BC07EBACD47FC321"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority of the foundation</header><text>The Foundation shall be the sole entity responsible for carrying out the activities described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H803A2EDEA11D419DB55F58900A4E4CC6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Stakeholder engagement</header><text>The Foundation shall convene, and may consult with, representatives from the Institute, institutions of higher education, the private sector, non-profit organizations, and commercialization organizations to develop activities for the mission of the Foundation under subsection (b) and to advance the activities of the Foundation under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF894EA4E6A5A43939CC96338C4225F9F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Foundation shall not be an agency or instrumentality of the Federal Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE87361150E6149B9A42CB7E42CF6FD45"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Support</header><text>The Foundation may receive, administer, solicit, accept, and use funds, gifts, devises, or bequests, either absolutely or in trust of real or personal property or any income therefrom or other interest therein to support activities under subsection (c), except that this subsection shall not apply if any of such is from a foreign country of concern or a foreign entity of concern.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA809282A57C4437881B1C5FB45F5819"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Tax exempt status</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall take all necessary and appropriate steps to ensure the Foundation is an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94AF590147124D35926B87551719D661"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Board of Directors</header><paragraph id="HF0CE4A319D6D4C469E3305AB4410A491"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Foundation shall be governed by a Board of Directors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAD8B211E51445499D5AE82E806F26D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><subparagraph id="H921D35BD49C24861BBF3418EA38973B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall be composed of the following:</text><clause id="H4082EA5B40D34CACBC49973975505014"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Eleven appointed voting members described in subparagraph (B).</text></clause><clause id="H2B4EA54BD1504156A8DFE62B8AECAEC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Ex officio nonvoting members described in subparagraph (C).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA48372074144590B9D339EC56AD9E89"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointed members</header><clause id="H31EED76B27C34161B0422692C67B6210"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Initial members</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, shall—</text><subclause id="H5C49EB3D7A26416C9E17495865F3F556"><enum>(I)</enum><text>seek to enter into an agreement with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to develop a list of individuals to serve as members of the Board who are well qualified and will meet the requirements of clauses (ii) and (iii); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3C8062CC852C4EA1AFDF27EFDD977EA3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>appoint the initial members of the Board from such list, if applicable, in consultation with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0317C59DFA624D97B43801784AAF37DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>The appointed members of the Board shall reflect a broad cross-section of stakeholders across diverse sectors, regions and communities, including from academia, private sector entities, technical standards bodies, the investment community, the philanthropic community, and other nonprofit organizations.</text></clause><clause id="H93FE2A0ECB4C4131A03C118B01783E37"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Experience</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, shall ensure the appointed members of the Board have the experience and are qualified to provide advice and information to advance the Foundation’s mission, including in science and technology research and development, technical standards, education, technology transfer, commercialization, or other aspects of the Foundation’s mission.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F16966207A24B0F8CB565585295C7A0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Nonvoting members</header><clause id="H3A8A06FAD9D54B569BE5559FB89347BE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Ex officio members</header><text>The Director (or Director’s designee) shall be an ex officio member of the Board.</text></clause><clause id="HECC902AFF5D24C049BCB5428F2AF5257"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>No voting power</header><text>The ex officio members described in clause (i) shall not have voting power on the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FF562C16CBD4B1AB49722C5804637C1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chair and vice chair</header><subparagraph id="HEA340B37AFBA425CADE9C6F028022B04"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall designate, from among its members—</text><clause id="HBC92456A7DA6481A8D740930B6FAEA9A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an individual to serve as the chair of the Board; and</text></clause><clause id="H499E36503E6A4C029A7B5CDD63218276"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an individual to serve as the vice chair of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21E7F5B704D44B20A3A071B0BB86FFFA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Terms</header><text>The term of service of the Chair and Vice Chair of the Board shall end on the earlier of—</text><clause id="H0C75B322D47A4E489D2847AFBA1BA0E0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date that is 3 years after the date on which the Chair or Vice Chair of the Board, as applicable, is designated for the respective position; and</text></clause><clause id="H05C722568DF64C75A5AF80508102FA98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the last day of the term of service of the member, as determined under paragraph (4)(A), who is designated to be Chair or Vice Chair of the Board, as applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20CA4EC765964859985DC8201E1E37D0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>The Chair and Vice Chair of the Board—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6f9a9cb855554d97950f741c3071d890"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not be representatives of the same area of subject matter expertise, or entity, as applicable; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5ffe3755fae54e8b9f9756b1332727f2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not be representatives of any area of subject matter expertise, or entity, as applicable, represented by the immediately preceding Chair and Vice Chair of the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AE9B0E0A7594639B4FA84FDE90B58C9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terms and vacancies</header><subparagraph id="H25DFEB0141764BACABB76A068CAAE75C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Term limits</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the term of office of each member of the Board shall be not more than five years, except that a member of the Board may continue to serve after the expiration of the term of such member until the expiration of the 180-day period beginning on the date on which the term of such member expires, if no new member is appointed to replace the departing board member.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B3432B9197D489F8EAE55BD12B31E65"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Initial appointed members</header><text>Of the initial members of the Board appointed under paragraph (4)(A), half of such members shall serve for four years and half of such members shall serve for five years, as determined by the Chair of the Board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE99D772AC58A49398E2C1D2C7BF807BF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the membership of the appointed members of the Board—</text><clause id="HE82788648C014ABEABAF98333EF11A22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be filled in accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation by an individual capable of representing the same area or entity, as applicable, as represented by the vacating board member under paragraph (2)(B)(ii);</text></clause><clause id="HA4A149EEBB9C4E409B5BD6EA0AB0E91C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not affect the power of the remaining appointed members to carry out the duties of the Board; and</text></clause><clause id="HD039EB47C89441D79553F2D0C3B84A2A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall be filled by an individual selected by the Board.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H01DDA092B60043E8A504250B16FB3BA5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the members of the Board shall constitute a quorum for the purposes of conducting the business of the Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8FB0F8F5B1A4374A3E05B14B08B2052"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Board shall carry out the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2258F5B117DB4C8893AA329330323A33"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Establish bylaws for the Foundation in accordance with paragraph (7).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3ED9EE016AF741479395DEA739A727ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Provide overall direction for the activities of the Foundation and establish priority activities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H595323A9589941F58987FE76CD2F23AD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Coordinate with the Institute the activities of the Foundation to ensure consistency with the programs and policies of the Institute.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72D5AD6EDA1C4E188A177BF5D3E550D4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Evaluate the performance of the Executive Director of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17F79ADBFEBC4CBAB4A74F8AE14E5DE6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Actively solicit and accept funds, gifts, grants, devises, or bequests of real or personal property to the Foundation, including from private entities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4816BA743B784B3A970E24FD43901EF6"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Carry out any other necessary activities of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE50AE5D5056D446CBE87949A579FE453"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Bylaws</header><text>The Board shall establish bylaws for the Foundation. In establishing such bylaws, the Board shall ensure the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBCFBC3F7C8C549C8B4D72140ED6CAEB6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The bylaws of the Foundation include the following:</text><clause id="HEC925D0845EF4E96988C99C1B78C0578"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Policies for the selection of the Board members, officers, employees, agents, and contractors of the Foundation.</text></clause><clause id="HA08C0309374C4A73AB2E8B45572DCA93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Policies, including ethical and disclosure standards, for the following:</text><subclause id="H8F660697B3B6495196CD022F72F3660D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The acceptance, solicitation, and disposition of donations and grants to the Foundation, including appropriate limits on the ability of donors to designate, by stipulation or restriction, the use or recipient of donated funds.</text></subclause><subclause id="HCFA23138EF2E4B21BA16B43EBA6FE0A5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The disposition of assets of the Foundation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H5812311732C74C378D45A8EEF17C4CA0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Policies that subject all employees, fellows, trainees, and other agents of the Foundation (including appointed voting members and ex officio members of the Board) to conflict of interest standards.</text></clause><clause id="H15DA810F68044EDC9B57DFAF4E7543E2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The specific duties of the Executive Director of the Foundation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7077E5A8347F413DBEFA630A2D83B628"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The bylaws of the Foundation and activities carried out under such bylaws do not—</text><clause id="H35FE566794B640FDB3A0FCB058A6160D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reflect unfavorably upon the ability of the Foundation to carry out its responsibilities or official duties in a fair and objective manner; or</text></clause><clause id="HDAFD27C5C7B6430F95CAFA5C13FB99F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>compromise, or appear to compromise, the integrity of any governmental agency or program, or any officer or employee employed by, or involved in a governmental agency or program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C34A0F2465A48B384AE5D8FE003950F"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Restrictions on membership</header><subparagraph id="idad9ec2385afd4d06bc2c0a5feb959e9e"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Employees</header><text>No employee of the Department of Commerce may be appointed as a voting member of the Board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5254800189124eaaa1a34fbd8ae70dd5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Status</header><text>Each voting member of the Board shall be—</text><clause id="id05f3dd9ca10441e2a6b06dbdd177a582"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a citizen of the United States;</text></clause><clause id="id80d4024ca33e476ea58867e81214e0bc"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a national of the United States (as such term is defined in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="id1bcd73d43820402e96c92cff5584fc7c"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an alien admitted as a refugee under section 207 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="id9ef2ab91fee54790b3db8aa5afb9f5a6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an alien lawfully admitted to the United States for permanent residence.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D227DF0D2B54B9CAB0A1A0D5F0DFDEF"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Compensation</header><subparagraph id="HD01D4D5A8C5344E2A7CDC7C339D23CF1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Members of the Board may not receive compensation for serving on the Board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12E97BC2BCFD49519B2538A37C761592"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain expenses</header><text>In accordance with the bylaws of the Foundation, members of the Board may be reimbursed for travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, and other necessary expenses incurred in carrying out the duties of the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B5F56B4FF5E423F99D218ED4BF22F8D"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Liaison representatives</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, shall designate representatives from across the Institute to serve as the liaisons to the Board and the Foundation.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc52454a48daf4462b747ae4be5e2b994"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Personal liability of Board members</header><text>The members of the Board shall not be personally liable, except for malfeasance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9FFE1D9FFB7A4ABDA2A7D760634F5FE4"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Administration</header><paragraph id="H7C64455ECAC44B61ADE1B4CFFC595545"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><subparagraph id="H6AAA09C56A6345A5A740E4411E9D3D55"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Foundation shall have an Executive Director who shall be appointed by the Board, and who shall serve at the pleasure of the Board, and for whom the Board shall establish the rate of compensation. Subject to the bylaws established under subsection (i)(7), the Executive Director shall be responsible for the daily operations of the Foundation in carrying out the activities of the Foundation under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEE3B27F51B24C698B3FF339AE2E8FAA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>In carrying out the daily operations of the Foundation, the Executive Director of the Foundation shall carry out the following:</text><clause id="H945BB6D9266A43ECAB58DE31EC757684"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Hire, promote, compensate, and discharge officers and employees of the Foundation, and define the duties of such officers and employees.</text></clause><clause id="HB7FF8F088E5E4583A2ACC55CA2B16BDC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Accept and administer donations to the Foundation, and administer the assets of the Foundation.</text></clause><clause id="H40BFFCD80E1E4A329ED9F8E85191C923"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Enter into such contracts and execute legal instruments as are appropriate in carrying out the activities of the Foundation.</text></clause><clause id="H3AC65D23725544F0873FED0F929AB500"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Perform such other functions as necessary to operate the Foundation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idf4a9a18816264709912750ce787b718f"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><clause id="id16637f820e29464fa235f8145150e752"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text>The Executive Director shall be—</text><subclause id="id22144bc7bc024c9ba9d0eca8ce5aa477"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a citizen of the United States;</text></subclause><subclause id="id1d6a8aad800b41898ee67462a7bb7d8c"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a national of the United States (as such term is defined in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="id2d88f17bb7de4d869ae8ecd76b649813"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an alien admitted as a refugee under section 207 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause id="id3a0c3cbbb9c64a4e820d864a3e90bb65"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an alien lawfully admitted to the United States for permanent residence.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="iddbbdef6a663a46d488736e087dfcd096"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Officers and employees</header><text>Each officer or employee of the Foundation shall be—</text><subclause id="idf480618941b5434a971759ab2d2284a2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a citizen of the United States;</text></subclause><subclause id="id99ed3a42c9ab4157b224195872db8e0a"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a national of the United States (as such term is defined in section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="idacdbe7775b1c4222babe14b374a6feb0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an alien admitted as a refugee under section 207 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause id="ide441a140f48d4fe1aa80c4fd060418b9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an alien lawfully admitted to the United States for permanent residence. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A17A04C4007400BA8ECE8D7BEDECDE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative control</header><text>No member of the Board, officer or employee of the Foundation or of any program established by the Foundation, or participant in a program established by the Foundation, may exercise administrative control over any Federal employee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2045F5C75E454837BE70667A91554316" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transfer of funds to Institute</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Foundation may transfer funds and property to the Institute, which the Institute may accept and use and which shall be subject to all applicable Federal limitations relating to federally funded research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD42E75D1D3B24111A1CED17E54E8CB21"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the establishment of the Foundation, the Foundation shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a strategic plan that contains the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3B65F21405D9486AA5EB4B02D0A795F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A plan for the Foundation to become financially self-sustaining in the next five years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BB5254DA23F4E4385C5155FE6F75071"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Short- and long-term objectives of the Foundation, as identified by the Board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88BCE2BED39D4C28AB28EB08BD7EBDD5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the efforts the Foundation will take to be transparent in the processes of the Foundation, including processes relating to the following:</text><clause id="HFFFC3591CD1B4F5C82FE904795BFEF55"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Grant awards, including selection, review, and notification.</text></clause><clause id="H9D85429D99114886AAA97939A50E45FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Communication of past, current, and future research priorities.</text></clause><clause id="H7D625ACAFC6D414A8AE6B93AE3EB354E" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Solicitation of and response to public input on the priorities identified by the Foundation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1764CF8E7264BD0970B151FC08D7A42"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the financial goals and benchmarks of the Foundation for the following ten years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB06D668781BD40DB974A004A6D664187"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the efforts undertaken by the Foundation to ensure maximum complementarity and minimum redundancy with investments made by the Institute. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF99DEC33AB7E42B0AA6F02F9079F34CC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report</header><subparagraph id="HF81AA8EA0FCB420D9C7BBA1A0047713F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the establishment of the Foundation and not later than February 1 of each year thereafter, the Foundation shall publish a report describing the activities of the Foundation during the immediately preceding fiscal year. Each such report shall include with respect to such fiscal year a comprehensive statement of the operations, activities, financial condition, progress, and accomplishments of the Foundation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6E726C4AA694C10BDD3E035D8C5A3D3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Financial condition</header><text>With respect to the financial condition of the Foundation, each report under subparagraph (A) shall include the source, and a description of, all support under subsection (g) provided to the Foundation. Each such report shall identify the persons or entities from which such support is received, and include a specification of any restrictions on the purposes for which such support may be used.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H603BEE71C4704CED9E1790B5E778F2BE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>The Foundation shall make copies of each report submitted under subparagraph (A) available—</text><clause id="HA275AFE1A2744D74B907A3D2ABEE8317"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for public inspection, and shall upon request provide a copy of the report to any individual for a charge not to exceed the cost of providing such copy; and</text></clause><clause id="HF97140D1CD61491A882FBCB2F29B18B3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8701C4FB8734D468AEEAD152741A0E6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Audits and disclosure</header><text>The Foundation shall—</text><subparagraph id="HF9FB10B70B784DB89D1BA9B72041D9F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide for annual audits of the financial condition of the Foundation, including a full list of the Foundation’s donors and any restrictions on the purposes for which gifts to the Foundation may be used; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4178013BDB204AD0922B5F1204AFF468"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make such audits, and all other records, documents, and other papers of the Foundation, available to the Secretary and the Comptroller General of the United States for examination or audit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF732A077B02B4BDEBC2E892A08BBEF27"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Evaluation by Comptroller General</header><text>Not later than five years after the date on which the Foundation is established, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBBD2FDB95F294ED597C004AD0CA50DFE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An evaluation of the following:</text><clause id="HA099A13828224C6DB3C7B4E66B3DF2EB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The extent to which the Foundation is achieving the mission of the Foundation.</text></clause><clause id="HF52B180736A248DA9AB76E322FEE5ADF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The operation of the Foundation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70C8A54EB67D4428A83A30DA263356F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any recommendations on how the Foundation may be improved.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0FD7CB18D5D64C01904E21122D7D522C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Integrity</header><paragraph id="H33DF12F9B3CD4BCE9921E94CE0F110D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To ensure integrity in the operations of the Foundation, the Board shall develop and enforce procedures relating to standards of conduct, financial disclosure statements, conflicts of interest (including recusal and waiver rules), audits, and any other matters determined appropriate by the Board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H237D1B686BEC449693CDE321EE4565F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Financial conflicts of interest</header><text>To mitigate conflicts of interest and risks from malign foreign influence, any individual who is an officer, employee, or member of the Board is prohibited from any participation in deliberations by the Foundation of a matter that would directly or predictably affect any financial interest of any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCF71C1D9082E4F119F656A20E2F96F2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Such individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AFE86B6F24E4173A4425E1442CCC236" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A relative of such individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC15C4074AF6A4D38B16BDFC0EA2A6E6F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A business organization or other entity in which such individual or relative of such individual has an interest, including an organization or other entity with which such individual is negotiating employment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idbbbe08f5768f4ad198e40ab5fad7ec4e"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Security</header><text>This section shall be carried out in accordance with the provision of subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>; enacted as part of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>) and section 223 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6605">42 U.S.C. 6605</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1502421D59344FB83BD4BAD3AAFD7E1"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Intellectual property</header><text>The Board shall adopt written standards to govern the ownership and licensing of any intellectual property rights developed by the Foundation or derived from the collaborative efforts of the Foundation</text></subsection><subsection id="H05DA71A80197484A99036F23F7A3AAC8"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Full faith and credit</header><text>The United States shall not be liable for any debts, defaults, acts, or omissions of the Foundation. The full faith and credit of the United States shall not extend to any obligations of the Foundation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0701E324D77C48519BACF766D1C7E857"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Support services</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director, may provide facilities, utilities, and support services to the Foundation if it is determined by the Director to be advantageous to the research programs of the Institute.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F6B15CAD48F44FEB02A2C9A66A5C4B2" commented="no"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Nonapplicability</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Foundation.</text></subsection><subsection id="id3bc9d146a1c1427d99d1ba7c3292b593"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Separate fund accounts</header><text>The Board shall ensure that amounts received pursuant to the authorization of appropriations under subsection (q) are held in a separate account from any other funds received by the Foundation. </text></subsection><subsection id="HCD6F9687A2154DF5951E7031689E58A0"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Funding; authorization of appropriations</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, from amounts authorized to be appropriated for a fiscal year beginning with fiscal year 2025 to the Secretary of Commerce pursuant to section 10211, the Director may transfer not less than $500,000 and not more than $1,250,000 to the Foundation each such fiscal year. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8A86C402D8ED4B0ABEE60BAC50E15939"><enum>(r)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBF5068E3FF034E73A34CB2CF7125C067"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Board</term> means the Board of Directors of the Foundation, established pursuant to subsection (i).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H316F8CD85E284B1492DF29F7B8AC37F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id811888c951fd45dcaec8691cda7cf049"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign country of concern</header><text>The term <term>foreign country of concern</term> has the meaning given such term in section 10638 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19237">42 U.S.C. 19237</external-xref>; enacted as part of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9ab191f3460d4145baf43bbb0184b551"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign entity of concern</header><text>The term <term>foreign entity of concern</term> has the meaning given such term in section 10638 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19237">42 U.S.C. 19237</external-xref>; enacted as part of division B of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E06A6230B2642D2A84D735268F2C8C6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foundation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Foundation</term> means the Foundation for Standards and Metrology established pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE72B9699487E4392AD5DF598B7533FA0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institute</header><text>The term <term>Institute</term> means the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C3527E9B3124DA48BFB3E6F5F8EA366"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DCED37590694DBF839BFC98CE2A9C84"><enum>(8)</enum><header>NIST associate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>NIST associate</term> means any guest researcher, facility user, volunteer, or other nonemployee of the National Institute of Standards and Technology who conducts research or otherwise engages in an authorized activity with National Institute of Standards and Technology personnel or at a National Institute of Standards and Technology facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H518665C55A7D4C0A9734286719631BC8"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Relative</header><text>The term <term>relative</term> has the meaning given such term in section 13101 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA638DFC83DF149DA8BA2E001C10AEF61"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA958E89DF6C84517B744E7F850DA243D"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Technical standard</header><text>The term <term>technical standard</term> has the meaning given such term in section 12(d)(5) of the National Technology Transfer and Advancement Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/272">15 U.S.C. 272</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6e1dd11f83bc45bb90936a56d9c99ad2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref> is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 10235 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id0D72545C8C394D46984B1719AC58CC0B" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 10236. Foundation for Standards and Metrology.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="idF9496B99D7E74118966A626FB1FFC2CD" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>304.</enum><header>Prohibition on certain policies relating to the use of artificial intelligence or other automated systems</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 7 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President, acting through the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, shall issue a technology directive with respect to artificial intelligence or other automated systems that prohibits any action, directive, rule, regulation, policy, principle, or guidance by a Federal agency that includes policies that require, recommend, promote, or encourage any of the following concepts or rules:</text><paragraph id="idcdee77c9cd9b4fd0a418a094329a45ac"><enum>(1)</enum><text>One race or sex is inherently superior to another race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf78027b10cb442de93b13aa269338c5a"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States is fundamentally racist or sexist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id05a992abd71345389bf9d255de17b713"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An individual, by virtue of his or her race or sex, is inherently racist, sexist, or oppressive, whether consciously or unconsciously.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id382cdbfb4ea546c18ab7426a8422db76"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An individual should be discriminated against or receive adverse treatment solely or partly because of his or her race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idcb4e9a7178e14563a5708c1701534d20"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Members of one race or sex cannot and should not attempt to treat others without respect to race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1f5e5a9fbe6248239b6b54b7bd3c5c17"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The moral character of an individual is necessarily determined by his or her race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1b35094e80ef4e1db45f5ba9d81c0a1d"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An individual, by virtue of his or her race or sex, bears responsibility for actions committed in the past by other members of the same race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf8c5d238635045e8a83e2700d38b6f2e"><enum>(8)</enum><text>An individual should feel discomfort, guilt, anguish, or another form of psychological distress on account of his or her race or sex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ida68ec51099cd444ca18a03c69168bb30"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Meritocracy or traits such as a hard work ethic are racist or sexist, or were created by a particular race to oppress another.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idd5e0905428f14bd18bfdf44692ba4c0b"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Artificial intelligence, algorithms, or other automated systems should be designed in an equitable way that prevents disparate impacts based on a protected class or other societal classification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5ba6d309fc3a4cc2b07461e4af86cc55"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Input data used by designers, developers, or deployers of artificial intelligence, algorithms, or other automated systems should be modified to prevent disparate impacts based on a protected class or other societal classification.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id9036b589a17345b0bc646e107544efa1"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Designers, developers, integrators, or deployers of artificial intelligence, algorithms, or other automated systems should conduct disparate impact or equity impact assessments prior to deployment or implementation of such technology to ensure inclusivity and equity in the creation, design, or development of the technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf6257d7d7a4246dca1cde9a2d93baa9e"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Federal agencies should review input data used by designers, developers, or deployers of artificial intelligence, algorithms, or other automated systems to ensure the technology—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idb8693467552540a0b48285f53a0c73e8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets the view of that Federal agency of what constitutes bias or misinformation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ida384ce5d142a470ebd3c009c5518978a"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contains no positions contrary to the position of the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="id772f95e3f1694f05be018864924151a5" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><enum>305.</enum><header>Certifications and audits of temporary fellows</header><subsection id="idacfc2975efdd4416999fb6d0d094a965"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="ide4ef0aa39d2b4cd29b30bb1b09b5ddec"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3502 of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idbfd7c5071f2e4c8ba78b74848177d5c8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Committees of Jurisdiction</header><text>The term <term>committees of jurisdiction</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id67dd6ce5d3f340cc8568c5d3bc9896a7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd72a3b7c2eb04573a977ff731a2de249"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ida4e170af8681469696c06d08b068784c"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical and emerging technologies</header><text>The term <term>critical and emerging technologies</term> means a subset of artificial intelligence and other critical and emerging technologies included in the list of such technologies identified and maintained by the National Science and Technology Council of the Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idc633ce152f2148f5a11353b06da525f5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Inherently governmental function</header><text>The term <term>inherently governmental function</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5 of the Federal Activities Inventory Reform Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/270">Public Law 105–270</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/501">31 U.S.C. 501</external-xref> note) and includes the meaning given such term in subpart 7.5 of part 7 of the Federal Acquisition Regulation, or successor regulation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide5c262a701d74b108c83b697bce3f22a"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Temporary fellow</header><text>The term <term>temporary fellow</term>, with respect to an agency, means a fellow, contractor, consultant, or any other person performing work for the agency who is not a Federal government employee.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id15582ebc81d54776a547eaf03148ed9a"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><paragraph id="id7ecc3a84919e41cbadddf550ebea7e92"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Prior to performing any work for an agency under this Act relating to artificial intelligence and other critical and emerging technologies, a temporary fellow and the head of the agency shall sign a certification that the temporary fellow will not perform any inherently governmental functions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ide7bdf6225d1d4458ba0cc9d3e9b81f24"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submittal</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the head of an agency signs a certification under paragraph (1), the head of the agency shall submit a copy of the certification to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget and the chairpersons and ranking members of the committees of jurisdiction.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id07fc4a6fdb5e4cf5ab2d94fa7f93119b"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Audit</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idfeecf217c3e445f3b513e96dc684705d"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>For each agency using a temporary fellow to carry out this Act, the inspector general of the agency shall perform an annual audit of the use of temporary fellows by the agency, which includes—</text><subparagraph id="idafe0beb0fd00441e8c907f7852c9e674"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of temporary fellows used by the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id529dae7f9c914f95b6a455a5f05fa7e8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the entities paying any temporary fellow for their work for the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id03092a2264754d3590d3aea63d3c774e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the work temporary fellows are performing for the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6f0ba9ad3e674655a856eefa0f90fd2f"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the authorities under which the agency hired the temporary fellows; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7491125b55b54c249f27bea2b11adcaf"><enum>(E)</enum><text>whether the temporary fellows and the agency are complying with the requirements of section (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="ide5953fbd2ba242bd8d9f3770e1c9e705"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submittal to Congress</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the inspector general of an agency completes an audit under paragraph (1), the head of the agency shall submit to the chairpersons and ranking members of the committees of jurisdiction and the Director of the Office of Management and Budget a report containing the findings of inspector general with respect to the audit. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20241218" legis-day="20241216">December 18 (legislative day, December 16), 2024</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

