<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BAG24B29-HH0-5Y-43S"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S4758 IS: To require the Secretary of Defense to carry out a pilot program on using artificial intelligence-enabled software to optimize the workflow and operations of depots, shipyards, and other manufacturing facilities run by the Department of Defense, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-07-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 4758</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20240724">July 24, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S381">Mr. Rounds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Defense to carry out a pilot program on using artificial intelligence-enabled software to optimize the workflow and operations of depots, shipyards, and other manufacturing facilities run by the Department of Defense, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="id390eb675d69d47a7a5fff9793f0375b9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Department of Defense pilot program on use of artificial intelligence</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id981a3fe4c1d34846999a07f866f27ed0"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pilot program required</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall commence carrying out a pilot program to assess the feasibility and advisability of using artificial intelligence-enabled software to optimize the workflow and operations for—</text><paragraph id="ida6860d1342204ae8b82c53212deed10a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>depots, shipyards, or other manufacturing facilities run by the Department of Defense; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idad6d3a2623f34752bd2c52df4422e6e4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>contract administration for the Department, including the adjudication and review of contracts managed by the Defense Contract Management Agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7967e080d4af44c5b7b03d35fe772b3e"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Software</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program required by subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="id596c34bfe1754e62ad4e9e39ff533f7c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use best in breed software platforms; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id23f573b1e1e2402c91b5b7398293f2da"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consider industry best practices in the selection of software programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id82229411033e4f43b7e3f6a03a62e07f"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be implemented based on human centered design practices to best identify the business needs for improvement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf4e011bf54804de29f7c67f0b249af13"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demonstrate connection to enterprise platforms of record with relevant data sources.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idcd9d51bd7a7e4ba7b09236b40fe8be25"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minimum expenditures</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program required by subsection (a), the Secretary shall expend or obligate not less than $35,000,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="ida1cfc0edc8a14ac880decff5e52b328f"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program required by subsection (a)(1) in consultation with the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment, the Secretary of the Army, Secretary of the Navy, and Secretary of the Air Force.</text></subsection><subsection id="id17836d3550d64d8498aac8627a57af6a"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the commencement of the pilot program pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate and the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives a report containing the following information:</text><paragraph id="id2470f10ecb2b42de9fac0ce706f96514"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An evaluation of each software platform used in the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idec90f19a61044ba2a7b049822b1089cc"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An analysis of how workflows and operations were modified as part of the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id436c3fc6c15748a99b13989f112582fe"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A quantitative assessment of the impact the software had at each of the locations in which the pilot program was carried out.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

