<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-BAG24821-RGL-P0-L5P"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 S4976 IS: Artificial Intelligence Acquisitions Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>2d Session</session><legis-num>S. 4976</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20240801">August 1, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S350">Mr. Rubio</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S404">Mr. Scott of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S317">Mr. Barrasso</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSCM00">Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Office of Information and Communication Technology Services and other Federal agencies to develop a list of artificial intelligence products and services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence Acquisitions Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idde010989074e4382b2bfc3fd6289c527"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4729d21d1b3a4a188f8cdf6cd948e53d"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Artificial intelligence</header><text>The term <term>artificial intelligence</term> has the meaning given that term in section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id731c898c36bf41f1983f50124a22a199"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Control</header><text>The term <term>control</term> has the meaning given that term in section 800.208 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id75d6c7cfb35d44b4b9bc3b1c54015c47"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text>The term <term>country of concern</term>—</text><subparagraph id="id93d9f7627ec44ac3bedfc4fa09480f00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a country the government of which is a foreign adversary, as defined in section 8(c) of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1607">47 U.S.C. 1607(c)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5c67b4d854b346698d06fcd3531e3e7f"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="idde234c95d2ed4a34852d5ae2b1a5ba52"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the People’s Republic of China (including the Special Administrative Regions of the People’s Republic of China, Hong Kong and Macau);</text></clause><clause id="id87996dedcea04debb9a92a1a79a22275"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Russian Federation;</text></clause><clause id="idb5bab04d9f9d4e06b1c7e92eada72945"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Islamic Republic of Iran;</text></clause><clause id="id7e06ed9d0f8048e49aea8661cc94b950"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea;</text></clause><clause id="id02d62b4d52bb4b5ab67698050bcdd615"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Republic of Cuba; </text></clause><clause id="id47c98dbe1c684f25be1153c8fa060175"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Maduro Regime of Venezuela; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idc0bbc542f00f4ca991f522dc4b5e1c0d"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Syrian Arab Republic.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id6fd018ba6d304be486c1a72374394077"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 5122 of title 42, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id3ef9725b19334012a6616a37c17dd027"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Firmware</header><text>The term <term>firmware</term> has the meaning given the term in section 120.40 of title 22, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id8eadf68a35f64172a0fdb4ccff40bf78" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Foreign person of concern</header><text>The term <term>foreign person of concern</term> means— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id4c4a90f1d2454806b672d2c5a13dcbab"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any corporation, business association, partnership, trust, society, financial institution, insurer, underwriter, guarantor, and any other business organization, any other nongovernmental entity, organization, or group, or any government or agency thereof, that—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf39a701415a94685bba9e3722e1e1d99"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is domiciled in or subject to the laws of a country of concern;</text></clause><clause id="ide6c2423b87e645168c7337fee6d0444b"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is directly or indirectly controlled by any person domiciled in or subject to the laws of a country of concern; or</text></clause><clause id="id3d4947b1ce79484fbd34a74bcacadc1d"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is directly or indirectly controlled by a government of a country of concern; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id97b28bf1c1b14702b0f615ab7c69d7be"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any successor to any entity described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id0b7ea11c489e4757b357a1b63bd96f34"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <term>person</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="id1c6100fae96e4148b50e105992bcd3b8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a natural person; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id7cc21c5b64f242baa664368ff9f386c0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a corporation, business association, partnership, society, trust, financial institution, insurer, underwriter, guarantor, and any other business organization, any other nongovernmental entity, organization, or group, or any government or agency thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb6a9d6fa435a4b60ad7eef63bd109cf3"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Semiconductor chip product</header><text>The term <term>semiconductor chip product</term> has the meaning given the term in section 901 of title 17, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id639fb4d714d840ab86f05e0a1ba301e9"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Executive Director</header><text>The term <term>Executive Director</term> means the Executive Director for Information and Communications Technology and Services.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="id31e7f34397114951881fe012c29a6313"><enum>3.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Determination of artificial intelligence and large language model products or services posing national security risks</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id56b46cf316724864b6fddbc93453f26e"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development of list</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7c4a4f0f687d484d86b30a3fa91ef333"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Executive Director, in coordination with the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology and the Federal Acquisition Security Council, shall develop a list containing any artificial intelligence product or service that meets 1 or more of the following criteria: </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id30da2d5ea6f94fbd9dd74513b444853e"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Uses software or firmware produced or developed by a foreign person of concern.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id328c9363048447ef9bf6b79d1ca488cf"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Has a logic semiconductor chip product that is manufactured by a foreign person of concern.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idce6271a6fca74ef5b90b5796795c1e78"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Is offered by a foreign person of concern.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id24b57e10b2f94245a19683a02eefa901"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application to logic semiconductor chips</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)(B), the term <quote>manufactured</quote> does not include the assembly, testing, or packing of logic semiconductor chips.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idaf993caf4bac40ac814dc6da6649a81d" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Publication of list</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, Executive Director, in coordination with the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology and the Federal Acquisition Security Council, shall publish on a publicly available website of the Office of Information and Communication Technology Services of the Bureau of Industry and Security the list developed pursuant to subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="iddb3df2a5cdcd49a4998329ba82c80ca0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updates to list</header><paragraph id="idd46821cad44d4e8197ca27338071f21f"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Executive Director, in coordination with the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology and the Federal Acquisition Security Council, shall annually update the list developed pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id478d8219f726465ba7cf9a80f5e7171e"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Removal from list</header><text>The Executive Director may remove an artificial intelligence product or service from the list developed pursuant to subsection (a) if—</text><subparagraph id="ida6eb4a7c20a3421d9c6e8e6a8f6b4e82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the person that owns such product or service submits to the Federal Acquisition Security Council a certification that the product or service does not meet any of the criteria described in subsection (a), including information in support of such certification; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id68bf2d69431e485d83c53e184d11308e"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Federal Acquisition Security Council—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id2ddc8b9b72ec4382b9fd7ae818b070b4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviews such certification and information; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id03db5006c3104d9799641e8ac3ef4d1d"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">certifies to the Executive Director that the product or service does not meet any of the criteria described in subsection (a). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="id63920334a15c452781b3f4a8d863e64f"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public notification</header><text>If the list is not updated pursuant to paragraph (1) during the most recently completed annual period, then not later than 90 days after the end of such annual period, the Federal Acquisition Security Council shall notify the public that no updates were necessary during such annual period to protect national security.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="idfb3e340e51264c3e84416da76e26f24d"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on purchase of covered artificial intelligence and large language model products and services</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idf4544044c160405a993845ce05b293e7"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prohibition on purchase of covered products and services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 30 days after the date the list developed pursuant to section 4(a) is published in accordance with section 4(c), the head of a Federal department or agency may not—</text><paragraph id="id0dd6ca562dba46dca950ec0a6bcd8c81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>purchase, rent, lease, or otherwise obtain any artificial intelligence or large language model product or service included on such list; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2684ca00df804a71be790086f80daa5c"><enum>(2)</enum><text>award contracts, grants, or otherwise use any Federal funds to procure a product or service from persons that use any such artificial intelligence or large language model product or service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id6d283fede5324f47bf746a0299e543b3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Divestment from covered products and services</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id3a65db4c13dd42dc8e372b594e16b063"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial divestment</header><text>Any person that is a recipient of a contract to sell a product or provide a service for a Federal agency and has acquired, prior to the date of the enactment of this Act, artificial intelligence and large language model products or services from a foreign person of concern through purchase, rental, lease, or contract shall divest from and discontinue use of such products or services not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9dba27c4343e46da82843589ac2dd738"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ongoing divestment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date an artificial intelligence or large language model product or service is added to the list developed pursuant to section 4(a), any person that is a recipient of a contract to sell a product or provide a service for a Federal agency that uses such product or service shall divest from and discontinue use of such product or service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="idb62a9573703445f4ae358d83b9fd9d25" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception on prohibition on purchase for intelligence activities</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any other authorized intelligence activity (as that term is described in section 1101 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3231">50 U.S.C. 3231</external-xref>)). </text></subsection><subsection id="id1000da10647a4b0c91f40a3ecdb557d7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception for certain Department of Defense activities</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to the Secretary of Defense with respect to the procurement of any artificial intelligence or large language model product for the purpose of engaging in defense intelligence activities or researching adversarial artificial intelligence.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

