<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6164504D37B646D5B3A62F73761D1D50" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 3863 IH: Fair Representation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2021-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">117th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3863</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20210614">June 14, 2021</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C000754">Mr. Cooper</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the use of ranked choice voting in elections for Senators and Representatives in Congress, to require each State with more than one Representative to establish multi-member congressional districts, to require States to conduct congressional redistricting through independent commissions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H421CF06EC9124AB8BC8AF9E7B0DCD587" style="OLC"><section id="HFEACE2CE90ED4BF58A7CAB3EBFDF7328" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H752402D4D97346CA8F7ECA5F6F09A3E6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Representation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C23D84AC4914871A530FD6014D964F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="yes-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HFEACE2CE90ED4BF58A7CAB3EBFDF7328" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFE92A1F43B724CBFA55F37F3BB9DD563" level="section">Sec. 2. Finding of constitutional authority.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H826C310F12F649F0B6A1120600D0DE8C" level="title">Title I—Ranked Choice Voting</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9D46C86C6D454282A5E4E996F20485B1" level="section">Sec. 101. Requiring ranked choice voting for election of Senators and Representatives.</toc-entry><toc-quoted-entry style="OLC"><toc-entry idref="H67B669B6DC7145B184A3E4BE6B9EF08E" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Ranked Choice Voting</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC92C8FDF9F514020A822F62FF22D22BE" level="part">Part 1—Requiring Ranked Choice Voting for Election of Senators and Representatives</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0B21A5AF5925489D91C48E7F58B9F2C9" level="section">Sec. 321. Requiring ranked choice voting for election of Senators and Representatives.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFC0A14B777EA41C0B545FF51DEC35BDC" level="section">Sec. 322. Application to District of Columbia and territories.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H449ADF7ED52440D7A7D042CD42D60F75" level="section">Sec. 323. Treatment of States not holding primary elections prior to date of general election.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H371D9B4075334D298B5F173582E00FA5" level="part">Part 2—Tabulation Process</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8BD39F750864CAEB5B1076D1AE1553E" level="section">Sec. 331. Tabulation for single-seat congressional elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8A8B116F13694872BEA3214B966E2D0D" level="section">Sec. 332. Tabulation for multi-seat congressional elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3D1652F8C0DB4AA7A000928280B81003" level="section">Sec. 333. Exclusion of inactive ballots.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3ACE9C9D5B42498C9F94311AA9882408" level="section">Sec. 334. Batch elimination.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDCD8CF4D7A6E4318B12211B0247E25DC" level="section">Sec. 335. Treatment of ties between candidates.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H450B8BBFCCB64B10B42E3DFFEF1D5A9F" level="section">Sec. 336. Continuing candidate defined.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4DB4B49B1C3E4815B5ED75140D2DD194" level="part">Part 3—Payments to States To Implement Ranked Choice Voting</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6F7F3C97EEC44E46ACB876686489A5E2" level="section">Sec. 341. Payments to States to implement ranked choice voting.</toc-entry></toc-quoted-entry><toc-entry idref="H39D7A9E60932411B9691B60978EDDD51" level="section">Sec. 102. Applicability of enforcement provisions of Help America Vote Act of 2002.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5BBDB395839E40B89F3683784F735762" level="section">Sec. 103. Effective date.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H419B5B7FB429418D8CC4F8FAEDCFC4A8" level="title">Title II—Multi-member Districts</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H40C942238ABC404192E73BBAC8AC4902" level="section">Sec. 201. Requiring use of multi-member districts in certain States.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8A6CC2B85A8641ECB82A20C453473946" level="section">Sec. 202. Requiring certain States to elect all Representatives at large.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H759FBA06CF9F4647A0CB07FED974207A" level="section">Sec. 203. Establishing minimum number of candidates in general election.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB6AD43300339476D8A81AC86108F6EBF" level="section">Sec. 204. Conforming amendments.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5DFB157446E4409480D6B40E7F93B05A" level="section">Sec. 205. Exception for States in which use of multi-member districts will result in diminishment of voting rights.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF17F8E68130A4549B45FE12C1100ADFC" level="section">Sec. 206. Effective date.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H873FF27DC79B43A398B4954FE478D0C0" level="title">Title III—Requirements for Congressional Redistricting </toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H762DC82934F042B0BB3E3C110A277107" level="subtitle">Subtitle A—General Requirements</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF920368F73464360BA876DC8E414DB2C" level="section">Sec. 301. Requiring congressional redistricting to be conducted through plan of independent State commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4A82B20D865E4321B1EE54CBCD70A7EF" level="section">Sec. 302. Limit on congressional redistricting after an apportionment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0FC270CE386A4EE7AF1AFCBEFFF9DBF0" level="subtitle">Subtitle B—Independent Redistricting Commissions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6F0565A2AA644866A36EDFB3E5945CEA" level="section">Sec. 311. Independent redistricting commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD13D197744794595B33EFD1306083B51" level="section">Sec. 312. Establishment of selection pool of individuals eligible to serve as members of commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0617931E6BB84FF49265D4AEF0541D51" level="section">Sec. 313. Criteria for redistricting plan by independent commission; public notice and input.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H418793C3F6C14DF19CAAF4CB2DDA5CDA" level="section">Sec. 314. Establishment of related entities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H98B6B515BEA14ABD8255556716F3371D" level="section">Sec. 315. Report on diversity of memberships of independent redistricting commissions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6AA388DFD34B4004A68BDFAC0B83BCDB" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Role of Courts in Development of Redistricting Plans</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H96BE6D4A86F2464BACDE19D75D98C43F" level="section">Sec. 321. Enactment of plan developed by 3-judge court.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9A0936FD655C487EAA8D4E448D6497B5" level="section">Sec. 322. Special rule for redistricting conducted under order of Federal court.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC0098C4610AE4DA886D5680859B82567" level="subtitle">Subtitle D—Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H08C9A5E1249948B5916EF6E4E0831E64" level="section">Sec. 331. Payments to States for carrying out redistricting.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H202E645CAEB54B4D89DB375F9B68EBB3" level="section">Sec. 332. Civil enforcement.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H065CD499A10646E7ABA8D694C1B04970" level="section">Sec. 333. State apportionment notice defined.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 334. Special rules for redistricting pursuant to 2020 decennial census.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3E1D13A7897B4E8CB5AFE7343A117544" level="title">Title IV—General Provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF691BC01900A4676A760C1DB9E5EED37" level="section">Sec. 401. No effect on elections for State and local office.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9CD612103A92462E90141EF7B457FDE1" level="section">Sec. 402. Severability.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4E0CAAF9C08F463D969CC4993F20A989" level="section">Sec. 403. Effective date.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HFE92A1F43B724CBFA55F37F3BB9DD563"><enum>2.</enum><header>Finding of constitutional authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that it has the authority to establish the terms and conditions States must follow in carrying out congressional redistricting after an apportionment of Members of the House of Representatives and in administering elections for the Senate and House of Representatives because—</text><paragraph id="H96C94D654FAD4908BF5F6B68BE919F08"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the authority granted to Congress under article I, section 4 of the Constitution of the United States gives Congress the power to enact laws governing the time, place, and manner of elections for Senators and Members of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AE408C80714444BA37B97D7CF0B5E39"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the authority granted to Congress under section 5 of the 14th Amendment to the Constitution gives Congress the power to enact laws to enforce section 2 of such amendment, which requires Representatives to be apportioned among the several States according to their number.</text></paragraph></section><title id="H826C310F12F649F0B6A1120600D0DE8C"><enum>I</enum><header>Ranked Choice Voting</header><section id="H9D46C86C6D454282A5E4E996F20485B1"><enum>101.</enum><header>Requiring ranked choice voting for election of Senators and Representatives</header><subsection id="HCECB2195D9574601A70ABB1F1A9DC391"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subtitle:</text><quoted-block id="H38BFCA5FE8924C948143C4D950972ED4" style="OLC"><subtitle id="H67B669B6DC7145B184A3E4BE6B9EF08E"><enum>C</enum><header>Ranked Choice Voting</header><part id="HC92C8FDF9F514020A822F62FF22D22BE"><enum>1</enum><header>Requiring Ranked Choice Voting for Election of Senators and Representatives</header><section id="H0B21A5AF5925489D91C48E7F58B9F2C9"><enum>321.</enum><header>Requiring ranked choice voting for election of Senators and Representatives</header><subsection id="HC62C0B598C194BE5A6BC68224E74B719"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Ranked choice voting</header><text>Each State shall carry out elections for the office of Senator and the office of Representative in Congress using a system of ranked choice voting under which each voter shall rank the candidates for the office in the order of the voter’s preference, in accordance with the following:</text><paragraph id="H3A57702BE9D04A598688D342B50A5411"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In any single-seat election and any election for the office of Senator, the State shall carry out the election using single-seat ranked choice voting as described in section 331.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDB6F3644DFD4220A83246E72B5EE972"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In any multi-seat election, the State shall carry out the election using multi-seat ranked choice voting as described in section 332.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE85F153329CE4D7990359E533855F808"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ballot design</header><text>Each State shall ensure that the ballot used in an election carried out using a system of ranked choice voting under this title meets each of the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H2C6621FDCD8A4F50BA224DC552372993"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The ballot shall be simple and easy to understand.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68480EBE76A646ABA6306EEE37A8AF60"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The ballot shall include all qualified candidates for the election and (to the extent permitted under State law) options for voters to select write-in candidates. If feasible, the ballot shall permit voters to rank every candidate in the election. If it is not feasible for the ballot to permit voters to rank every candidate, the State may limit the number of candidates who may be ranked on the ballot to not fewer than six.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C21B6CA52C84AA39218C1D1029786E3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The ballot shall include such instructions as the State considers necessary to enable the voter to rank candidates and successfully cast the ballot under the system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85CCDECFEF294978A90D6E2D95745C97"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this title—</text><paragraph id="HA11F247447384BFD8A8746EB5ADE9B0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>single-seat election</term> means any primary election in which exactly one candidate in the primary election will advance to the general election, any special election for exactly one seat, any general election for the office of Senator, and any general election in which only one Representative is elected at large; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1F6B62F4A9645F48F3A6693ACD11C59"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>multi-seat election</term> means any primary election in which more than one candidate in the primary election will advance to the general election, any special election for more than one seat, and any general election in which more than one Representative is elected at large or in a multi-member district.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HFC0A14B777EA41C0B545FF51DEC35BDC"><enum>322.</enum><header>Application to District of Columbia and territories</header><subsection id="H67556B662B6D4F6F9529F2CCB9292FAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Election of delegates and resident commissioner</header><text>In this subtitle, the term <term>Representative</term> includes a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress.</text></subsection><subsection id="H910FEEA49B6949188DBF1EC6DA4BEB8F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application to Northern Mariana Islands</header><text>This subtitle shall apply with respect to the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands in the same manner as this subtitle applies to a State.</text></subsection></section><section id="H449ADF7ED52440D7A7D042CD42D60F75"><enum>323.</enum><header>Treatment of States not holding primary elections prior to date of general election</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this title shall be construed to require a State to hold a primary election for the office of Senator or Representative in Congress prior to the date established under section 25 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/7">2 U.S.C. 7</external-xref>) for the regularly scheduled general election for such office, so long as the determination of the candidates who are elected to such office is based solely on the votes cast with respect to the election held on such date, as determined in accordance with the system of ranked choice voting under this title.</text></section></part><part id="H371D9B4075334D298B5F173582E00FA5"><enum>2</enum><header>Tabulation Process</header><section id="HC8BD39F750864CAEB5B1076D1AE1553E"><enum>331.</enum><header>Tabulation for single-seat congressional elections</header><subsection id="H182D41D630A8475B82AAE778D9B78D90"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="HDECE569410D348D2A92452EBBB0C68B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination of candidate’s number of votes</header><text>In the case of a single-seat election, the number of votes received by a candidate in either the initial tabulation or in an additional round of tabulation shall be equal to the number of ballots on which that candidate is the highest ranked continuing candidate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F3A066ED23F4CDDB74E6FE778B9C73F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for election</header><text>In the case of a single-seat election, a candidate shall be elected to the office of Senator or Representative in Congress (or, in the case of a primary election, shall advance to the general election for such office as provided under the law of the State involved) if—</text><subparagraph id="H4108D2C9E3564E019F502B1CC80A1F9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the initial tabulation of ballots, the candidate receives a number of votes greater than 50 percent of the number of ballots cast in the election; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8019A9C1EFE44C7D96F1A3D8FCE8A146"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if the election official carries out an additional round of tabulation under subsection (b), the candidate receives the greatest number of votes of the 2 remaining continuing candidates (as described in such subsection).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB1B1A6C118244E8EB70EB8A063D65862"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Process in case no candidate elected under initial tabulation</header><paragraph id="H539282C465744B5AAD96D4E2FE1948CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Additional rounds of tabulation</header><text>If, under the initial tabulation of ballots, no candidate is elected to office (or, in the case of a primary election, no candidate advances to the general election for such office) under the criteria described in subsection (a)(2)(A), the election official shall carry out additional rounds of tabulation in accordance with paragraph (2) until only two continuing candidates remain.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCABB73A3A3074615B9114898251AE474"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of ballots in additional rounds</header><text>In each additional round of tabulation carried out under this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HEC3CC783EEB5449185F1CB64109EB4C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the candidate receiving the fewest number of votes among all candidates (or, in the case of a State which applies batch elimination under section 334, each candidate in the batch elimination group) shall be treated as a defeated candidate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F07089E86774C059BDDC29472AAA4BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each ballot cast for a defeated candidate, the election official shall determine the highest-ranked candidate on the ballot who is a continuing candidate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08DE9563B0A84F16A3E8FA4A80234C86"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the vote cast on the ballot shall be transferred to, and added to the total number of votes received by, the highest-ranked continuing candidate determined under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8A8B116F13694872BEA3214B966E2D0D"><enum>332.</enum><header>Tabulation for multi-seat congressional elections</header><subsection id="H5B874295C83F485198CC739EE6BB3CA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H7E071CD367D942C1B15C35C1D48163CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Votes counted in rounds</header><text>In the case of a multi-seat election, the votes shall be counted in a series of rounds of tabulation until the number of winning candidates equals the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election, as described in paragraph (4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6165B9269DDE4E4DA550099EFB095B6B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for election</header><text>In the case of a multi-seat election, a candidate shall be considered a winning candidate and shall be elected to one of the offices of Representative in the congressional district (or, in the case of a primary election, shall advance to the general election for such offices as provided under the law of State involved) if—</text><subparagraph id="H1C3F2D5A282B472A872916032828C16D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in any round, the candidate has a vote total that exceeds the multi-seat election threshold, as determined under this section; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F618E13FA4B4A08A209C9F78F0286BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the candidate is a continuing candidate and the number of remaining continuing candidates plus the number of candidates already designated as winning candidates is equal to or less than the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA15CE109B70D4F0F9F91FDA1C97C299A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Determination of multi-seat election threshold</header><text>The multi-seat election threshold with respect to an election shall be equal to the total number of valid votes cast in the election divided by the sum of the number one and the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election, rounded up to four decimal places.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC983752E3E3749CDB3BE3B234B4E832C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tabulation process</header><text>In the case of a multi-seat election, the votes shall be counted in a series of rounds, beginning with the initial round, under which each candidate has a number of votes equal to the number of votes cast in the election in which the candidate was the highest-ranked candidate, and proceeding as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H31BEC03137F8475198CC22C5E9979FF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>If, following any round of counting, the number of winning and continuing candidates combined is greater than the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election, and at least one candidate has a vote total that exceeds the multi-seat election threshold, as determined under this section, then the following round shall be a surplus tabulation round.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9A5182EA3F447F9B024F1DFB271C84E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If, following any round of counting, the number of winning and continuing candidates combined is greater than the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election, and no candidate has a vote total that exceeds the multi-seat election threshold, as determined under this section, then the following round shall be a candidate elimination round.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD912FBEE1AE4282894F2923031A520E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>If, following any round of counting, the number of winning and continuing candidates combined is equal to or less than the required number of winning candidates with respect to the election, then the remaining continuing candidates shall be designated as winning candidates, and the tabulation is complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H777ACE3042CE43BF9AE152ABFA0E43BB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Tabulation rounds described</header><subparagraph id="HD5C9A2A032E04550AA34F59DA416B7F4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Surplus tabulation round</header><text>In this section, a <quote>surplus tabulation round</quote> is a tabulation round under which each candidate with a vote total greater than the multi-seat election threshold is designated as a winning candidate and the surplus votes for such candidate are transferred to other candidates, as described in subsection (b)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5F623ACB1A04CFEA8CF40769C8E6FF4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Candidate elimination round</header><text>In this section, a <quote>candidate elimination round</quote> is a tabulation round under which the candidate with the fewest votes is designated as defeated and votes for that candidate are transferred to other candidates, as described in subsection (b)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91A436D41FED4495A74212F592651C98"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Process for transferring votes</header><paragraph id="HD01C19B2873B409BA2B926203950058E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Surplus tabulation rounds</header><text>In a surplus tabulation round, each candidate with a vote total that exceeds the multi-seat election threshold shall be designated as a winning candidate, and the election official shall transfer the surplus votes for each such candidate to other candidates as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H6B7513BD98B144329103299B8203B40B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The official shall determine the surplus fraction for each candidate designated as a winning candidate at the beginning of the round by taking the difference between the candidate’s vote total at the beginning of the round and the multi-seat election threshold, and dividing that difference by the candidate’s vote total at the beginning of the round.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12B8BA80D0F14DFEBBC9B7A0E3F49A1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The official shall reweight each vote counting for each candidate designated as a winning candidate at the beginning of the round by multiplying the vote’s current weight (equal to one if the vote has not been reweighted in any prior surplus tabulation round) by the surplus fraction determined with respect to the candidate under subparagraph (A), rounding down to four decimal places.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0937578AEFB3428DB65604B08C822525"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The official shall transfer each vote counting for each candidate designated as a winning candidate at the beginning of the round to the highest ranked continuing candidate on the ballot on which the vote was cast, counting the vote as a fraction of a vote equal to its new weight as determined under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H583306E001034E80A0B37C2B0664212D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>For all subsequent surplus tabulation rounds, the official shall set the vote total of each candidate designated as a winning candidate at the beginning of the round to be equal to the multi-seat election threshold.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AF0C72DDE95468891683F911E41289A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Candidate elimination rounds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a candidate elimination round, the candidate with the fewest votes (or, in the case of a State which applies batch elimination under section 334, each candidate in the batch elimination group) shall be designated as defeated, and the election official shall transfer the votes for such candidate to other candidates as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H1953E3D370BE4061AC72E39D36130521"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The official shall transfer each vote counting for the candidate designated as defeated at the beginning of the round to the highest ranked continuing candidate on the ballot on which the vote was cast, except that if the vote was counted as a fraction of a vote due to being reweighted in a prior surplus transfer round, it shall continue to count as the same fraction of a vote in the subsequent candidate elimination round.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B205C56018E422D9E25652B55ED9937"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For all subsequent candidate elimination rounds, the official shall set the vote total of each candidate designated as defeated at the beginning of the round to zero votes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3D1652F8C0DB4AA7A000928280B81003"><enum>333.</enum><header>Exclusion of inactive ballots</header><subsection id="H2A142CDDCA644B1399BCE1740287C181"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Initial tabulation</header><text>In the initial tabulation of ballots under section 331 or the initial round of tabulation under section 332, if a vote is cast on an inactive ballot, no vote on the ballot shall be counted for any candidate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE1F24E8EE256414E925C5D368D20185C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional rounds of tabulation</header><paragraph id="HCE19BA68EAE546B0BF780628A70CE42F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Single-seat elections</header><text>In any additional round of tabulation conducted with respect to a single-seat election under section 331(b), if a vote cast for a defeated candidate is cast on an inactive ballot, no vote on the ballot may be transferred to a continuing candidate under section 331(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11D78D10D3B64B29BB29F22C5078C128"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Multi-seat elections</header><text>In any additional round of tabulation conducted with respect to a multi-seat election under section 332(b)—</text><subparagraph id="HE8BF2E5515954BBA8880A2C03A523BC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if a vote cast for the winning candidate is cast on an inactive ballot, no portion of the surplus vote on such ballot may be transferred to a continuing candidate under any surplus vote tabulation round described in paragraph (2) of section 332(b); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD9E84DAECCD4523A08F986F0E7A8D1E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if a vote cast for a defeated candidate is cast on an inactive ballot, the vote may not be transferred to any continuing candidate under any candidate elimination round described in paragraph (3) of section 332(b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8E3FA8760F94C049635AAB560477821"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inactive ballot defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>inactive ballot</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H2F47417C68FB4B6F8A6FC66E75BFC99A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a ballot on which the voter does not rank any of the continuing candidates in order of preference;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H169750F2AFF244A796BEC5043B9C2C8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a ballot on which the voter ranked more than one continuing candidate at the highest order of preference; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H922C946DCF6A41D39C3DDA7F52DB64DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a ballot on which the voter skips two or more consecutive numerical rankings prior to the ranking for the continuing candidate at the highest order of preference.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3ACE9C9D5B42498C9F94311AA9882408"><enum>334.</enum><header>Batch elimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">At the option of the State, with respect to any candidate elimination round carried out under this subsection, a State may use batch elimination to treat multiple candidates as defeated candidates for purposes of section 331(b)(2) and section 332(b)(2). A continuing candidate is in the elimination batch if the number of winning and continuing candidates with more votes than that candidate is greater than the number of winning candidates required with respect to the election, and it is mathematically impossible for that candidate to be a winning candidate in the election for any of the following reasons:</text><paragraph id="H0551164CB08E43BBB452D299E052A555"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The candidate’s vote total in the initial tabulation of ballots plus all of the votes that could possibly be transferred to the candidate in the additional rounds of tabulation would not be enough to equal or surpass the continuing candidate with the next highest vote total in the initial tabulation of ballots.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E06EF78127D4275BB247148AE2A7B84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The candidate has a lower current vote total than a continuing candidate who is described by paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDCD8CF4D7A6E4318B12211B0247E25DC"><enum>335.</enum><header>Treatment of ties between candidates</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If a tie occurs between candidates with the greatest number of votes or the fewest number of votes at any point in the tabulation of ballots under this part and the tabulation cannot proceed until the tie is resolved, the tie shall be resolved in accordance with State law.</text></section><section id="H450B8BBFCCB64B10B42E3DFFEF1D5A9F"><enum>336.</enum><header>Continuing candidate defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part, the term <term>continuing candidate</term> means, with respect to any round of tabulation under this part, a candidate who is neither a winning candidate nor a candidate who is treated as a defeated candidate under such subsection during the tabulation of ballots under that round of tabulation.</text></section></part><part id="H4DB4B49B1C3E4815B5ED75140D2DD194"><enum>3</enum><header>Payments to States To Implement Ranked Choice Voting</header><section id="H6F7F3C97EEC44E46ACB876686489A5E2"><enum>341.</enum><header>Payments to States to implement ranked choice voting</header><subsection id="H7C00BBA31E9F44F19BFE7A7EE0B9B8F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Payments</header><text>Not later than June 1, 2021, the Commission shall make a payment to the State in an amount equal to—</text><paragraph id="H98DE4F9942534A2F938D2F87BDD6DA62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, $1,500,000; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7DD392806014DDEB22F3D5F4DE97742"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of any other State, the sum of $1,000,000 and the product of—</text><subparagraph id="HC04AAC79CB0341F5B77548E894ECFDDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of Representatives to which the State is entitled under the reapportionment of Representatives resulting from the regular decennial census conducted during 2020; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1635A5D16E942C28DE4FFBAE78A29B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$500,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD00512F43E3A48019DEAFE5B6FD19EA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A State shall use the payment made under subsection (a) to implement ranked choice voting under this subtitle, including educating voters about ranked choice voting, and to otherwise carry out elections for Federal office in the State.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2EA04522473A4CEE8AEBEFB35BD1A236"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No effect on requirements payments</header><text>The receipt or use of the payment made under this section shall not affect a State’s eligibility for or use of a requirements payment made under part 1 of subtitle D of title II.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7E06F075DE5F462F95E5702B09C7D3A1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for payments under this section.</text></subsection></section></part></subtitle><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H53945329CF5B4EE7A4F9AB1990346005"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by adding at the end of the item relating to title III the following:</text><toc container-level="title-container" idref="H826C310F12F649F0B6A1120600D0DE8C" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="yes-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"><toc-quoted-entry style="OLC"><toc-entry idref="H67B669B6DC7145B184A3E4BE6B9EF08E" level="subtitle">Subtitle C—Ranked Choice Voting</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC92C8FDF9F514020A822F62FF22D22BE" level="part">Part 1—Requiring Ranked Choice Voting for Election of Senators and Representatives</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 321. Requiring ranked choice voting for election of Senators and Representatives.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFC0A14B777EA41C0B545FF51DEC35BDC" level="section">Sec. 322. Application to District of Columbia and territories.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H449ADF7ED52440D7A7D042CD42D60F75" level="section">Sec. 323. Treatment of States not holding primary elections prior to date of general election.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H371D9B4075334D298B5F173582E00FA5" level="part">Part 2—Tabulation Process</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC8BD39F750864CAEB5B1076D1AE1553E" level="section">Sec. 331. Tabulation for single-seat congressional elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8A8B116F13694872BEA3214B966E2D0D" level="section">Sec. 332. Tabulation for multi-seat congressional elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3D1652F8C0DB4AA7A000928280B81003" level="section">Sec. 333. Exclusion of inactive ballots.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3ACE9C9D5B42498C9F94311AA9882408" level="section">Sec. 334. Batch elimination.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDCD8CF4D7A6E4318B12211B0247E25DC" level="section">Sec. 335. Treatment of ties between candidates.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H450B8BBFCCB64B10B42E3DFFEF1D5A9F" level="section">Sec. 336. Continuing candidate defined.</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="part">Part 3—Payments to States To Implement Ranked Choice Voting</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 341. Payments to States to implement ranked choice voting.</toc-entry></toc-quoted-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H39D7A9E60932411B9691B60978EDDD51"><enum>102.</enum><header>Applicability of enforcement provisions of Help America Vote Act of 2002</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 401 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>sections 301, 302, and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>title III</quote>.</text></section><section id="H5BBDB395839E40B89F3683784F735762"><enum>103.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title and the amendments made by this title shall apply with respect to—</text><paragraph id="HD2D5A89F51774C1782D1D1FEB1903732"><enum>(1)</enum><text>elections for the office of Senator which are held during 2022 or any succeeding year; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6973155BDD94906B627265628BD075A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>elections for the office of Representative which are held pursuant to the reapportionment of Representatives resulting from the regular decennial census conducted during 2020 and all subsequent elections.</text></paragraph></section></title><title id="H419B5B7FB429418D8CC4F8FAEDCFC4A8"><enum>II</enum><header>Multi-member Districts</header><section id="H40C942238ABC404192E73BBAC8AC4902"><enum>201.</enum><header>Requiring use of multi-member districts in certain States</header><subsection id="H698487B7AB674B4C9DA102E61C56EBF1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rules for States with six or more representatives</header><text>If a State is entitled to six or more Representatives in Congress under an apportionment made under section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)</external-xref>), the State shall establish a number of districts for the election of Representatives in the State that is less than the number of Representatives to which the State is entitled, and Representatives shall be elected only from districts so established.</text></subsection><subsection id="H382933C9EBA445B2873B6079F7070E12"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criteria for number of districts</header><text>In establishing the number of districts for the State under subsection (a), the State shall follow the following criteria:</text><paragraph id="H41DC4E73E5B049F0A3046BF0AB3410EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The State shall ensure that districts shall each have equal population per Representative as nearly as practicable, in accordance with the Constitution of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3453C5330E01492A8955590D12EDCD1B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of Representatives to be elected from any district may not be fewer than three or greater than five.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8A6CC2B85A8641ECB82A20C453473946"><enum>202.</enum><header>Requiring certain States to elect all Representatives at large</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If a State is entitled to five or fewer Representatives in Congress under an apportionment made under section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(a)</external-xref>), the State shall elect all such Representatives at large.</text></section><section id="H759FBA06CF9F4647A0CB07FED974207A"><enum>203.</enum><header>Establishing minimum number of candidates in general election</header><subsection id="H3AB5CBF024054496BC3A1286D7784029"><enum>(a)</enum><header>States with partisan nominating primaries</header><paragraph id="H0ADC3A834BF74145851CA1F95A792941"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, in a primary election for the office of Representative, the candidates that advance to the general election do so by winning the nomination of a political party (without regard to whether or not the election is open or closed to voters on the basis of political party preference), the State shall ensure that the number of candidates to be nominated by each political party is equal to the number of Representatives who will be elected from the district involved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4A031EA029141A1B3944E4D45D06C46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority of political parties to determine number of candidates advancing in multi-seat elections</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), in the case of a primary election described in such paragraph which is a multi-seat primary election, a State may permit a political party to adopt a rule that provides for such number of nominees of that political party to advance to the general election as the party considers appropriate, so long as the number is not less than two.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2328ED4334C04C369A812BD216884729"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Multi-seat primary election defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>multi-seat primary election</term> means a primary election held to select the candidates for a general election in which more than one Representative shall be elected.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H57EEBA7BD799428D981560D0E5974BC2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>States with nonpartisan blanket primaries</header><paragraph id="HD8E706D44AB34B68A81F695C943CEECA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number of candidates</header><text>If a State uses a nonpartisan blanket primary election to determine which candidates will advance to the general election for the office of Representative, the State shall ensure that the number of candidates who advance to the general election for the office is not less than the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="H19E9404A0B824FDAA46C4235A59FBCCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">five;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F6133C7FD194C0B89D30207BA208848"><enum>(B)</enum><text>twice the number of Representatives who will be elected from the district involved; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8996DEE6E3944DFF882330E8DF81F332"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such greater number as the State may establish by law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H41D3BE34DD814E15985BCBDD9AD598D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonpartisan blanket primary election defined</header><text>In this subsection, a <quote>nonpartisan blanket primary election</quote> is a primary election for the office of Representative conducted prior to the date established under section 25 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/7">2 U.S.C. 7</external-xref>) for the regularly scheduled general election for such office, under which—</text><subparagraph id="HD51A05D1F0C843319EC0826C0AAB546F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each candidate for such office, regardless of the candidate’s political party preference or lack thereof, shall appear on a single ballot;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7401A1EE6AE9437F8ECB1B9B9D5043D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each voter in the State who is eligible to vote in elections for Federal office in the district involved may cast a ballot in the election, regardless of the voter’s political party preference or lack thereof; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB052268474E9428D9335651FC012F20B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the identification and number of candidates who advance to the general election for the office is determined without regard to the candidates’ political party preferences or lack thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31CF593D6D9F408EB6D20C7EF38E7584"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception for states not holding primary elections prior to date of regularly scheduled general election</header><text>In the case of a State that does not hold primary elections for the office of Representative prior to the date established under section 25 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/7">2 U.S.C. 7</external-xref>) for the regularly scheduled general election for such offices, all seats shall be elected at the election taking place on such date.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB6AD43300339476D8A81AC86108F6EBF"><enum>204.</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><subsection id="HCFA4FF781235421C951F9593B122A026"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Election of Representatives prior to reapportionment</header><text>Section 22(c) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(c)</external-xref>), is amended by striking <quote>Until a State</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in title II of the Fair Representation Act, until a State</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H522D2C5A4AAD4B06A4BD7D15D72DED7A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Number of Representatives</header><text>Section 22(b) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for apportioning Representatives in Congress among the several States by the equal proportions method</quote>, approved November 15, 1941 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2b">2 U.S.C. 2b</external-xref>), is amended by striking <quote>Each State</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in title II of the Fair Representation Act, each State</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEA03C6EDC75D45958763FE266DF161DB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Number of Representatives from each district</header><text>The Act entitled <quote>An Act for the relief of Doctor Ricardo Vallejo Samala and to provide for congressional redistricting</quote>, approved December 14, 1967 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2c">2 U.S.C. 2c</external-xref>), is amended by striking <quote>In each State</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in title II of the Fair Representation Act, in each State</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H65A5DCA693014A9CBE22A3ECC68B180C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Nomination for Representatives at large</header><text>Section 5 of the Act entitled <quote>An Act For the apportionment of Representatives in Congress among the several States under the Thirteenth Census</quote>, approved August 8, 1911 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/5">2 U.S.C. 5</external-xref>), is amended by striking <quote>Candidates for Representative</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in title II of the Fair Representation Act, candidates for Representative</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H5DFB157446E4409480D6B40E7F93B05A"><enum>205.</enum><header>Exception for States in which use of multi-member districts will result in diminishment of voting rights</header><subsection id="HC0123F4601A14199BB6045E2D1216C87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the written evaluation of any of the redistricting plans of the independent redistricting commission of a State under subtitle B of title III with respect to the apportionment of Representatives resulting from a decennial census, as developed and published under section 313(e), indicates that the redistricting plan will deny or abridge the right to vote by having the effect of diminishing the ability of any citizens of the United States on account of race or color, or in contravention of the guarantees set forth in section 4(f)(2) of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10303">52 U.S.C. 10303(f)(2)</external-xref>), to elect their preferred candidates of choice—</text><paragraph id="H58E4D003765F49218A6C2C307226EFF4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>this title shall not apply with respect to any election held in the State which is based on the apportionment of Representatives to which such redistricting plan would apply; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FDEA970A8504168900303D45D6AAB1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the independent redistricting commission shall (in accordance with subtitle B of title III) develop and publish a redistricting plan for the State for purposes of title III under which there are no multi-member districts in the State.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H287FB72B9DD5495DBCAD92C1FE60256C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No effect on other requirements</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to waive the application of any of the other titles of this Act or the amendments made by any of the other titles of this Act to a State for which there are no multi-member districts as a result of this section, including the requirement to use ranked choice voting as set forth in title I or the requirement to carry out congressional redistricting in the State through the use of independent redistricting commissions as set forth in title III.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF17F8E68130A4549B45FE12C1100ADFC"><enum>206.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This title and the amendments made by this title shall apply with respect to the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress and each subsequent Congress.</text></section></title><title id="H873FF27DC79B43A398B4954FE478D0C0"><enum>III</enum><header>Requirements for Congressional Redistricting </header><subtitle id="H762DC82934F042B0BB3E3C110A277107"><enum>A</enum><header>General Requirements</header><section id="HF920368F73464360BA876DC8E414DB2C"><enum>301.</enum><header>Requiring congressional redistricting to be conducted through plan of independent State commission</header><subsection id="HE912611DA51941D38D8F53915F261A73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of Plan Required</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, and except as provided in subsection (c) and subsection (d), any congressional redistricting conducted by a State shall be conducted in accordance with—</text><paragraph id="H7D74B95A95A44D4F99F44C7B79F6B23B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the redistricting plan developed and enacted into law by the independent redistricting commission established in the State, in accordance with subtitle B; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53216E9E21DE4C4897E78F5C342AF2DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if a plan developed by such commission is not enacted into law, the redistricting plan developed and enacted into law by a 3-judge court, in accordance with section 321.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8CD9FB3B6C74841BFC209C70B6FDF30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 22(c) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(c)</external-xref>), is amended by striking <quote>in the manner provided by the law thereof</quote> and inserting: <quote>in the manner provided by title III of the Fair Representation Act</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFC0DD36CC4384FDDA5E4131780395C26"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special rule for existing commissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) does not apply to any State in which, under law in effect continuously on and after the date of the enactment of this Act, congressional redistricting is carried out in accordance with a plan developed and approved by an independent redistricting commission which is in compliance with each of the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="H29BA84344ADF4621917396D5D910A297"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publicly available application process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Membership on the commission is open to citizens of the State through a publicly available application process.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79DE53BD871B49238D4EE2381BD3C428"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disqualifications for government service and political appointment</header><text>Individuals who, for a covered period of time as established by the State, hold or have held public office, individuals who are or have been candidates for elected public office, and individuals who serve or have served as an officer, employee, or paid consultant of a campaign committee of a candidate for public office are disqualified from serving on the commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DF8E53C5FEF48BAB7C20F3C0BC28F4D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Screening for conflicts</header><text>Individuals who apply to serve on the commission are screened through a process that excludes persons with conflicts of interest from the pool of potential commissioners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87CD2813B7BB44C0AE6FE0E8336E470D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Multi-partisan composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Membership on the commission represents those who are affiliated with the two political parties whose candidates received the most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State, as well as those who are unaffiliated with any party or who are affiliated with political parties other than the two political parties whose candidates received the most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CD6E84CF2394C46BE8E4BE351C80D38"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Criteria for redistricting</header><text>Members of the commission shall draw maps in accordance with the criteria set forth in section 313(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7325D7814984798B66753E41620D412"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Public input</header><text>Public hearings are held and comments from the public are accepted before a final map is approved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H093FDFE34AD04BDD9212FF9BA0D13D82"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Broad-based support for approval of final plan</header><text>The approval of the final redistricting plan requires a majority vote of the members of the commission, including the support of at least one member of each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3DB845BC1E964A419F614BAEF9873207"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members who are affiliated with the political party whose candidate received the most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC59C96F4C2754E8982A8FF2C5205110D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members who are affiliated with the political party whose candidate received the second most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H411A19BDE677491888EE97EA222F5981"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members who not affiliated with any political party or who are affiliated with political parties other than the political parties described in subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4A82B20D865E4321B1EE54CBCD70A7EF"><enum>302.</enum><header>Limit on congressional redistricting after an apportionment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A State which has been redistricted in the manner provided by law after an apportionment under section 22(a) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a</external-xref>), may not be redistricted again until after the next apportionment of Representatives under such section, unless a court requires the State to conduct such subsequent redistricting to comply with the Constitution, to enforce the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10301">52 U.S.C. 10301 et seq.</external-xref>), to comply with this Act, or to comply with any other applicable Federal law.</text></section></subtitle><subtitle id="H0FC270CE386A4EE7AF1AFCBEFFF9DBF0"><enum>B</enum><header>Independent Redistricting Commissions</header><section id="H6F0565A2AA644866A36EDFB3E5945CEA"><enum>311.</enum><header>Independent redistricting commission</header><subsection id="H2C6462C9B12F4A71AFA5651E64C4F416"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Appointment of members</header><paragraph id="H16EEA830998F4B4D8B82BA95DC48A38F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The nonpartisan agency established or designated by a State under section 314(a) shall establish an independent redistricting commission for the State, which shall consist of 15 members appointed by the agency as follows:</text><subparagraph id="HD45858D546C04CAF9B603C4CC130A7E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than October 1 of a year ending in the numeral zero, the agency shall, at a public meeting held not earlier than 15 days after notice of the meeting has been given to the public, first appoint 6 members as follows:</text><clause id="H1EAD396C1F044E0A8CB6C6CC0218D537"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The agency shall appoint 2 members on a random basis from the majority category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(A)).</text></clause><clause id="H5E983BC40CBF4E73AB0B23523C6C9B0A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The agency shall appoint 2 members on a random basis from the minority category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(B)).</text></clause><clause id="H866E1BDD61E14E06BAC1E45125ED5F3D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The agency shall appoint 2 members on a random basis from the independent category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(C)).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6396E9F7A074C26A840EB684682193A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Not later than November 15 of a year ending in the numeral zero, the members appointed by the agency under subparagraph (A) shall, at a public meeting held not earlier than 15 days after notice of the meeting has been given to the public, then appoint 9 members as follows:</text><clause id="HBB3A3D4FBB5B4BCB810EA5D4A231FB45"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The members shall appoint 3 members from the majority category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(A)).</text></clause><clause id="HD6C51FBD8E68484C9DC857436AF70D17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The members shall appoint 3 members from the minority category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(B)).</text></clause><clause id="H2AB60BDDE94546D8994F5354CCA1751D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The members shall appoint 3 members from the independent category of the approved selection pool (as described in section 312(b)(1)(C)).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB967E1B1C42F46569D108B25E7A72559"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rules for appointment of members appointed by first members</header><subparagraph id="HE86A68C9563D4A95B5F0CDF1D43533A9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Affirmative vote of at least 4 members</header><text>The appointment of any of the 9 members of the independent redistricting commission who are appointed by the first members of the commission pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (1), as well as the designation of alternates for such members pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (3) and the appointment of alternates to fill vacancies pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (4), shall require the affirmative vote of at least 4 of the members appointed by the nonpartisan agency under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (1), including at least one member from each of the categories referred to in such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2122DBF7A6C4838ACB993613A1AB9CB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ensuring diversity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In appointing the 9 members pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (1), as well as in designating alternates pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (3) and in appointing alternates to fill vacancies pursuant to subparagraph (B) of paragraph (4), the first members of the independent redistricting commission shall ensure that the membership is representative of the demographic groups (including racial, ethnic, economic, and gender) and geographic regions of the State, and provides racial, ethnic, and language minorities protected under the Voting Rights Act of 1965 with a meaningful opportunity to participate in the development of the State’s redistricting plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A74D55E81854E9A94F8A16F93533A3D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Designation of alternates to serve in case of vacancies</header><subparagraph id="HF7030FBB56914B04940548004A1A4408"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Members appointed by agency</header><text>At the time the agency appoints the members of the independent redistricting commission under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (1) from each of the categories referred to in such subparagraph, the agency shall, on a random basis, designate 2 other individuals from such category to serve as alternate members who may be appointed to fill vacancies in the commission in accordance with paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8ABA91A507E4879921DECDADD7DE297"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Members appointed by first members</header><text>At the time the members appointed by the agency appoint the other members of the independent redistricting commission under subparagraph (B) of paragraph (1) from each of the categories referred to in such subparagraph, the members shall, in accordance with the special rules described in paragraph (2), designate 2 other individuals from such category to serve as alternate members who may be appointed to fill vacancies in the commission in accordance with paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FBECE23012D4C90B6BE4B5C99893E67"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appointment of alternates to serve in case of vacancies</header><subparagraph id="H632EE28F411B4460B22B67269809373D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Members appointed by agency</header><text>If a vacancy occurs in the commission with respect to a member who was appointed by the nonpartisan agency under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (1) from one of the categories referred to in such subparagraph, the agency shall fill the vacancy by appointing, on a random basis, one of the 2 alternates from such category who was designated under subparagraph (A) of paragraph (3). At the time the agency appoints an alternate to fill a vacancy under the previous sentence, the agency shall designate, on a random basis, another individual from the same category to serve as an alternate member, in accordance with subparagraph (A) of paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H663BA36A8EE04F618719A9E9745F4AC0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Members appointed by first members</header><text>If a vacancy occurs in the commission with respect to a member who was appointed by the first members of the commission under subparagraph (B) of paragraph (1) from one of the categories referred to in such subparagraph, the first members shall, in accordance with the special rules described in paragraph (2), fill the vacancy by appointing one of the 2 alternates from such category who was designated under subparagraph (B) of paragraph (3). At the time the first members appoint an alternate to fill a vacancy under the previous sentence, the first members shall, in accordance with the special rules described in paragraph (2), designate another individual from the same category to serve as an alternate member, in accordance with subparagraph (B) of paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC665ADD0BF95444897532996889451D7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Removal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of the independent redistricting commission may be removed by a majority vote of the remaining members of the commission if it is shown by a preponderance of the evidence that the member is not eligible to serve on the commission under section 312(a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3108793FD6E4FBFA3B81796B0DC7798"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Procedures for Conducting Commission Business</header><paragraph id="H908E70EE04334A679440B185507F50DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chair</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of an independent redistricting commission established under this section shall select by majority vote one member who was appointed from the independent category of the approved selection pool described in section 312(b)(1)(C) to serve as chair of the commission. The commission may not take any action to develop a redistricting plan for the State under section 313 until the appointment of the commission’s chair.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F1303028260471D81D736EEC17E2295"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requiring majority approval for actions</header><text>The independent redistricting commission of a State may not publish and disseminate any draft or final redistricting plan, or take any other action, without the approval of at least—</text><subparagraph id="HBACCAB3B87E9400EA72EC9CBC2A53D10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a majority of the whole membership of the commission; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EA46D29DA6F4A98B2D918E2B92879CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at least one member of the commission appointed from each of the categories of the approved selection pool described in section 312(b)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4B41BF136D6436DBC57F9B21194DFEE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A majority of the members of the commission shall constitute a quorum.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79CF9AC8E2A04991A29D9EF1A2BF3074"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staff; Contractors</header><paragraph id="H17DA7CDDE37541939EA8B81FE115ADA0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under a public application process in which all application materials are available for public inspection, the independent redistricting commission of a State shall appoint and set the pay of technical experts, legal counsel, consultants, and such other staff as it considers appropriate, subject to State law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE648D155DF734030813D31F3C8354B1B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contractors</header><text>The independent redistricting commission of a State may enter into such contracts with vendors as it considers appropriate, subject to State law, except that any such contract shall be valid only if approved by the vote of a majority of the members of the commission, including at least one member appointed from each of the categories of the approved selection pool described in section 312(b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H857221D45B0C4E6CAF7A18CB5749D0B4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reports on expenditures for political activity</header><subparagraph id="HE28FD9D404F04B4C86C526343913F3E6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report by applicants</header><text>Each individual who applies for a position as an employee of the independent redistricting commission and each vendor who applies for a contract with the commission shall, at the time of applying, file with the commission a report summarizing—</text><clause id="H8213589845844CA896F5168D41F1EF21"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any expenditure for political activity made by such individual or vendor during the 10 most recent calendar years; and</text></clause><clause id="H512F97CA665F45DE810918676AB6490A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any income received by such individual or vendor during the 10 most recent calendar years which is attributable to an expenditure for political activity.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EA5BA5D785C48BBBC526F4B06FDCE93"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual reports by employees and vendors</header><text>Each person who is an employee or vendor of the independent redistricting commission shall, not later than one year after the person is appointed as an employee or enters into a contract as a vendor (as the case may be) and annually thereafter for each year during which the person serves as an employee or a vendor, file with the commission a report summarizing the expenditures and income described in subparagraph (A) during the 10 most recent calendar years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3607DF04CCF64FFAA59E8ACFA899DF0E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Expenditure for political activity defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>expenditure for political activity</term> means a disbursement for any of the following:</text><clause id="HA4DF8069E14D4DD7B2D4142E75DA0B72"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An independent expenditure, as defined in section 301(17) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101(17)</external-xref>).</text></clause><clause id="HF4444BEDCADB45649A28C4185675A076"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An electioneering communication, as defined in section 304(f)(3) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30104">52 U.S.C. 30104(f)(3)</external-xref>) or any other public communication, as defined in section 301(22) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101(22)</external-xref>) that would be an electioneering communication if it were a broadcast, cable, or satellite communication.</text></clause><clause id="H298110E3FB484AC28E3E84F3852CEEAA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Any dues or other payments to trade associations or organizations described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such Code that are, or could reasonably be anticipated to be, used or transferred to another association or organization for a use described in paragraph (1), (2), or (4) of section 501(c) of such Code.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EE21B6427BF400DB488F98D107707D7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Goal of impartiality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The commission shall take such steps as it considers appropriate to ensure that any staff appointed under this subsection, and any vendor with whom the commission enters into a contract under this subsection, will work in an impartial manner, and may require any person who applies for an appointment to a staff position or for a vendor’s contract with the commission to provide information on the person’s history of political activity beyond the information on the person’s expenditures for political activity provided in the reports required under paragraph (3) (including donations to candidates, political committees, and political parties) as a condition of the appointment or the contract.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8F5C2D690724DF1BD68B2B4BE88B29D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Disqualification; waiver</header><subparagraph id="HFF83B809C42646A08503633DB8F232D2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The independent redistricting commission may not appoint an individual as an employee, and may not enter into a contract with a vendor, if the individual or vendor meets any of the criteria for the disqualification of an individual from serving as a member of the commission which are set forth in section 312(a)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD03C3DFB8DEC4B1DB65EC3E27BB7198E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The commission may by unanimous vote of its members waive the application of subparagraph (A) to an individual or a vendor after receiving and reviewing the report filed by the individual or vendor under paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD32A994A5C1941828250F6D708CF1769"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H6F302F4FF865461FA386E8B0778E0F30"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The independent redistricting commission of a State shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><subparagraph id="H1D05B8F0670F47E780F407BBEC008D42"><enum>(A)</enum><text>June 14 of the next year ending in the numeral zero; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12144309E50646A0A9CE6F41C5604977"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the day on which the nonpartisan agency established or designated by a State under section 314(a) has, in accordance with section 312(b)(1), submitted a selection pool to the Select Committee on Redistricting for the State established under section 314(b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H330F9372907C44EBABDF8394CA77D27E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preservation of records</header><text>The State shall ensure that the records of the independent redistricting commission are retained in the appropriate State archive in such manner as may be necessary to enable the State to respond to any civil action brought with respect to congressional redistricting in the State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD13D197744794595B33EFD1306083B51"><enum>312.</enum><header>Establishment of selection pool of individuals eligible to serve as members of commission</header><subsection id="H542967CF653F4E37BA183DF61F37582C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Criteria for Eligibility</header><paragraph id="HA018134A028D4125A63AF8D0FFC9E5DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An individual is eligible to serve as a member of an independent redistricting commission if the individual meets each of the following criteria:</text><subparagraph id="HE9CFD9DF5DAC4AC48B8766360E5D3648"><enum>(A)</enum><text>As of the date of appointment, the individual is registered to vote in elections for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A3BB3A09D534338847765DB703405D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>During the 3-year period ending on the date of the individual’s appointment, the individual has been continuously registered to vote with the same political party, or has not been registered to vote with any political party.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24CEC26B73B44B669567CC9592ECEC17"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual submits to the nonpartisan agency established or designated by a State under section 313, at such time and in such form as the agency may require, an application for inclusion in the selection pool under this section, and includes with the application a written statement, with an attestation under penalty of perjury, containing the following information and assurances:</text><clause id="H4A9BAD7F360940B491C667C601342C3A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The full current name and any former names of, and the contact information for, the individual, including an electronic mail address, the address of the individual’s residence, mailing address, and telephone numbers.</text></clause><clause id="H0D3D473FD85444CAA218EB19DB866C3A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The individual’s race, ethnicity, gender, age, date of birth, and household income for the most recent taxable year.</text></clause><clause id="H6FB6825C69D6408A881771587F4895AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The political party with which the individual is affiliated, if any.</text></clause><clause id="H22811D07988E4193BC0CD9FC4942BCDC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reason or reasons the individual desires to serve on the independent redistricting commission, the individual’s qualifications, and information relevant to the ability of the individual to be fair and impartial, including, but not limited to—</text><subclause id="H1F9C1AEDC3554B78BC44AC63447F5A80"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any involvement with, or financial support of, professional, social, political, religious, or community organizations or causes; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H05614B14D2FE4D6EA63F1B58109A75C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the individual’s employment and educational history.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4DFE8C95337C4EE580E7091B129BECD2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>An assurance that the individual shall commit to carrying out the individual’s duties under this Act in an honest, independent, and impartial fashion, and to upholding public confidence in the integrity of the redistricting process.</text></clause><clause id="HA1DB0B485E544AF1AB40D2BC24094276"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>An assurance that, during the covered periods described in paragraph (3), the individual has not taken and will not take any action which would disqualify the individual from serving as a member of the commission under paragraph (2).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H13400CE6B21C44B6A55358D276878876"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disqualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual is not eligible to serve as a member of the commission if any of the following applies during any of the covered periods described in paragraph (3):</text><subparagraph id="H35FA3FA82D7C476AB05AD92AF6E1001B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual holds public office or is a candidate for election for public office.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4141201F87E54B99AF03B23DEA6781F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual serves as an officer of a political party or as an officer, employee, or paid consultant of a campaign committee of a candidate for public office or of any political action committee (as determined in accordance with the law of the State).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H921718FA83684AC28A629EB14D3BC0F6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual holds a position as a registered lobbyist under the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1601">2 U.S.C. 1601 et seq.</external-xref>) or an equivalent State or local law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42D2F045446640C995AFE81FA366630F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual is an employee of an elected public official, a contractor with the government of the State, or a donor to the campaign of any candidate for public office or to any political action committee (other than a donor who, during any of such covered periods, gives an aggregate amount of $1,000 or less to the campaigns of all candidates for all public offices and to all political action committees).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC283A4BF4C99404388A00A2867DA4B80"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual paid a civil money penalty or criminal fine, or was sentenced to a term of imprisonment, for violating any provision of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAEACEF2F67094EE5A2C1B4214A1E1F15"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The individual or (in the case of the covered periods described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (3)) an immediate family member of the individual is an agent of a foreign principal under the Foreign Agents Registration Act of 1938, as amended (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/611">22 U.S.C. 611 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA2D02283582444DA081BDA84B08A4D7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered periods described</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>covered period</term> means, with respect to the appointment of an individual to the commission, any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2BEFA3FF9B3F4AE3BF4D7434151DA9BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 10-year period ending on the date of the individual’s appointment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3AFB767163B4D958F34CE23F385ADBD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The period beginning on the date of the individual’s appointment and ending on August 14 of the next year ending in the numeral one.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD76F7194BA11484C8317AB9FE14105AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The 10-year period beginning on the day after the last day of the period described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBCC4D76BA074780B745CAA71A6C06B3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Immediate family member defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>immediate family member</term> means, with respect to an individual, a father, stepfather, mother, stepmother, son, stepson, daughter, stepdaughter, brother, stepbrother, sister, stepsister, husband, wife, father-in-law, or mother-in-law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7711807212B04173A50E82317BD37477"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Development and Submission of Selection Pool</header><paragraph id="H9B88DE4F270346C29C5B06FBE9E1DC35"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 15 of each year ending in the numeral zero, the nonpartisan agency established or designated by a State under section 314(a) shall develop and submit to the Select Committee on Redistricting for the State established under section 314(b) a selection pool of 36 individuals who are eligible to serve as members of the independent redistricting commission of the State under this Act, consisting of individuals in the following categories:</text><subparagraph id="HA5B2F28FBED6424CA06D0370D642BBF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A majority category, consisting of 12 individuals who are affiliated with the political party whose candidate received the most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H452B62D700E14BEB82D3C960C3F2CEED"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A minority category, consisting of 12 individuals who are affiliated with the political party whose candidate received the second most votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D9F5772B1334DB5855BC7E93D54B681"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An independent category, consisting of 12 individuals who are not affiliated with either of the political parties described in subparagraph (A) or subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6865C86A1CEB4D4196434FC5AB374EDF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Factors taken into account in developing pool</header><text>In selecting individuals for the selection pool under this subsection, the nonpartisan agency shall—</text><subparagraph id="H757A808ECE194D8AB55D1D70919D4B19"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that the pool is representative of the demographic groups (including racial, ethnic, economic, and gender) and geographic regions of the State, and includes applicants who would allow racial, ethnic, and language minorities protected under the Voting Rights Act of 1965 a meaningful opportunity to participate in the development of the State’s redistricting plan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA90C7A73F6084BB9853B3F0E9452EEA1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>take into consideration the analytical skills of the individuals selected in relevant fields (including mapping, data management, law, community outreach, demography, and the geography of the State) and their ability to work on an impartial basis.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2FA968F7802427C87056B54FA5CC8B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interviews of applicants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To assist the nonpartisan agency in developing the selection pool under this subsection, the nonpartisan agency shall conduct interviews of applicants under oath. If an individual is included in a selection pool developed under this section, all of the interviews of the individual shall be transcribed and the transcriptions made available on the nonpartisan agency’s website contemporaneously with release of the report under paragraph (6).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B950B3A52944CE0967507789555CB5B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determination of political party affiliation of individuals in selection pool</header><text>For purposes of this section, an individual shall be considered to be affiliated with a political party only if the nonpartisan agency is able to verify (to the greatest extent possible) the information the individual provides in the application submitted under subsection (a)(1)(D), including by considering additional information provided by other persons with knowledge of the individual’s history of political activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59C16C705A8A447F96F8D59442B3C4FD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Encouraging residents to apply for inclusion in pool</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The nonpartisan agency shall take such steps as may be necessary to ensure that residents of the State across various geographic regions and demographic groups are aware of the opportunity to serve on the independent redistricting commission, including publicizing the role of the panel and using newspapers, broadcast media, and online sources, including ethnic media, to encourage individuals to apply for inclusion in the selection pool developed under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87441E0317BE4873960F7F4FDF45A691"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Report on establishment of selection pool</header><text>At the time the nonpartisan agency submits the selection pool to the Select Committee on Redistricting under paragraph (1), it shall publish and post on the agency’s public website a report describing the process by which the pool was developed, and shall include in the report a description of how the individuals in the pool meet the eligibility criteria of subsection (a) and of how the pool reflects the factors the agency is required to take into consideration under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D2D71134C804AD38DFC78A826D5A1B3"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Public comment on selection pool</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the 14-day period which begins on the date the nonpartisan agency publishes the report under paragraph (6), the agency shall accept comments from the public on the individuals included in the selection pool. The agency shall post all such comments contemporaneously on the nonpartisan agency’s website and shall transmit them to the Select Committee on Redistricting immediately upon the expiration of such period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C00B3CD5DCE4A05AEFC02AC0BF4682E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Action by Select Committee</header><subparagraph id="H07984B7EB60740719120DE4692B64FDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not earlier than 15 days and not later than 21 days after receiving the selection pool from the nonpartisan agency under paragraph (1), the Select Committee on Redistricting shall—</text><clause id="H6032C1A4A1484356BA97378E7F5F4668"><enum>(i)</enum><text>approve the pool as submitted by the nonpartisan agency, in which case the pool shall be considered the approved selection pool for purposes of section 311(a)(1); or</text></clause><clause id="H3951640C1DBF4C6FB366142A02444200"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reject the pool, in which case the nonpartisan agency shall develop and submit a replacement selection pool in accordance with subsection (c).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA31D93912D014052978E5BD5AD1845B0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inaction deemed rejection</header><text>If the Select Committee on Redistricting fails to approve or reject the pool within the deadline set forth in subparagraph (A), the Select Committee shall be deemed to have rejected the pool for purposes of such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H983D5964A28C4EC7B93942A4708E9AFB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development of Replacement Selection Pool</header><paragraph id="HE9A69327774647AF865E71E953D82339"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Select Committee on Redistricting rejects the selection pool submitted by the nonpartisan agency under subsection (b), not later than 14 days after the rejection, the nonpartisan agency shall develop and submit to the Select Committee a replacement selection pool, under the same terms and conditions that applied to the development and submission of the selection pool under paragraphs (1) through (7) of subsection (b). The replacement pool submitted under this paragraph may include individuals who were included in the rejected selection pool submitted under subsection (b), so long as at least one of the individuals in the replacement pool was not included in such rejected pool.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA70222DB57484414AD086364D6A5492C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Action by Select Committee</header><subparagraph id="H36EA94C3AADC4548B1513A19514F6B37"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 21 days after receiving the replacement selection pool from the nonpartisan agency under paragraph (1), the Select Committee on Redistricting shall—</text><clause id="H4957311F49B54CED8D7C80D08BBE39F0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>approve the pool as submitted by the nonpartisan agency, in which case the pool shall be considered the approved selection pool for purposes of section 311(a)(1); or</text></clause><clause id="H659F797E213D4B6182DD0E7681942CEF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reject the pool, in which case the nonpartisan agency shall develop and submit a second replacement selection pool in accordance with subsection (d).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC54AFEB60674CCD819A65222E331A27"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inaction deemed rejection</header><text>If the Select Committee on Redistricting fails to approve or reject the pool within the deadline set forth in subparagraph (A), the Select Committee shall be deemed to have rejected the pool for purposes of such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFC0774392EB4820893D5364507FEF4B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Development of Second Replacement Selection Pool</header><paragraph id="H3B68D8EDF7F349878A1D67F71CEB2412"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Select Committee on Redistricting rejects the replacement selection pool submitted by the nonpartisan agency under subsection (c), not later than 14 days after the rejection, the nonpartisan agency shall develop and submit to the Select Committee a second replacement selection pool, under the same terms and conditions that applied to the development and submission of the selection pool under paragraphs (1) through (7) of subsection (b). The second replacement selection pool submitted under this paragraph may include individuals who were included in the rejected selection pool submitted under subsection (b) or the rejected replacement selection pool submitted under subsection (c), so long as at least one of the individuals in the replacement pool was not included in either such rejected pool.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE76793ECBD0C4D23A57F2F6CDDA09CEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Action by Select Committee</header><subparagraph id="H0E962A1754EE4408ABC9E795973F5884"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not earlier than 15 days and not later than 14 days after receiving the second replacement selection pool from the nonpartisan agency under paragraph (1), the Select Committee on Redistricting shall—</text><clause id="H88890484825B48608FA8B58BA18A6D06"><enum>(i)</enum><text>approve the pool as submitted by the nonpartisan agency, in which case the pool shall be considered the approved selection pool for purposes of section 311(a)(1); or</text></clause><clause id="HA90FEF660324486C92FF2E6037B68FCF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reject the pool.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H252925C0C95E4FE8B29D560B38DEE78A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inaction deemed rejection</header><text>If the Select Committee on Redistricting fails to approve or reject the pool within the deadline set forth in subparagraph (A), the Select Committee shall be deemed to have rejected the pool for purposes of such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2B48B467858497389BAB60D5E7C534C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Effect of rejection</header><text>If the Select Committee on Redistricting rejects the second replacement pool from the nonpartisan agency under paragraph (1), the redistricting plan for the State shall be developed and enacted in accordance with subtitle C.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0617931E6BB84FF49265D4AEF0541D51"><enum>313.</enum><header>Criteria for redistricting plan by independent commission; public notice and input</header><subsection id="H7D73E395901B469987ACBAB28019B9B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development of redistricting plan</header><paragraph id="H9793D258C6944770AB59E117C2E07F65"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In addition to the criteria set forth in section 311(b), the independent redistricting commission of a State shall develop a redistricting plan for the State in accordance with the following criteria, prioritized according to the following order:</text><subparagraph id="HB977DC832DE74AED93FB6CC07DCCE3C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Districts shall comply with the United States Constitution, including the requirement that they equalize total population per Representative elected.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70246EAC3CC34FAD96E6CB120967DAB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Districts shall be established in a manner consistent with the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10301">52 U.S.C. 10301 et seq.</external-xref>) and all applicable Federal laws.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E776F90310F45FEA20AC3152FBC697E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Districts shall provide racial, ethnic, and language minorities with an equal opportunity to participate in the political process and to elect candidates of choice and shall not dilute or diminish their ability to elect candidates of choice whether alone or in coalition with others.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H948773352884415CB609341EE1D9E9E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To the extent practicable, districts shall reflect the diversity of political opinion in the State such that no district in the State—</text><clause id="HD7DC83BD58F84442B79512FD16B726CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>elects exactly 3 Representatives and the nominee of one political party for President received at least 75 percent of the votes cast in the geographic area covered by the district in 2 of the 3 most recent Presidential elections;</text></clause><clause id="H1E4BF541C956445EA1A79A4C577A123A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>elects exactly 4 Representatives and the nominee of one political party for President received at least 80 percent of the votes cast in the geographic area covered by the district in 2 of the 3 most recent Presidential elections; or</text></clause><clause id="H864D885153D64E1A9F83BC7373DDC23D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>elects exactly 5 Representatives and the nominee of one political party for President received at least 83 percent of the votes cast in the geographic area covered by the district in 2 of the 3 most recent Presidential elections.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB174873BAB147A1A1D24D5E921A520D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To the greatest extent practicable the State shall minimize the number of districts electing 4 Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDC37D37733F467DB181ADCFE8E849CA"><enum>(F)</enum><text>To the greatest extent practicable the State shall maximize the number of districts electing 5 Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CA9AF90597043C3A26535550AF34677"><enum>(G)</enum><text>To the extent practicable, districts shall minimize the division of any community of interest, municipality, county, or neighborhood. In this subparagraph, the term <term>community of interest</term> means an area with recognized similarities of interests, including but not limited to ethnic, economic, social, cultural, geographic, or historic identities. Such term may, in circumstances, include political subdivisions such as counties, municipalities, or school districts, but shall not include common relationships with political parties, officeholders, or political candidates.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H97CF068AAD7B40C88544F62A25801AB9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No favoring or disfavoring of political parties</header><text>The redistricting plan developed by the independent redistricting commission shall not, when considered on a statewide basis, unduly favor or disfavor any political party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C3D70B6CC774CB6B9BF70A0AB335DF4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibiting consideration of residence of member or other candidate</header><text>In developing the redistricting plan for the State, the independent redistricting commission may not take into consideration the residence of any Member of the House of Representatives or candidate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D9E77061D04425EB8F46A62A63E5031"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public notice and input</header><paragraph id="HBB274DB8CD774B5FBCF266242ECBA842"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of open and transparent process</header><text>The independent redistricting commission of a State shall hold each of its meetings in public, shall solicit and take into consideration comments from the public, including proposed maps, throughout the process of developing the redistricting plan for the State, and shall carry out its duties in an open and transparent manner which provides for the widest public dissemination reasonably possible of its proposed and final redistricting plans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA87E35680994466ACF31CBDEAA799FE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Website</header><subparagraph id="H532E38CF65544D75A80DFC78C5A3D4E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Features</header><text>The commission shall maintain a public internet site which is not affiliated with or maintained by the office of any elected official and which includes the following features:</text><clause id="HE70C3937FC83450A9628FD6912D6443C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>General information on the commission, its role in the redistricting process, and its members, including contact information.</text></clause><clause id="H3F939377A87845C0B37941CA6324E1FF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An updated schedule of commission hearings and activities, including deadlines for the submission of comments.</text></clause><clause id="H46E4504DB2AD4865A4F2E1799F3DF6B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>All draft redistricting plans developed by the commission under subsection (c) and the final redistricting plan developed under subsection (d), including the accompanying written evaluation under subsection (e).</text></clause><clause id="HCCBB2BF3B73B43D491FC97929A8D4BC6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>All comments received from the public on the commission’s activities, including any proposed maps submitted under paragraph (1).</text></clause><clause id="HF0514F13F3574ACFB588F92B9B64D7BE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Live streaming of commission hearings and an archive of previous meetings, including any documents considered at any such meeting, which the commission shall post not later than 24 hours after the conclusion of the meeting.</text></clause><clause id="H97508D10FC9D481380B88AD308239B70"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Access in an easily useable format to the demographic and other data used by the commission to develop and analyze the proposed redistricting plans, together with access to any software used to draw maps of proposed districts and to any reports analyzing and evaluating any such maps.</text></clause><clause id="HC9D0090D618C4633B98BC1B17968737B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>A method by which members of the public may submit comments and proposed maps directly to the commission.</text></clause><clause id="H03C7F92995BD4DE49331794D9AAF393D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>All records of the commission, including all communications to or from members, employees, and contractors regarding the work of the commission.</text></clause><clause id="HE88E4B818D8643A0AA99B46083A4A992"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of all contractors receiving payment from the commission, together with the annual disclosures submitted by the contractors under section 311(c)(3).</text></clause><clause id="HEB2523405E1A48E5A2E2F8C541DE50EA"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of the names of all individuals who submitted applications to serve on the commission, together with the applications submitted by individuals included in any selection pool, except that the commission may redact from such applications any financial or other personally sensitive information.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FD23B1BCEBF4167997D8881933CC75B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Searchable format</header><text>The commission shall ensure that all information posted and maintained on the site under this paragraph, including information and proposed maps submitted by the public, shall be maintained in an easily searchable format.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA642102EBCAB42769369D8FF9024E747"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>The commission shall ensure that the public internet site under this paragraph is operational (in at least a preliminary format) not later than January 1 of the year ending in the numeral one.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC035BDA3EBD448AD9825284F92ED0D8D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public comment period</header><text>The commission shall solicit, accept, and consider comments from the public with respect to its duties, activities, and procedures at any time during the period—</text><subparagraph id="H40A44F2FDCC449C88A37AA1EF40CF1A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>which begins on January 1 of the year ending in the numeral one; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65B0B87BAC3C43AEB6C44EAE4E55A5CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which ends 7 days before the date of the meeting at which the commission shall vote on approving the final redistricting plan for enactment into law under subsection (d)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8F8B5AEDD9D4BC6A36A126B5EB80EA3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Meetings and hearings in various geographic locations</header><text>To the greatest extent practicable, the commission shall hold its meetings and hearings in various geographic regions and locations throughout the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49307BC578404ABB8DEA499D9F5397BF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Multiple language requirements for all notices</header><text>The commission shall make each notice which is required to be posted and published under this section available in any language in which the State (or any jurisdiction in the State) is required to provide election materials under section 203 of the Voting Rights Act of 1965.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9D988375F9E4ED3B04B21E8EE23BC14"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development and Publication of Preliminary Redistricting Plan</header><paragraph id="H9E9DB5D398D2458891312D5EF9038D66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prior to developing and publishing a final redistricting plan under subsection (d), the independent redistricting commission of a State shall develop and publish a preliminary redistricting plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA1C8233F19449CEBC29D51AC88914DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minimum public hearings and opportunity for comment prior to development</header><subparagraph id="H4E25E2792FF74C7EBD8DF1513ED5E4B8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>3 hearings required</header><text>Prior to developing a preliminary redistricting plan under this subsection, the commission shall hold not fewer than 3 public hearings at which members of the public may provide input and comments regarding the potential contents of redistricting plans for the State and the process by which the commission will develop the preliminary plan under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75EB3FA70FC44C8A81D9F5B1E68B2A72"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum period for notice prior to hearings</header><text>Not fewer than 14 days prior to the date of each hearing held under this paragraph, the commission shall post notices of the hearing in on the website maintained under subsection (b)(2), and shall provide for the publication of such notices in newspapers of general circulation throughout the State. Each such notice shall specify the date, time, and location of the hearing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H063841A3F21F408D865CA88CCAC5E6A8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Submission of plans and maps by members of the public</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any member of the public may submit maps or portions of maps for consideration by the commission. As provided under subsection (b)(2)(A), any such map shall be made publicly available on the commission’s website and open to comment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H61168E81FA2E499DAB6ADF491F48F566"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication of preliminary plan</header><subparagraph id="HCBC9C867198244019D941A56012B3F7B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The commission shall post the preliminary redistricting plan developed under this subsection, together with a report that includes the commission’s responses to any public comments received under subsection (b)(3), on the website maintained under subsection (b)(2), and shall provide for the publication of each such plan in newspapers of general circulation throughout the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC24207F7DB374319B0B874241ACAA5F5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum period for notice prior to publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not fewer than 14 days prior to the date on which the commission posts and publishes the preliminary plan under this paragraph, the commission shall notify the public through the website maintained under subsection (b)(2), as well as through publication of notice in newspapers of general circulation throughout the State, of the pending publication of the plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H859079DF9C194C58BBEA56FC5BFEA6BF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Minimum post-publication period for public comment</header><text>The commission shall accept and consider comments from the public (including through the website maintained under subsection (b)(2)) with respect to the preliminary redistricting plan published under paragraph (3), including proposed revisions to maps, for not fewer than 30 days after the date on which the plan is published.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03390D7A2F0742B48ACA8F9FB78940C8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Post-publication hearings</header><subparagraph id="HE35458636C514503BB49FFC5ADEC120B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>3 hearings required</header><text>After posting and publishing the preliminary redistricting plan under paragraph (3), the commission shall hold not fewer than 3 public hearings in different geographic areas of the State at which members of the public may provide input and comments regarding the preliminary plan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF2821A480974D199FEED6025305D646"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum period for notice prior to hearings</header><text>Not fewer than 14 days prior to the date of each hearing held under this paragraph, the commission shall post notices of the hearing in on the website maintained under subsection (b)(2), and shall provide for the publication of such notices in newspapers of general circulation throughout the State. Each such notice shall specify the date, time, and location of the hearing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H617C09D677F640D497609AC39D89CA8A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Permitting multiple preliminary plans</header><text>At the option of the commission, after developing and publishing the preliminary redistricting plan under this subsection, the commission may develop and publish subsequent preliminary redistricting plans, so long as the process for the development and publication of each such subsequent plan meets the requirements set forth in this subsection for the development and publication of the first preliminary redistricting plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8311CAE73884202BA39E39002E5BAC9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Process for Enactment of Final Redistricting Plan</header><paragraph id="HC335B1BCA54C41CDAA569FAAF595D0A9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After taking into consideration comments from the public on any preliminary redistricting plan developed and published under subsection (c), the independent redistricting commission of a State shall develop and publish a final redistricting plan for the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H358B68164CBB4392A88ABC52F671CCC6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Meeting; final vote</header><text>Not later than the deadline specified in subsection (h), the commission shall hold a public hearing at which the members of the commission shall vote on approving the final plan for enactment into law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFD7090BD82C4F878C6B989695F837C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication of plan and accompanying materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not fewer than 14 days before the date of the meeting under paragraph (2), the commission shall provide the following information to the public through the website maintained under subsection (b)(2), as well as through newspapers of general circulation throughout the State:</text><subparagraph id="H10E43732D5BD41829ED6FC1AE3ABE4C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The final redistricting plan, including all relevant maps.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H634CE0AE94894FE891ECAB2B8110276F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A report by the commission to accompany the plan which provides the background for the plan and the commission’s reasons for selecting the plan as the final redistricting plan, including responses to the public comments received on any preliminary redistricting plan developed and published under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF8EA11033E14A519E553857DBA1C2E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any dissenting or additional views with respect to the plan of individual members of the commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CD0325B99FA4D6AAE4C787FEEB090D7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Enactment</header><text>The final redistricting plan developed and published under this subsection shall be deemed to be enacted into law if—</text><subparagraph id="HEC01E2F42AE24B6EA4955A6967A59041"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the plan is approved by a majority of the whole membership of the commission; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H034630F5EB584C5AB806F3307399E021"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at least one member of the commission appointed from each of the categories of the approved selection pool described in section 312(b)(1) approves the plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA7BE235BB3345A0A8CB6C359098AC2F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Written evaluation of plan against external metrics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The independent redistricting commission shall include with each redistricting plan developed and published under this section a written evaluation that measures each such plan against external metrics which cover the criteria set forth in paragraph (1) of subsection (a), including the impact of the plan on the ability of communities of color to elect candidates of choice, measures of partisan fairness using multiple accepted methodologies, and the degree to which the plan preserves or divides communities of interest.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB986B08566074FB5BE5DF2ABE643322F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The independent redistricting commission of a State may begin its work on the redistricting plan of the State upon receipt of relevant population information from the Bureau of the Census, and shall approve a final redistricting plan for the State in each year ending in the numeral one not later than 8 months after the date on which the State receives the State apportionment notice or October 1, whichever occurs later.</text></subsection></section><section id="H418793C3F6C14DF19CAAF4CB2DDA5CDA"><enum>314.</enum><header>Establishment of related entities</header><subsection id="HC8FAB541FC5B4B8A82B1D41F802B58CC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment or Designation of Nonpartisan Agency of State Legislature</header><paragraph id="HA9E8D25997E64FBBA743F73241C9626A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State shall establish a nonpartisan agency in the legislative branch of the State government to appoint the members of the independent redistricting commission for the State in accordance with section 311.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B05402E51744D92AA52147D408336BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonpartisanship described</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, an agency shall be considered to be nonpartisan if under law the agency—</text><subparagraph id="H68B620BF4D754D3FBFAD3D686E4D63DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is required to provide services on a nonpartisan basis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AC469EBED40406199985E6862F69F18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is required to maintain impartiality; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H483E7F6F3B0F4334AC9FE5020EEDD41D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is prohibited from advocating for the adoption or rejection of any legislative proposal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD434B8C07BCB4021A8A868E98C43620A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Training of members appointed to commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 15 of a year ending in the numeral one, the nonpartisan agency established or designated under this subsection shall provide the members of the independent redistricting commission with initial training on their obligations as members of the commission, including obligations under the Voting Rights Act of 1965 and other applicable laws.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50B220E6350C46B1B6ED4670DAF319DC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The nonpartisan agency established or designated under this subsection shall adopt and publish regulations, after notice and opportunity for comment, establishing the procedures that the agency will follow in fulfilling its duties under this Act, including the procedures to be used in vetting the qualifications and political affiliation of applicants and in creating the selection pools, the randomized process to be used in selecting the initial members of the independent redistricting commission, and the rules that the agency will apply to ensure that the agency carries out its duties under this Act in a maximally transparent, publicly accessible, and impartial manner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24E7DAA7CDDE41F8AD36CCDC819F59A9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Designation of existing agency</header><text>At its option, a State may designate an existing agency in the legislative branch of its government to appoint the members of the independent redistricting commission plan for the State under this Act, so long as the agency meets the requirements for nonpartisanship under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H205CEC2133F04A7DA33DDD617DC0661F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Termination of agency specifically established for redistricting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State does not designate an existing agency under paragraph (5) but instead establishes a new agency to serve as the nonpartisan agency under this section, the new agency shall terminate upon the enactment into law of the redistricting plan for the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA45D8F67BCE4926BFAC6173A6885022"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Preservation of records</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State shall ensure that the records of the nonpartisan agency are retained in the appropriate State archive in such manner as may be necessary to enable the State to respond to any civil action brought with respect to congressional redistricting in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF889DC46B5894645A29BC6B58DD52E56"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State shall meet the requirements of this subsection not later than each October 15 of a year ending in the numeral nine.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C43A462137B4E3DA392C4B284C995AA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of Select Committee on Redistricting</header><paragraph id="HD06D340D65584B818032A5F520737070"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State shall appoint a Select Committee on Redistricting to approve or disapprove a selection pool developed by the independent redistricting commission for the State under section 312.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9554CB2D98F84ED4A36F122E6C3BCE43"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The Select Committee on Redistricting for a State under this subsection shall consist of the following members:</text><subparagraph id="H8AF124ADED72441B8C22B1F25959CF18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One member of the upper house of the State legislature, who shall be appointed by the leader of the party with the greatest number of seats in the upper house.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF279791C9B9A4DB3B3998CC97D61A054"><enum>(B)</enum><text>One member of the upper house of the State legislature, who shall be appointed by the leader of the party with the second greatest number of seats in the upper house.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE39247E1A0746DA83D15B97248D2229"><enum>(C)</enum><text>One member of the lower house of the State legislature, who shall be appointed by the leader of the party with the greatest number of seats in the lower house.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H890338A6BD674D9B99A59E760E40C3AC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>One member of the lower house of the State legislature, who shall be appointed by the leader of the party with the second greatest number of seats in the lower house.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E05BDC95953408FAB9C45DDFCCB7B18"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Special rule for States with unicameral legislature</header><text>In the case of a State with a unicameral legislature, the Select Committee on Redistricting for the State under this subsection shall consist of the following members:</text><subparagraph id="H9284C5DE39EE495EAC33EF23B55D949F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Two members of the State legislature appointed by the chair of the political party of the State whose candidate received the highest percentage of votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63C2AA5654D9495CB4DBB33173B9984A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Two members of the State legislature appointed by the chair of the political party whose candidate received the second highest percentage of votes in the most recent statewide election for Federal office held in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6B15D24650147A79574462A293989D2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The State shall meet the requirements of this subsection not later than each January 15 of a year ending in the numeral zero.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H98B6B515BEA14ABD8255556716F3371D"><enum>315.</enum><header>Report on diversity of memberships of independent redistricting commissions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than May 15 of a year ending in the numeral one, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the extent to which the memberships of independent redistricting commissions for States established under this subtitle with respect to the immediately preceding year ending in the numeral zero meet the diversity requirements as provided for in sections 311(a)(2)(B) and 312(b)(2).</text></section></subtitle><subtitle id="H6AA388DFD34B4004A68BDFAC0B83BCDB"><enum>C</enum><header>Role of Courts in Development of Redistricting Plans</header><section id="H96BE6D4A86F2464BACDE19D75D98C43F"><enum>321.</enum><header>Enactment of plan developed by 3-judge court</header><subsection id="HE1E3C0BAF2524C2F9DBC2262D08D3B48"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development of Plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any of the triggering events described in subsection (f) occur with respect to a State—</text><paragraph id="H5B4703996F244B8D9ECDEE1EB8850AF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than December 15 of the year in which the triggering event occurs, the United States district court for the applicable venue, acting through a 3-judge Court convened pursuant to section 2284 of title 28, United States Code, shall develop and publish the congressional redistricting plan for the State; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H405E675904224153913123BE9DBBA90A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the final plan developed and published by the Court under this section shall be deemed to be enacted on the date on which the Court publishes the final plan, as described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H992B97CA102642D5AB85201C63668250"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicable venue described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the <quote>applicable venue</quote> with respect to a State is the District of Columbia or the judicial district in which the capital of the State is located, as selected by the first party to file with the court sufficient evidence of the occurrence of a triggering event described in subsection (f).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCADB61E8184B4F12AD71640E150BF6CC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Procedures for Development of Plan</header><paragraph id="HE496CCF5EE584F2DB5D2FFC14017A63E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In developing a redistricting plan for a State under this section, the Court shall adhere to the same terms and conditions that applied (or that would have applied, as the case may be) to the development of a plan by the independent redistricting commission of the State under section 313(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D8841DC454445E48FD25D02AFE7F260"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Access to information and records of commission</header><text>The Court shall have access to any information, data, software, or other records and material that was used (or that would have been used, as the case may be) by the independent redistricting commission of the State in carrying out its duties under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H870ACE7FD9EA4D0CBB265A5BA74DDD64"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Hearing; public participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing a redistricting plan for a State, the Court shall—</text><subparagraph id="H78CEDEB0389A461CBB873C97495AD468"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hold one or more evidentiary hearings at which interested members of the public may appear and be heard and present testimony, including expert testimony, in accordance with the rules of the Court; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CCF9A63852E4C7EA458F05881B0DCCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider other submissions and comments by the public, including proposals for redistricting plans to cover the entire State or any portion of the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36D769587564715BCB74F1D96B91E3A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of special master</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To assist in the development and publication of a redistricting plan for a State under this section, the Court may appoint a special master to make recommendations to the Court on possible plans for the State.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60255A30B9C94623B54E3E68F20A3D9D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Publication of plan</header><paragraph id="H1A4FAC2A22354DFE90C72833776B5081"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public availability of initial plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon completing the development of one or more initial redistricting plans, the Court shall make the plans available to the public at no cost, and shall also make available the underlying data used by the Court to develop the plans and a written evaluation of the plans against external metrics (as described in section 313(e)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEE4FC7CC4A04B36991F60721A81E217"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication of final plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At any time after the expiration of the 14-day period which begins on the date the Court makes the plans available to the public under paragraph (1), and taking into consideration any submissions and comments by the public which are received during such period, the Court shall develop and publish the final redistricting plan for the State.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF660BF7872F94D99A19211B720B4E7A7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of interim plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the event that the Court is not able to develop and publish a final redistricting plan for the State with sufficient time for an upcoming election to proceed, the Court may develop and publish an interim redistricting plan which shall serve as the redistricting plan for the State until the Court develops and publishes a final plan in accordance with this section. Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit or otherwise affect the authority or discretion of the Court to develop and publish the final redistricting plan, including but not limited to the discretion to make any changes the Court deems necessary to an interim redistricting plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB59D02BA58BC4457A4F176822CC0542C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Triggering Events Described</header><text>The <quote>triggering events</quote> described in this subsection are as follows:</text><paragraph id="H37452907423545659AF314763CAF96CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The failure of the State to establish or designate a nonpartisan agency of the State legislature under section 314(a) prior to the expiration of the deadline set forth in section 314(a)(8).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3735B184CB34F75B8963BB1F07BA8DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The failure of the State to appoint a Select Committee on Redistricting under section 314(b) prior to the expiration of the deadline set forth in section 314(b)(4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E81B74C802B41049B5CC6536899AC00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The failure of the Select Committee on Redistricting to approve any selection pool under section 312 prior to the expiration of the deadline set forth for the approval of the second replacement selection pool in section 312(d)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD196DB68F6E0436F85F21840B99AB676"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The failure of the independent redistricting commission of the State to approve a final redistricting plan for the State prior to the expiration of the deadline set forth in section 313(f).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9A0936FD655C487EAA8D4E448D6497B5"><enum>322.</enum><header>Special rule for redistricting conducted under order of Federal court</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If a Federal court requires a State to conduct redistricting subsequent to an apportionment of Representatives in the State in order to comply with the Constitution or to enforce the Voting Rights Act of 1965, section 313 shall apply with respect to the redistricting, except that the court may revise any of the deadlines set forth in such section if the court determines that a revision is appropriate in order to provide for a timely enactment of a new redistricting plan for the State.</text></section></subtitle><subtitle id="HC0098C4610AE4DA886D5680859B82567"><enum>D</enum><header>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</header><section id="H08C9A5E1249948B5916EF6E4E0831E64"><enum>331.</enum><header>Payments to States for carrying out redistricting</header><subsection id="H5B724637112343FBB0AFF05F01CDABA3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of payments</header><text>Subject to subsections (c) and (d), not later than 30 days after a State receives a State apportionment notice, the Election Assistance Commission shall make a payment to the State in an amount equal to the product of—</text><paragraph id="H62AF36AFACE04D74A8A0655D9EBA1797"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of Representatives to which the State is entitled, as provided under the notice; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFBC48B0970B4C34819CE5DE2F57C5A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$150,000.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F031D0797164F1881C552E6B0288F24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A State shall use the payment made under this section to establish and operate the State’s independent redistricting commission, to implement the State redistricting plan, and to otherwise carry out congressional redistricting in the State.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4ACE2472305642B1BDD3C5E845D28AA1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No payment to states electing members at large</header><text>The Election Assistance Commission shall not make a payment under this section to any State which, under the apportionment notice, will elect all of its Representatives at large.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA228A60CB7204105A990983E62D90E80"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requiring Submission of Selection Pool as Condition of Payment</header><paragraph id="HA5752A4930064B92B1F9037073876C02"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2) and paragraph (3), the Election Assistance Commission may not make a payment to a State under this section until the State certifies to the Commission that the nonpartisan agency established or designated by a State under section 314(a) has, in accordance with section 312(b)(1), submitted a selection pool to the Select Committee on Redistricting for the State established under section 314(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H063541840BA64F8D8C381A91EB46C0F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception for States with existing commissions</header><text>In the case of a State which, pursuant to section 301(c), is exempt from the requirements of section 301(a), the Commission may not make a payment to the State under this section until the State certifies to the Commission that its redistricting commission meets the requirements of section 301(c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C1AD02B7C944437ADAFE5F805FF569A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for payments under this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H202E645CAEB54B4D89DB375F9B68EBB3"><enum>332.</enum><header>Civil enforcement</header><subsection id="HD0FAF6746CB1401EB49E5931D4E8825F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Civil Enforcement</header><paragraph id="H267C86D38C754E14960EC6EB424A4C71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Actions by Attorney General</header><text>The Attorney General may bring a civil action in an appropriate district court for such relief as may be appropriate to carry out this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56B22CC2060847D595566BB324306919"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of private right of action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any citizen of a State who is aggrieved by the failure of the State to meet the requirements of this Act may bring a civil action in the United States district court for the applicable venue for such relief as may be appropriate to remedy the failure. For purposes of this section, the <quote>applicable venue</quote> is the District of Columbia or the judicial district in which the capital of the State is located, as selected by the person who brings the civil action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H14619C983BAD4C17A03A56AC48BF31A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expedited Consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any action brought forth under this section, the following rules shall apply:</text><paragraph id="H0B18548B85F84C0F85B4E2AB5068960B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The action shall be filed in the district court of the United States for the District of Columbia or for the judicial district in which the capital of the State is located, as selected by the person bringing the action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0E12EFB268349D6BFD84917F51DBDF1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The action shall be heard by a 3-judge court convened pursuant to section 2284 of title 28, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C5A56C11A64471595396141CB6F7843"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The 3-judge court shall consolidate actions brought for relief under subsection (b)(1) with respect to the same State redistricting plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B26BEAE6F1B48EEBF47069768260610"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A copy of the complaint shall be delivered promptly to the Clerk of the House of Representatives and the Secretary of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD048A6B087144A6DA3439C1A52CDD41C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A final decision in the action shall be reviewable only by appeal directly to the Supreme Court of the United States. Such appeal shall be taken by the filing of a notice of appeal within 10 days, and the filing of a jurisdictional statement within 30 days, of the entry of the final decision.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64D28A50E25C4DF4BE93322CE861C5FF"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be the duty of the district court and the Supreme Court of the United States to advance on the docket and to expedite to the greatest possible extent the disposition of the action and appeal.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4B39DD3829B40478146F92038B904AB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Attorney’s Fees</header><text>In a civil action under this section, the court may allow the prevailing party (other than the United States) reasonable attorney fees, including litigation expenses, and costs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF534C37643494469801597BFAA0279BC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Relation to Other Laws</header><paragraph id="HE43F0C95D27F44AF9C188F9AF73EAAAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rights and remedies additional to other rights and remedies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rights and remedies established by this section are in addition to all other rights and remedies provided by law, and neither the rights and remedies established by this section nor any other provision of this Act shall supersede, restrict, or limit the application of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10301">52 U.S.C. 10301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5BAC151583E421DAB92CECEA18DE52A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Voting Rights Act of 1965</header><text>Nothing in this Act authorizes or requires conduct that is prohibited by the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10301">52 U.S.C. 10301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H065CD499A10646E7ABA8D694C1B04970"><enum>333.</enum><header>State apportionment notice defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title, the <quote>State apportionment notice</quote> means, with respect to a State, the notice sent to the State from the Clerk of the House of Representatives under section 22(b) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial censuses and to provide for an apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(b)</external-xref>), of the number of Representatives to which the State is entitled.</text></section><section id="H9D6C3D7A6C8E4C9DB5BCA12D9161D467"><enum>334.</enum><header>Special rules for redistricting pursuant to 2020 decennial census</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, in the case of congressional redistricting conducted by a State pursuant to the 2020 decennial census, the following shall apply:</text><paragraph id="H390EBC616B114028B853DBFBE988D3A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The independent redistricting commission of the State shall enact the congressional redistricting plan for the State not later than January 15, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2411CD00F66A459BA216BDA016A8F80D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The State may waive or modify any of the deadlines described in subtitle B if the State determines that waiving or modifying the deadline is appropriate to ensure that the State meets the deadline described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94D8EF6EDFF641AC9F33F1B1EA9CAB75"><enum>(3)</enum><text>None of triggering events described in subsection (f) of section 321 (relating to the authority of a United States district court to develop and publish the plan) shall apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7462AEF533494B2E98CC34E40ECA3EE4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The failure of the State to enact the plan by the deadline described in paragraph (1) shall be treated as a triggering event under subsection (f) of section 321, and the United States district court for the applicable venue shall develop and publish the congressional redistricting plan for the State in accordance with such section.</text></paragraph></section></subtitle></title><title id="H3E1D13A7897B4E8CB5AFE7343A117544"><enum>IV</enum><header>General Provisions</header><section id="HF691BC01900A4676A760C1DB9E5EED37"><enum>401.</enum><header>No effect on elections for State and local office</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or in any amendment made by this Act may be construed to affect the manner in which a State carries out elections for State or local office, including the process by which a State establishes the districts used in such elections.</text></section><section id="H9CD612103A92462E90141EF7B457FDE1"><enum>402.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act or any amendment made by this Act, or the application of a provision of this Act or an amendment made by this Act to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, and the application of the provisions to any person or circumstance, shall not be affected by the holding.</text></section><section id="H4E0CAAF9C08F463D969CC4993F20A989"><enum>403.</enum><header>Effective date</header><subsection id="H220920476F054448B5A481DFC7FB6CA8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Redistricting</header><text>Title III and the amendments made by such title shall apply with respect to redistricting carried out pursuant to the decennial census conducted during 2020 or any succeeding decennial census.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC9FEEF42D5C493EAE783B79CF84B4AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ranked choice voting; use of multi-Member districts</header><text>Titles I and II and the amendments made by such titles shall apply with respect to elections for Federal office held in 2022 and each succeeding year.</text></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

