<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H18E1E1162EFA42B1AD9137AEB318A33E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>91 HR 10262 IH: Analysis and Improvement Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2024-11-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">2d Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 10262</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20241126">November 26, 2024</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001156">Mr. McHenry</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the financial regulators to carry out studies on the realized and potential benefits of artificial intelligence, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD5F89CE73A344312BBFB72383900453E" style="OLC"><section id="HF236805E0B25437593FF7E3BF306C107" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Analysis and Improvement Act of 2024</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AI Act of 2024</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H7BCE36B78E894A8E906EBF05453D10A4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on AI benefits and risks by banking regulators</header><subsection id="H3B55AA874AD54586BB97003A448477E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and the National Credit Union Administration Board shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and publish publicly, a report that examines—</text><paragraph id="HA98BDA8B347E4154A8EDD8B98DFC62C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">realized and potential benefits and risks of AI technology, including—</text><subparagraph id="HD18059BA30B74FD8B0A624A8A27C5E65"><enum>(A)</enum><text>banking institutions’ use of AI for customer service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H992DB95DB220485CBEE30BFC94EE0E94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>banking institutions’ use of AI in loan underwriting and servicing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07B3E8A2F9B148CDB3A892F836BD33F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">banking institutions’ use of AI in home valuation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA451DF8CF0604F3FA0C7CB9EAA25666A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>banking institutions’ use of AI to detect and deter fraud, money laundering, cybercrime, and other illicit activity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA61562F4EB31466E9F5257B862050DBF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the use of AI in debt collection, including foreclosures;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87ADE63D621141E8B48C89C63B2ED6DE"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">banking institutions’ use of AI for internal processes and compliance procedures, including for compliance with Federal fair lending laws; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F6D2677C27B46ACB1877AD492E9EC82"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how a variety of smaller banking institutions, including community banks, credit unions, rural depository institutions, minority depository institutions, and community development financial institutions, can leverage the benefits of AI technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23C2F04695DB47FFBFA8486E629240F8"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">banking institutions’ use of AI to mitigate bias and discrimination and increase banking services to historically underserved and underbanked consumers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53CED3D10677486BB3BF4480B70C2908"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">banking institutions’ use of AI to enhance cybersecurity risk management;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8D6D07D19E14FAC872743E16C72A331"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the use of AI to enhance competitiveness among banking institutions of all sizes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42F0F673E4E6401DBD0D86BBAF29B604"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI, including for the purposes described in subparagraphs (A) through (J), by nonbank financial technology firms; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94C89CAF1CBD482C878852DB3BE8FFEA"><enum>(L)</enum><text>any other use cases such agency heads determine appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A8BBE3AE54F440DA7C7D6BBAD3CE962"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">statues, regulations, and agency guidance, or the lack thereof, impacting the development and the use of AI by entities regulated by such agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CD0F8512EAD49678A2D1A7A99C466D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current use cases of AI by such agencies for supervision, and other areas where AI applications would be uniquely suited but are not currently being deployed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FC4916A5F704EBBA91586A9B2965EE7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any challenges such agencies have in leveraging AI and hiring and retaining staff with expertise in AI technology and potential solutions to overcome such challenges. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74B2B9D2CF884E83819E0A435BA6677C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include regulatory proposals and legislative recommendations that facilitate the responsible adoption of AI within the financial services industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF380CBE5BF3F4D79A814AA0C12E75284"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public input</header><text>The agency heads described under subsection (a) shall publish a request for information to collect public input to inform the drafting of the report required under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H7863D48D056A46949D0D2E572BC63283"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Banking institution defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>banking institution</term> means a depository institution (as defined in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act) and a State credit union or a Federal credit union (as such terms are defined, respectively, under section 101 of the Federal Credit Union Act).</text></subsection></section><section id="HCE5D24E9026642F6ABA0F81F0CBD105B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study on AI benefits and risks by the Securities and Exchange Commission</header><subsection id="H39E22E4FFAC34E6592776D0EF9FD5C84"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Securities and Exchange Commission shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and publish publicly, a report that examines—</text><paragraph id="H1CC039123091405880811E92210CD95C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>realized and potential benefits and risks of AI technology, including—</text><subparagraph id="H4C53002DD9FF4860824CB9ACF1097A04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>market participants’ use of AI for market research, examining the difference between public and private markets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43B8375963EE42479ED7ECA844396E7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>market participants’ use of AI for portfolio management;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCAB6E6D76704F48BB9D4D3215CFF9E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>exchanges’ use of AI for market surveillance, fraud detection, and order placements; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H348C0EBBF0C943FEAE1A89AE323F7AE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other use cases the Commission determines appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14E12CA57104B9EB511330C6688CDCB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">statues, regulations, and agency guidance, or the lack thereof, impacting development and use of AI;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H053BA740A3444F15ADB23A1D7FC35AA3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current use cases of AI by the Commission in supervision and other areas where AI applications would be uniquely suited but are not currently being deployed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39881350134E4DD4A418EE203FA01824"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any challenges the Commission has in leveraging AI and in hiring or retaining staff with expertise in AI technology and potential solutions to overcome such challenges.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H19C57336EA224D92BBD62D0088D0CDD8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include regulatory proposals and legislative recommendations that facilitate the responsible adoption of AI within the financial services industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2B91E81583F649C7926FDC007D6EAAAA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall—</text><paragraph id="H5A11FBA3ADD646A882252F8BC924E847"><enum>(1)</enum><text>publish a request for information to collect public input to inform the drafting of the report required under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC23744711ADB467CBB5461B4DA56AF1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with self-regulatory organizations to inform the drafting of the report under subsection (a). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE3B17D9D3E044BCF9B912973C49D0DE1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Study on AI benefits and risks by housing and mortgage regulators</header><subsection id="H91D3C326098145369DAFECFE633484D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, the Administrator of the Rural Housing Service of the Department of Agriculture, the Director of the Federal Housing Finance Agency, and the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and publish publicly, a report that examines—</text><paragraph id="H62614267F8594596B2136705E85376AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>realized and potential benefits and risks of AI technology, including—</text><subparagraph id="H9B52C9FD236A491987C52C3F6F0B611C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI to create efficiencies for homebuyers in evaluating, comparing, and obtaining a mortgage loan and in sustaining their homeownership over time;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7626ECC48C5140B1BE6354868167CA46"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI to enhance the accuracy, efficiency, and fairness of credit decisions, particularly for homebuyers in underserved communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89F3833143904304AD223F83DB13B929"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI to enhance the effectiveness of risk management and compliance within the housing finance system, including for compliance with Federal fair lending laws;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FA1AC79FD3B48E88CB4FEC31EDDC903"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the use of AI by real estate agents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19AB99F233834D56BD5030BC2CF17ED7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the use of AI in the marketing and outreach to retail customers regarding housing products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF01583862DAC4BC991B808B9BE8B22DD"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the use of AI in property management;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C21F27DA61F4E0BBD6414081F2CEFDA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the use of AI by landlords;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6D84ADF17AF46B69FE60ADBB1AEC6C7"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI by online housing platforms;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3638CAA786E4CBCAF1A67B6855FE4E4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the use of AI by mortgage servicers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09B11E4BDA08469992405385EE6353C7"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the use of AI in mortgage underwriting and servicing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46D75B9E3BC5411CA63D367615778AFB"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other use cases such agency heads determine appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H457A397ED89A403F9EA9331DCA0AA97F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">statues, regulations, and agency guidance, or the lack thereof, impacting development and implementation of AI;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF986AAF3B0E48A894256A5BF4C9CA70"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current use cases of AI by such agencies in supervision and other areas where AI applications would be uniquely suited but are not currently being deployed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H010D8D60A1C648A69727D18BF8920E64"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any challenges such agencies have in leveraging AI and hiring or retaining staff with expertise in AI technology and potential solutions to overcome such challenges. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4291DA8C0062473B994465825198B46B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a) shall include regulatory proposals and legislative recommendations that facilitate the responsible adoption of AI within the housing industry and the housing finance industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="H973C2AF6643A4D049D7B716B82EC3B18"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The agency heads described under subsection (a) shall publish a request for information to collect public input to inform the drafting of the report required under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H4DC618CA8103476CAF0598B960B74DEA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Study on AI benefits and risks in securing the U.S. financial system from national security threats</header><subsection id="H61FE821D1F0E43D78BB3F1FC9F4A0050"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and publish publicly, a report that examines—</text><paragraph id="H31EDAC52E506442392D15D75075A5098"><enum>(1)</enum><text>realized and potential benefits and risks of AI technology, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8725DFCD4DB146079071627A50CF268E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI by financial institutions (as defined in section 5312(a) of title 31, United States Code) to meet the institutions’ obligations under the Bank Secrecy Act and sanctions laws; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H981051FEA940400C8C165822E9B8F2D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of AI by financial institutions to protect against cybersecurity threats and to respond to cybersecurity attacks;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H639685D5B428410584F3561BA363B8A1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">statues, regulations, and agency guidance impacting development and use of AI by financial institutions to comply with the Bank Secrecy Act and sanctions laws;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49C4797DA84541A4BB321A09AD5977CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current use cases of AI by the Department of the Treasury and areas where AI applications would be uniquely suited but are not currently being deployed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE24C369760244C1C8462756554AE4D06"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any challenges the Department of Treasury has in leveraging AI and hiring or retaining staff with expertise in AI technology and potential solutions to overcome such challenges.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84E40EC2DBBC4FCB81B3DB41A9E4012B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a) shall include regulatory proposals and legislative recommendations that facilitate the responsible adoption of AI within the financial services industry.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBF2EDD19116246ECB37D520894315298"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public input</header><paragraph id="HECC9512966904570AAE6DCE2E3476DAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall publish a request for information to collect public input to inform the drafting of the report required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF70488A90654FAFAA186E4D3ADA506F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall consult with the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation Board, the Comptroller of the Currency, the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and the National Credit Union Administration Board to inform the drafting of the report required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0A92D469933346D5A700CB3BCD0AC56E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HAD72952FB239422998E7536CCEB0BD9B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>AI</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>AI</term> has the meaning given the term <term>artificial intelligence</term> under section 5002 of the National Artificial Intelligence Initiative Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/9401">15 U.S.C. 9401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C3479A0C7174126BAA457741A2ACAC2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bank Secrecy Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Bank Secrecy Act</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H791A40B0EBB645BBA28F1183CA780632"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 21 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1829b">12 U.S.C. 1829b</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBCB6A2A3D88493B80B9EBDCBF233D9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>chapter 2 of title I of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/91/508">Public Law 91–508</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1951">12 U.S.C. 1951 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1252E2DEA9934F75BEEB6AA7837F366D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

